<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="specsx.xsl"?>
<specs xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:space="preserve">
 <!-- Ny forenklet TEI version:
   Giv alle <sekt> ider i overensstemmelse med kanoniseret udgave [KN1]
     brug altid @id ifm. <refsekt>
   Brug <ex gen="-sks"> i alle TEI eksempler, 
     som kompletteres med <ex gen="-kn1"> eller billede fra sks.dk/SKS-B -->

 <kolofon>
  <titel>
   TEI usage for <tit>Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</tit>.
   Code book and documentation
  </titel>
  <forf>Karsten Kynde</forf>
  <kodning>XML</kodning>
  <copyright>Det Kongelige Biliotek &amp; forf.</copyright>
<!--
  <fil>http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.xml</fil>
  <pfil>http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.pdf</pfil>
-->
  <fil>teidoc.xml</fil>
  <htmlfil>teidoc.htm</htmlfil>
  <pfil>teidoc.pdf</pfil>
  <dato>20170224</dato>
  <vers>1.9</vers>
 </kolofon>

 <sekt id="1">
 <rubrik>Introduction</rubrik>
 <html:p>The following specification is written in the well known bottom up manner, the details being given in the start and the overview in the end. For many purposes it may prove most effective to read it backwards.</html:p>
   <html:p></html:p>
 <sekt id="1.1">
  <rubrik>Purpose and history</rubrik>
  <html:p><tit>Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</tit> (Søren Kierkegaards Writings, <tit>SKS</tit>) is a collected edition of Kierkegaards works and manuscripts, issued in a book version of 55 volumes, <reflit id="SKS-B"/> by the Søren Kierkegaard Research Centre of Copenhagen University thoughout the years 1997-2012.
  An electronic<refnote id="1"/> version at the website <tit>sks.dk</tit>, <reflit id="SKS-E"/> was published for the first time in 2007, latest updated in version 1.8.1 in 2014, see the reference list in <refapp id="lit"/>.
  Since 2013 <tit>sks.dk</tit> has been hosted by the Royal Library.</html:p>
  <html:p>In order to establish the texts constituting <tit>SKS</tit>, a digital text
format was conceived. The format should fulfill the following
requirements
  </html:p>
    <html:ol>
      <html:li>The texts should be convertible to any other feasible format.</html:li>
      <html:li>A relatively easy way to edit text versions should be
available.</html:li>
      <html:li>The format should be flexible towards new, yet unknown
features</html:li>
    </html:ol>
  <html:p>The first attempt in this direction was done in 1994 and termed <tit>Kierkegaard Normal Format, version 0</tit> (KN0).
    Later, in 1999 this format was transformed into a new <tit>Kierkegaard Normal Format, version 1</tit> <reflit id="KN1"/> that followed the international standard for the Extensible Mark-up Language <reflit id="XML"/>.</html:p>
   <html:p>The Royal Library has felt that a migration into the format of the Text Encoding Initiative, <reflit id="TEI"/>, would be an important step toward a lasting preservation of the text corpus. The present documentation covers this migration together with the initial rationales and objectives of the encoding. The section numbering follows that of <reflit id="KN1"/>.</html:p>
   <html:p>As the edition is now finished and published, the third requirement as mentioned above is no longer called for.
   The same counts for the second requrement, and as the need for this paper is no longer so much to instruct the <em>writing</em> but rather the <em>reading</em> of the text, most sections that elaborates on the former has been labeled <cit>obsolete</cit>.
   So, only the first requirement remains to reformulate the encoding into TEI terms.</html:p>
<sem on="TEI">Whenever the description mentions issues that is specific to the TEI way of things, it is marked by brackets like this one.</sem>
<html:p>Introductions to the art of digital text establishment and management in general are numerous and so are the reasons for choosing TEI/xml in particular, e.g. <reflit id="TEIlite"/>, others may be found at the TEI Consortium website, <html:a href="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/">www.tei-c.org</html:a>.</html:p>
   
  <html:p>Before, during and after this encoding process the text is established philologically as described in the <tit>Text Critical Guidelines</tit>, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> or <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/>, which shall hence not be repeated here.
Although the layout of <tit>SKS</tit> – book or electronic version – will be
mentioned several times in the description of the format, this paper is
not meant to define the layout as such, at least not in any detailed
manner, in stead <reflit id="Layout"/> should be consuleted in such matters.</html:p>
  <html:p> In the following text the <term>elements</term> of the format are described. The
elements are said to <term>mark</term> phenomenas of the copy text, e.g. the authors
underlining of a word. This means that the <term>tags</term> specific to the
respective element should be used when establishing the underlined
text digitally. This process is termed <term>encoding</term>. As mentioned,
the digital text is published in various versions.
This process is termed <term>rendering</term>. So the purpose of the following is
to describe the encoding of phenomena appearing from the copy text
of the author, to be rendered differently in various versions of <tit>SKS</tit>.</html:p>
  <note id="1">The terms <term>electronic</term> and <term>digital</term> are used with the same meaning with a slight bias towards <cit>digital</cit> when we talk about TEI and the text corpus as a whole.
    However, when mentioning <tit>SKS-E</tit>, <cit>electronic</cit> is preferred, acknowledging that <cit>-E</cit> abbreviates that word.</note>
 </sekt>

 <sekt id="1.2">
  <rubrik>Metalanguage and syntax</rubrik>
  <html:p>The varios <term>elements</term> are described in the sequel by a pseudo-formal syntax, to be shortly introduced:</html:p>
   <html:p>In one of the authors texts we find the following phrase:</html:p>

  <ex gen="-kn1">S<e name="o-">ø</e>mmer det sig nu for dette, der som saadant altid er <ant>foeminini generis,</ant> paa Grund af sin quindelige Natur at hengive sig til den St<e name="ae">æ</e>rkere</ex>

  <html:p>The words <ant>foeminini generis</ant> are, due to their Latin origin, set in
Roman (or Antiqua) type as opposed to the blackletter type as
customarily used for Danish books at the time of the author. In <tit>SKS</tit>
such words should be rendered in a distinct typeface as well, although we will refrain from using balckletters. In TEI
the words should be encoded</html:p>
  <ex gen="-sks">som saadant altid er <hi rendition="#ant">foeminini generis,</hi></ex>
   <html:p><tag>hi rendition="#ant"</tag> is an XML <term>tag</term> and <tag>/hi</tag> similarly an <term>end tag</term>. 
    <x>hi</x> is the <term>name</term> of the tag.
    The tag also have an <term>attribute</term>, with the <cite>name</cite> <x>rendition</x> and the <term>value</term> <x>"#ant"</x>.
The text between the tags is called the <term>content</term>.
     Together they constitutes an <term>element</term> with a fixed meaning, in this case: a Roman typeface text. 
     The syntax of the element is described in the
following way:</html:p>

   <html:blockquote>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>hi</name>
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#ant"</elem>
    </synx>
   </html:blockquote>
   
   <html:p>The blue color suggests that this is a clickable link to the formal description of the tag and the attribute, resp., in <reflit id="TEI"/>.
   If a text obeys the rules described there (which the <tit>SKS</tit> corpus does), it is said to be <term>valid</term> TEI.</html:p>

  <html:p>According to the TEI rules, <tag>hi</tag> may contain what is termed coherent text below (in sect. <refsekt id="2"/>), e.g text supplied by the editor. I.e. Roman text may be supplied and vice versa, supplied text may be typeset in Roman.
Only the tags must be parenthetically paired, e.g.</html:p>
  <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#ant"><supplied>Cap. IV</supplied></hi></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><ant><udg spec="supp">Cap. IV</udg></ant></ex>
  <html:p>or</html:p>
  <ex gen="-sks"><supplied><hi rendition="#ant">Cap. IV</hi></supplied></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><udg spec="supp"><ant>Cap. IV</ant></udg></ex>
  <html:p>but <em>not</em></html:p>
  <html:blockquote><fed>*</fed> <tag>hi rendition="#ant</tag><tag>supplied</tag><html:code>Cap. IV</html:code><tag>/hi</tag><tag>/supplied</tag></html:blockquote>

  <html:p>Elements may be empty, i.e. they relates to a point in the text rather
than a fraction of it, e.g. a page break in the original copy text, a
<term>correllation mark</term>.
In this case a special notation is used</html:p>
  <html:blockquote><tag>pb/</tag> meaning <tag>pb</tag><tag>/pb</tag></html:blockquote>
   
   <html:p>Now, consider this more complex syntax:</html:p>
  <synx>
    <elem><name>note</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="author"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="subnote"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="">place</attr>="bottom <sepa>|</sepa> margin"</elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><elem><name>seg</name>
      type="refMarker"</elem>
    <meta>digit <sepa>|</sepa> litra</meta>
    <tag>/seg</tag><sepa>]</sepa>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><elem><name>p</name></elem><sepa>}</sepa>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/note</tag>
  </synx>
  <html:p>This element marks the authors note.
    In this respect its <x>type</x> attribute should have the value <x>"author"</x> an it <em>may</em> also have a <tag>subtype</tag> attribute valued <x>"subnote"</x> designating this note as a note for a note.
    The <term>meta characters</term> [ and ] means that the bracketed attribute may be omittet.
    A <x>place</x> attribute <em>should</em> be supplied at its value <em>should</em> be either <x>"bottom"</x> or <x>"margin"</x>, the bar, |, meaning <cit>or</cit>.<refnote id="2"/>
  </html:p>
   <html:p>The content of the <tag>note</tag> element may include a reference marker, encoded by a <tag>seg</tag> element. Italics is used for the informal information that the content should be either a digit <cit>or</cit> a litra.
   As a contrast, all typewriter typefaced text is to be understood literarily.</html:p>
  <html:p>After this preliminary stuff, the note may include any number of paragraphs, encoded by <tag>p</tag> elements, { and } meaning that the braced element may be repeated.
   Paragraphs are described elsewhere, and this is why we will feel free to leave out the end tag as well as any attributes for the <tag>p</tag> tag. This is a part of the pseudo-formalness.</html:p>
    <note id="2">These rules apply for the <tit>SKS</tit> encoding practice, not for TEI validity as such.</note>

  <html:p>Finally the possibility of forming <term>XML-comments</term> should be
mentioned. These are comments at encoding level, i.e. they are part of but
do not affect the TEI encoding. A comment must not contain a double hyphen: <x>--</x>. Any text until <x>--></x>
is to be skipped.</html:p>
  <ex gen="-sks"> at Guds Majestæt er ikke<!--PAP har 'ikke er'--> degraderet.</ex>
 </sekt>
 </sekt>

 <sekt id="2">
 <rubrik>Coherent text</rubrik>

 <sem>By <term>coherent text</term> is understood ordinary <term>running text</term> including any number of elements of type <term>typographical signals</term>, <term>refering terms</term> <term>internal references</term> or <term>external references</term>.</sem>

 <sekt id="2.1">
 <rubrik>Running text</rubrik>

 <sem>Ordinary <term>running text</term> is text that does not contain tags. The character set used for <tit>SKS</tit> is the standard for xml encoded files, UTF-8, see <reflit id="Unicode"/>.</sem>

 <sem><term>Space</term>, <term>tabulation</term>, <term>new line</term> and <term>form feed</term> are all mentioned as white space. The specific value of these characters as well as their number in excess of 1 has no importance for the interpretation.</sem>

  <sekt id="2.1.1">
   <rubrik>Danish national characters, international diacritics,and other characters</rubrik>
   <sem>This and following chapters have mainly been relevant for the establishing of <tit>SKS</tit>. Readers interessted in thees details are kindly referred to the KN1 version of this document, <reflit id="KN1"/>.</sem>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.1.2">
   <rubrik>Greek</rubrik>
   <sem>Obsolete.</sem>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.1.3">
   <rubrik>Hebrew</rubrik>   
   <sem>Obsolete.</sem>

     <sekt id="2.1.3.1">
       <rubrik>On the sequence of hebrew text</rubrik>
       <sem>Hebrew words are read right to left and is coded in reading sequence in accordance with Unicode standard, i.e. hebrew text is placed in the file starting with the rightmost letter, e.g. (here illustrated by using a character entity coding with <x>&amp;h.al;</x> = &#x05d0; (aleph), <x>&amp;h.b;</x> = &#x05d1; (beth), <x>&amp;h.d;</x> = &#x05d3; (daleth), etc., in order to emphasise the sequence of the Hebrew letter encoding)</sem>
   <ex>
         <e name="h.al">א</e><e name="h.d">ד</e><e name="h.n">נ</e><e name="h.j">י</e>, hebr. ʼAdonáj, egl. min Herre
       </ex>
       <sem>In contrast, the whole words are placed left to right as they are found in the base-text. To ensure this sequence, a <term>left-to-right-mark</term>, <x>&amp;lrm;</x> = <x>&amp;#x200e;</x>, is placed between the word and the following white space, e.g.</sem>
   <ex>
         <e name="h.al">א</e><e name="h.aa">ָ</e><e name="h.b.">בּ</e><e name="h.aa">ָ</e><e name="h.al">א</e><e name="lrm">‎</e>   
         <e name="h.b">ב</e><e name="h.a">ַ</e><e name="h.r">ר</e> (bar abba), en faders søn
       </ex>
       <sem><x>&amp;lrm;</x> is put in Hebrew text immediately before a character which could be interpreted as belonging to the Hebrew content, i.e. white space, numbers, and square brackets, see <reflit id="Unicode"/>, 3.12 on <term>bidirectional behavior</term>.</sem>
       <sem>There are a number of reasons for this coding practice. It would seem consequent if the letters within the words were coded left to right too. When the Unicode standard is chosen here, it is due to certain internet browsers which show difficulties decoding Hebrew in this form, even with the reading direction specified in style sheets.
        Such as to which consonant a given vowel should belong.
        Not keeping to the standard when it comes to the words is due to  line breaking issues:
        Longer passages of Hebrew text are no doubt expected to start at the rightmost end of one line, continuing on the next;
        this is not true, however, for the short samples as they are found in the authors texts, and it is in our interpretation not the way the author understands them himself;
        they are furthermore often mentioned, outside any context of a sentence. 
        Word concordances and text critical apparatus may also come into troubles with words not appearing in the usual sequence.</sem>
     </sekt>
  </sekt>
  <sekt id="2.1.4">
   <rubrik>Exceptions for files on the web</rubrik>
   <sem>Obsolete.</sem>
  </sekt>
 </sekt>

 <sekt id="2.2">
  <rubrik>Empty elements</rubrik>
  <sem>Obsolete.</sem>
 </sekt>

 <sekt id="2.3">
 <rubrik>Typographical signals</rubrik>

  <sem>By typographical signals is understood <term>letterspacing</term>, <term>bold</term>, <term>Roman</term>, <term>italics</term>, <term>German</term>, <term>other typesetting</term>, <term>font size</term>, <term>superscipt</term>,
<term>subscript</term>, <term>leaders</term> and <term>editorial intervention</term>.</sem>
 <sem>Note that the practice of <tit>SKS</tit> is to include any punctuation marks following a highlighted word or phrase in the highlightning, and also that tags must be placed parenthetically if more than one applies (see <refsekt id="1.2"/>).</sem>
 <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#ant"><hi rendition="#fed">Lectori benevolo!</hi></hi></ex>
 <ex gen="-kn1"><ant><fed>Lectori benevolo!</fed></ant></ex>
 <sem on="TEI">Also note that <tit>SKS</tit> makes no claim for the reasons concerning the individual highlightning. Hence the TEI tag <tag>hi</tag> has been chosen in favour of e.g. <tag>emph</tag> for, say, underlined words, although they in most cases express emphasis; this interpretation is, however, entirely up to the reader.
 Especially for the so called Latin hand writing that the author uses for Latin language text, it would seem appropriate to use the <tag>foreign lang="la"</tag> coding (<reflit id="TEI"/> 3.3.2.1). Latin hand is not solely a language marker though. Throughout the period of »The Journal« Kierkegaard increasingly uses Latin hand for decoration purposes or to mark a special retrospective kind of entries about his work (see <refsekt id="3.6.1"/>, last example).</sem>
  <sem on="TEI">The technique followed for highlighting elements <refsekt id="2.3.1"/>-<refsekt id="2.3.9"/> below, for legend texts <refsekt id="2.5.2"/> and elsewhere, is to use the <x>rendition</x> attribute as at pointer to a <tag>rendition</tag> element in the <tag>encodingDesc</tag> part of the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, defining the copy-text appearance in terms of the <tit>cascading style sheets</tit> notation in a »very similar way to the class attribute defined for XHTML but with the important distinction that its function is to describe the appearance of the source text, not necessarily to determine how that text should be presented on screen or paper« (<reflit id="TEI"/> app. D, rendition), also see <reflit id="TEI"/> 2.3.4.1. and the examples below.
    <html:br/><html:br/>
    We can not, however, completely ignore how the text is eventually going to be rendered <html:em>by <tit>SKS</tit></html:em> »on screen or paper«. In these cases we take the liberty to use the competing attribute <x>rend</x> for this purpose, i.e. to modify or clarify the rendition of the copy-text, please see <refsekt id="2.3.1"/> and <refsekt id="2.3.4"/> below for examples.</sem>

  <sekt id="2.3.1">
  <rubrik>Spaced out, underlined</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>hi</name>    
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>
     = "#spa"</elem>
     <html:br/>
     <tag>hi    
     rendition
     = "#und"</tag>
    </synx>
   <sem>In printed works, marks words that are spaced out, i.e. they
are highlighted by an increased spacing of the individual letters of the
words. In manuscripts similar words are underlined. <tit>SKS</tit> unconditionally renders this element in italics, giving, however, the original rendering of the copy-text source by the following  statement in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of a printed text:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="spa" scheme="css"</elem><x>letter-spacing: 0.2em</x><tag>/rendition</tag></synx>
   <sem>Similarly, in a manuscript:</sem>
   <synx><elem>rendition
 xml:id="und" scheme="css"</elem><x>text-decoration: underline</x><tag>/rendition</tag></synx>
   <sem/>
  <ex gen="-sks">
   istedenfor hines <hi rendition="#spa">religieuse</hi> Characteer et <hi rendition="#spa">moralsk</hi> Tilsnit,
  </ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">
   istedenfor hines <spa>religieuse</spa> Characteer et <spa>moralsk</spa> Tilsnit,
  </ex>
  <sem>On rare occasions, where the text alludes to a pun on the word 'space', the spacing should be carried out as well; in this case, as explained above <refsekt id="2.3"/> we hedge our bets by specifying the attribute <x>rend="spa"</x> (please note the absence of a #).</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks">Mener man at kunne fastholde denne Inddeling, da er det fordi man <hi rendition="#spa" rend="spa">spatierer</hi> et Moment,</ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">
   Mener man at kunne fastholde denne Inddeling, da er det fordi man <spa gen="sic">spatierer</spa> et Moment,
  </ex>
  <sem>In the same way it may appear that a handwritten underlining  necessarily should be rendered so.
   Here is Kierkegaards young maidens introduction to the art of book printing:</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks">
   <p rendition="#xlang">
    <hi rendition="#und" rend="und">Vor</hi> 
    <hi rendition="#und" rend="und">egen</hi> 
    <hi rendition="#und" rend="und">lille</hi> 
    <hi rendition="#und" rend="und">Regine</hi>
   </p>
   <p>En saadan Streg under Ordet tjener til Efterretning for Sætteren om, at han skal spatiere det paagjeldende Ord. At spatiere betyder, at trække Ordene ud fra hinanden. Naar jeg derfor spatierer de ovenfor skrevne Ord, saa tænker jeg, at jeg skal trække dem <hi rendition="#und" rend="spa">saa langt ud,</hi> at en Sætter formodentlig vilde tabe Taalmodigheden, da han efter al Sandsynlighed ikke vilde komme til at sætte mere i sit Liv.</p>
  </ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">
     <lin ryk="xlang"><spa gen="und">Vor</spa> <spa gen="und">egen</spa> <spa gen="und">lille</spa> <spa gen="und">Regine</spa></lin>
     <lin>En saadan Streg under Ordet tjener til Efterretning for Sætteren om, at han skal spatiere det paagjeldende Ord. At spatiere betyder, at trække Ordene ud fra hinanden. Naar jeg derfor spatierer de ovenfor skrevne Ord, saa tænker jeg, at jeg skal trække dem <spa gen="sic">saa langt ud,</spa> at en Sætter formodentlig vilde tabe Taalmodigheden, da han efter al Sandsynlighed ikke vilde komme til at sætte mere i sit Liv.</lin>
  </ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.2">
  <rubrik>Italics</rubrik>
    <synx><elem><name>hi</name>
  <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr> =
#ita
"</elem></synx>
    

   <sem>Marks in the commentary volumes, highlighting by means of
italics, corresponding to the following statement in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of the document:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="ita" scheme="css"</elem><x>font-style: italic</x><tag>/rendition</tag></synx>
  </sekt>
  
  <sekt id="2.3.3">
   <rubrik>Curved underlining</rubrik>
    <synx><elem><name>hi</name>
  <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr> =
#cun
"</elem></synx>
    

   <sem>Marks in manuscripts a curve under a heading, typically a number. Rendered in <tit>SKS-B</tit> as a curved, in <tit>SKS-E</tit> a straight underlining, corresponding to the following statement in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of the document:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="cun" scheme="css"</elem><x>text-decoration: underline</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   <tag>!--curved underlining--</tag></synx>
   <sem/>
   <ex gen="-sks">
     <p rendition="#cen">
       <hi rendition="#ant">Rapport.</hi>    
       <hi rendition="#spa">Resultat</hi>
     </p>
     <p rendition="#cen">
       <hi rendition="#cun">1</hi>
     </p>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
    <lin ryk="cen"><ant>Rapport.</ant><e name="blank"> </e><e name="blank"> </e><e name="blank"> </e><e name="blank"> </e><spa>Resultat</spa></lin>
    <lin ryk="cen"><bue>1</bue></lin>
</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.4">
  <rubrik>Bold, double underline</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>hi</name>
  <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr> = "#bol"</elem>
     <html:br/>
     <tag>hi
       rendition = "#dun"</tag>
    </synx>
    
  <sem>In the printed works, marks highlighting by means of bold and
in the manuscripts double underlining. <tit>SKS</tit> unconditionally renders this element in bold, giving, however, the original rendering of the copy-text source by the following statement in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of a printed text:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="bol" scheme="css"</elem><x>font-weight: bold</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   </synx>
   <sem>and in a manuscript:</sem>
   <synx><elem>rendition
 xml:id="dun" scheme="css"</elem><x>border-bottom-style: double</x><tag>/rendition</tag></synx>
   <sem/>
  <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#bol">Efterskrift</hi> for de Læsere, der muligen kunne have Skade af at læse Forordet:</ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1"><fed>Efterskrift</fed> for de L<e name="ae">æ</e>sere, der muligen kunne have Skade af at l<e name="ae">æ</e>se Forordet:</ex>
   <sem>As elsewhere (<refsekt id="2.3.1"/>), it may appear that such a handwritten double underlining necessarily should be rendered so, e.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">(saaledes skrev Du: fortal<hi rendition="#dun" rend="dun">d</hi>t – Du veed formodl. god Beskeed om, hvad disse to Streger har at betyde.)</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.5">
  <rubrik>Roman, Latin hand</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>hi</name>
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#ant"</elem>
     <html:br/>
     <tag>hi
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#lat"</tag>
    </synx>
    
  <sem>In the printed works, marks Latin words and phrases set in a
Roman (antiqua) typeface rather than the blackletter type that was
usual at the time of the author. In the manuscripts the element
designates similar passages written in Latin hand (or <s.k.>Italian script</s.k.>).
<tit>SKS</tit> renders this element in a destinct sans serif typeface, in SKS-B Optima. In the <tag>teiHeader</tag> the following free description of the source is given for a printed text:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="ant" scheme="free"</elem><x>antiqua typeface, in SKS rendered sans-serif</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   </synx>
   <sem>and for a manuscript:</sem>
   <synx><elem>rendition
 xml:id="lat" scheme="free"</elem><x>latin hand, in SKS rendered sans-serif</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   </synx>
  <sem>E.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Naar jeg ikke er <hi rendition="#lat">reus voti</hi> saa vil Intet gaae for mig.</ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">Naar jeg ikke er <ant>reus voti</ant> saa vil Intet gaae for mig.</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.6">
  <rubrik>German</rubrik>
    <synx><elem><name>foreign</name>
<attr class="global">xml:lang</attr> = "de"</elem></synx>
    
  <sem>In the original KN1 version, this encoding was designed and used for the German translation, where it marks words and phrases that were written in German language by SK and thus not actually translated. The German translation renders the element in a destinct typeface.</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks">med sin fine, underligt skrattende Stemme [...] udbrød han: <foreign xml:lang="de">Ja! Was ist der
Mensch?</foreign> En Clarinet, svarede jeg</ex>
  <ex lang="dt" gen="-kn1">mit seiner d<e name="u..">ü</e>nnen, sonderbar schnarrenden Stimme [...] rief er aus: <dt>Ja! Was ist der
Mensch?</dt> Eine Klarinette, antwortete ich</ex>
  <sem>Also the English translation have made use of this encoding to facillitate hyphenation, place see <reflit id="KN1"/> for details.</sem>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.7">
  <rubrik>Other typographics</rubrik>
    <synx><elem><name>hi</name>
  <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr> =
#initTyp
"</elem>
     <html:br/>
     <tag>hi
       rendition = #schwTyp
"</tag>
     <html:br/>
     <tag>hi
       rendition = #gotTyp
"</tag>
    <html:br/>
     <tag>hi
       rendition = #capiTyp
"</tag></synx>
    
  <sem>Marks <term>initial letters</term> and rarely used typografical variants like <term>Schwabacher</term>, <term>Gothic</term>, and others. 
   The <tag>teiHeader</tag> declares:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="initTyp" scheme="css"</elem><x>font-size: 200%</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
    <tag>!--Initial letter--</tag>
   <html:br/>
    <elem>rendition
 xml:id="schwTyp" scheme="free"</elem><x>Schwabacher, in SKS rendered bold</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <elem>rendition
 xml:id="gotTyp" scheme="free"</elem><x>Gothic typeface</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
    <html:br/>
    <elem>rendition
 xml:id="capiTyp" scheme="free"</elem><x>Some spectacular type setting, in SKS rendered in small caps</x><tag>/rendition</tag></synx> 
   <sem>E.g.</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#initTyp">F</hi>orord bryder ingen Trætte</ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1"><typ art="init">F</typ>orord bryder ingen Tr<e name="ae">æ</e>tte</ex>
   <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#capiTyp">Victor Eremita</hi></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><typ art="capi">Victor Eremita</typ></ex>
  <sem><tit>SKS</tit> renders Gothic like normal text.</sem>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.8">
  <rubrik>Font size and line height</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>hi</name>
    <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>
    = "#size* #linHeight*"
   </elem>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks larger or smaller font or line height.
    The number following the <x>#size</x> value – spanning from -3 to 6 – gives the font size relative to the ordinary size of the context, and raises one for each clearly discernable increase in size, approximately 20%.
    The number following the <x>#linHeight</x> value gives the line height, roughly corresponding to the following declarations in the <tag>teiHeader</tag>:</sem>
   <synx>
    <elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="size-1" scheme="css"</elem><x>font-size: 83%</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <elem>rendition
 xml:id="size1" scheme="css"</elem><x>font-size: 120%</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   <html:br/>
   ...
   <html:br/>
   <elem>rendition
 xml:id="lineHeight1" scheme="css"</elem><x>line-height:150%</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <elem>rendition
 xml:id="lineHeight2" scheme="css"</elem><x>line-height:200%</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   </synx>
   <sem>In the following example, the line heigh is increased and retained thoughout the chapter including the quote which should be in a smaller font:</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks">
   <p><hi rendition="#size0 #lineHight1">Og naar han nu atter vender tilbage til mig, halv undseelig over, om jeg skulde have mærket Noget, og da efter en lille Pause vemodig udbryder:</hi></p>
    <p rendition="#lang"><hi rendition="#size-1 #lineHight2">Es blies ein Jäger wohl in sein Horn,</hi></p>
    <p rendition="#lang"><hi rendition="#size-1 #lineHight2">Wohl in sein Horn,</hi></p>
    <p rendition="#lang"><hi rendition="#size-1 #lineHight2">Und alles was er blies das war verlorn –</hi></p>
    <p><hi rendition="#size0 #lineHight1">saa er han virkelig nær ved at forstemme mig.</hi></p>
  </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
<lin><gra str="0" skyd="+1">Og naar han nu atter vender tilbage til mig, halv undseelig over, om jeg skulde have m<e name="ae">æ</e>rket Noget, og da efter en lille Pause vemodig udbryder:</gra></lin>
    <lin ryk="lang"><gra str="-1" skyd="+1">Es blies ein J<e name="a..">ä</e>ger wohl in sein Horn,</gra></lin>
    <lin ryk="lang"><gra str="-1" skyd="+1">Wohl in sein Horn,</gra></lin>
    <lin ryk="lang"><gra str="-1" skyd="+1">Und alles was er blies das war verlorn <e name="streg">–</e></gra></lin>
    <lin><gra str="0" skyd="+1">saa er han virkelig n<e name="ae">æ</e>r ved at forstemme mig.</gra></lin>
   </ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.9">
  <rubrik>Superscript and subscript, fractions or dates</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>hi</name>
    <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>
    = "#sup"
   </elem>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>hi
    rendition
    = "#sub"
   </tag>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks a slightly smaller text elevated or lowered,
    corresponding to the following declarations in the <tag>teiHeader</tag>:</sem>
   <synx><elem><name>rendition</name>
 xml:id="sup" scheme="css"</elem><x>vertical-align: super; font-size:      80%;</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
    <html:br/>
   <elem>rendition
 xml:id="sub" scheme="css"</elem><x>vertical-align: sub; font-size: 80%;</x><tag>/rendition</tag>
   </synx>
   <sem/>
   <sem></sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Et probat Raad for uvittige Forfattere, det koster 5<hi rendition="#sup">rd</hi></ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">Et probat Raad for uvittige Forfattere, det koster 5<hoj>rd</hoj></ex>


   <sem>Fractions are represented in the W3C Mathematical Markup Language <reflit id="MathML"/>
    .</sem>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>formula</name>
     notation="mathml"
     xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag><html:a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/chapter2.html#interf.toplevel">m:math</html:a></tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag><html:a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/chapter3.html#presm.mfrac">mfrac</html:a>
   <sepa>[</sepa><html:a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/chapter3.html#id.3.3.2.2">bevelled</html:a>="true"<sepa>]</sepa></tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<tag><html:a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/chapter3.html#presm.mi">mi</html:a></tag>
  <meta>numerator</meta>
   <tag>/m:mi</tag>
   <tag>mi</tag>
  </synx>
  <meta>denominator</meta>
  <synx>
   <tag>/m:mi</tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/m:mfrac</tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/m:math</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/formula</tag>
  </synx>
   <sem>Usually fractions are appearing like so-called vulgar fractions, i.e. slightly raised or lowered with a slash in between; in this case the attribute <x>bevelled="true"</x>.
    The most frequent fractions are defined as Unicode characters, se <refsekt id="2.1.1"/>, e.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">1 As først <formula xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" notation="mathml"><m:math><m:mfrac bevelled="true"><m:mi>1</m:mi><m:mi>10</m:mi></m:mfrac></m:math></formula> Drachme, dernæst <formula xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" notation="mathml"><m:math><m:mfrac bevelled="true"><m:mi>1</m:mi><m:mi>16</m:mi></m:mfrac></m:math></formula>. En Kodrans ¼ As. λεπτος = ½ Kodrans.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">1 As først <vulg><hoj>1</hoj><lav>10</lav></vulg> Drachme, dernæst <vulg><hoj>1</hoj><lav>16</lav></vulg>. En Kodrans ¼ As. λεπτος = ½ Kodrans.</ex>

   <sem>Dates positioned around a slash or bar is handled like fractions.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
    <date when="18340310">d <formula xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" notation="mathml">
                     <m:math>
                        <m:mfrac>
                           <m:mi>10</m:mi>
                           <m:mi>3</m:mi>
                        </m:mfrac>
                     </m:math>
                  </formula> 34.</date>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><dag dat="18340310">d <stang><hoj>10</hoj><lav>3 </lav></stang> 34.</dag></ex>
   <sem/>
   <ex gen="-sks">
    <hi rendition="#spa">Digesmutterne</hi> (<hi rendition="#ant">Saxicola</hi>) i <date when="18500400">April</date>. <hi rendition="#ant">S. oenanthe</hi> 
               <date when="18500405">
                  <formula xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" notation="mathml">
                     <m:math>
                        <m:mfrac bevelled="true">
                           <m:mi>5</m:mi>
                           <m:mi>4</m:mi>
                        </m:mfrac>
                     </m:math>
                  </formula>
               </date> 50; <hi rendition="#ant">S. rubetra</hi> 
               <date when="18500400">
                  <formula xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" notation="mathml">
                     <m:math>
                        <m:mfrac>
                           <m:mi>sidst</m:mi>
                           <m:mi>4.</m:mi>
                        </m:mfrac>
                     </m:math>
                  </formula>
               </date>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><spa>Digesmutterne</spa> (<ant>Saxicola</ant>) i <dag dat="18500400">April</dag>. <ant>S. oenanthe</ant> <dag dat="18500405"><vulg>
     <hoj>5</hoj><lav>4</lav></vulg></dag> 50; <ant>S. rubetra</ant> <dag dat="18500400"><stang><hoj>sidst</hoj><lav>4.</lav></stang></dag></ex>


  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.10">
  <rubrik>Leaders</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>seg</name>
    <attr class="typed">type</attr>
    = "leaders"
   </elem>
  </synx>
  <sem>Marks leaders as used in a table of contents:</sem>
  <ex gen="-sks">
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>4.</cell>
     <cell>Skyggerids <seg type="leaders"/></cell>
     <cell><ref type="page" target="#s159" n="163">159</ref>.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">
   <blok ryk="tab">
   <lin>
     <tab>4.</tab>
     <tab>Skyggerids <udpkt/></tab>
     <tab><refs id="159">163</refs>.</tab>
    </lin>
   </blok>
  </ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.11">
   <rubrik>Editorial intervention</rubrik>
   <synx>

   </synx>
   <sem>Marks different sorts of editorial intervention in the text. SKS renders these with diacritical marks.</sem>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.1">
    <rubrik>Doubtful reading</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>unclear</name></elem>
    </synx>
    <sem>marks text in manuscripts whose
reading is uncertain. <tit>SKS</tit> renders it in angle brackets. Completely
illegible letters are rendered with centered dots,
one for each letter as far as distinguishable.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
     hvor skulde <unclear>En</unclear> ogsaa have ahnet<unclear>,</unclear> at en saadan ung Pige kunde gaae og gjemme saadanne Ideer. 
	Men saaledes var <unclear>··</unclear> Pige,
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">hvor skulde <udg spec="tvivl">En</udg> ogsaa have ahnet<udg spec="tvivl">,</udg> at en saadan ung Pige kunde gaae og gjemme saadanne Ideer. 
	Men saaledes var <udg spec="tvivl"><e name="u">·</e><e name="u">·</e></udg> Pige,</ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.2">
   <rubrik>Supplied text</rubrik>
    <!--synx import="supplied"/-->
    <synx>
     <elem><name>supplied</name></elem>
    </synx>
    
    <sem>Signifies in manuscripts text supplied by the editor in order to render the text meaningful. <tit>SKS</tit> renders it in square brackets.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">Situationen er humoristisk nok, en gl.
	China<supplied>-Ca</supplied>ptain (74 Aar gl.) taler med mig paa den Maade derom.</ex>
    <!--html:img src="ex2.3.11.2.a.png"/-->
    <ex gen="-kn1">Situationen er humoristisk nok, en gl.
	China<udg spec="supp">-Ca</udg>ptain (74 Aar gl.) taler med mig paa den Maade derom.</ex>
    <sem>Tagging with <tag>supplied</tag> takes place only within journals, papers, or similar manuscript material, cf. <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 8.4. In printed works, supplied texts are introduced with a text critical note.</sem>
    <sem>OBS. Text supplied by the editor of <tit>SKS</tit> should not be confused with text supplied in a similar way by preceding editors, e.g. Barfod. As Barfods EP (see <refsekt id="2.5.3"/>), occasionally takes the place of copy-text, such supplements should be encoded and rendered literally.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">at man i Begyndelsen lader Børnene – paa et af de Spørgsmaal, som [gjøres] ethvert Barn i det korte Indbegreb af Viden, der bibringes dem: »hvad skal Barnet have?« – [svare]: »Da-Da«;</ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">
     at man i Begyndelsen lader Børnene – paa et af de Spørgsmaal, som [gjøres] ethvert Barn i det korte <kom id="cc-99">Indbegreb</kom> af Viden, der bibringes dem: »hvad skal Barnet have?« – [svare]: »<kom id="cc-166">Da-Da</kom>«;
    </ex>
    <!--html:img src="ex2.3.11.2.b.png"/-->
    <sem>Free style comments from Barfod are treated in <refsekt id="2.3.12"/>.</sem>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.3">
   <rubrik>Cancelled tekst</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>del</name></elem>
    </synx>
    <sem>Marks text in mss. that the author has deleted but
which the editor nevertheless places in the context (as opposed to
annotated cancellations cf. <refsekt id="2.5.2.2"/>). <tit>SKS</tit> renders it in top open square
brackets (<html:cite>foot</html:cite> or <html:cite>floor</html:cite> brackets). If the
cancellation stretches over several paragraphs, the tags must be
repeated at the entry and exit of each. In <tit>SKS-B</tit> the brackets will
normally be set only at the very beginning and end of the
cancellation.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
     <p rendition="#ind">
      <del>Hver Mandag mell. 9-10 Formiddag har hun mødt mig. Jeg har intet Skridt gjort derfor. Hun veed, hvilken Vei jeg pleier at gaae, jeg veed, hvad <app>
       <lem>Vei hun <witDetail wit="#Ms">s. 42-43 udrevet if. B-fort.</witDetail>
       </lem></app>
      </del>
     </p>
     <p>
      <pb xml:id="s44" n="44"/>
       <del>jeg <unclear>faar</unclear> dog gjort Alt saaledes, at hun ikke ahner, [...]</del>
     </p>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">
     <lin ryk="ind"><udg spec="slet">Hver Mandag mell. 9-10 Formiddag har hun m<e name="o-">ø</e>dt mig. Jeg har intet Skridt gjort derfor. Hun veed, hvilken Vei jeg pleier at gaae, jeg veed, hvad <tn>Vei hun <udg spec="fri" txt="s. 42-43 udrevet if. B-fort."/></tn></udg></lin>
     <lin><kor id="44"/><udg spec="slet">jeg <udg spec="tvivl">faar</udg> dog gjort Alt saaledes, at hun ikke ahner, [...]</udg></lin>
    </ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.4">
   <rubrik>Variant text</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>add</name>
      <attr class="transcriptional">status</attr>="variant"
     </elem>
    </synx>
    <sem>Marks text that the author has added without
cancelling similar text. <tit>SKS</tit> renders it in small square angels above
the line.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">Tanker, som anfalde <add status="variant">saare</add> bag fra</ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">Tanker, som anfalde <udg spec="var">saare</udg> bag fra</ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.5">
   <rubrik>Tacit correction</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>choice</name></elem>
      <elem><name>orig</name></elem>
      source text
      <tag>/orig</tag>
      <elem><name>reg</name></elem>
      corrected text
      <tag>/reg</tag>
      <tag>/choice</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>Marks text which the editor has
corrected from evidently false text. The part marked as <tag>orig</tag> is ignored by <tit>SKS</tit>.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">det simple gudsfrygtige Vers som vidunderlig prophetisk 
     <choice><orig>f</orig><reg>s</reg></choice>lynger sig igjenem den;</ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">det simple gudsfrygtige Vers som vidunderlig prophetisk <udg spec="stil" txt="f">s</udg>lynger sig igjenem den;</ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.6">
   <rubrik>Ellipsis</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>seg</name>
    <attr class="typed">type</attr>
    = "ellipsis"
   </elem>
  </synx>
    <sem>Marks text that in order to save space is to be left out in text-critical notes, 
see <refsekt id="2.5.2"/>. In the note <tit>SKS-B</tit> renders such text with three dots in italics in parentheses; in the main text as well as in <tit>SKS-E</tit> as a whole, this tagging is ignored. </sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
     <app>
      <lem>
       <add instant="false" rendition="#til">den Ene <seg type="ellipsis">vilde nemlig blive den anden, ligesom Katholiken blev Protestant og Protestanten</seg> Katholik. –</add>
      </lem>
     </app>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1"><tn><add type="til">den Ene <udg spec="ellipse">vilde nemlig blive den anden, ligesom Katholiken blev Protestant og Protestanten</udg> Katholik. <e name="streg">–</e></add></tn></ex>
    <sem>In some cases ellipses may grow to encompass several paragraphs and
thus violate the structure of XML. In such cases a milestone solution is used:</sem>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>milestone</name>
    <attr class="milestoneUnit">unit</attr>
    = "appLem"
    <attr class="typed">type</attr>
    = "ellipsis"
    <attr class="spanning">spanTo</attr>
    = "<meta>end text</meta>"
   </elem>
  </synx>
    <sem>The <tag>milestone</tag> is placed at the start of the ellipsis, but the end text after the ellipsis is instead repeated in the <x>spanTo</x> attribute;</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
     <p rendition="#ind">
      <app>
         <lem>Dette var Bønnen<milestone type="ellipsis" unit="appLem" spanTo="#Talemaader. –"/>
            <witDetail wit="#Ms">skrevet på oktavblad indklæbet i marginen, ms. s. 56</witDetail>
         </lem>
      </app>.
     </p>
     <p rendition="#lang">A: T:</p>
     <p rendition="#ind"> [...] endsige at Du skulde tage Bolig i zirlige Talemaader. –</p>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="ind"><tn>Dette var B<e name="o-">ø</e>nnen<udg spec="ellipse" txt="Talemaader. –"/><udg spec="fri" txt="skrevet på oktavblad indklæbet i marginen, ms. s. 56"/></tn>.</lin>
  <lin ryk="lang">A: T:</lin>
	<lin ryk="ind"> [...] endsige at Du skulde tage Bolig i zirlige Talemaader. –</lin></ex>
     <sem on="TEI">This is admittedly a lousy way to use the <x>spanTo</x> pointer attribute, another milestone should have been identified and placed at the ellipsis end. Since this mark-up is solely for the use of the printed <tit>SKS-B</tit> and thus at least partly obsolete, I find the hack acceptable.
     <html:br/>
       The seemingly unmotivated hash in front of the attribute value is in order to allow for strange characters such as kolon og square brackets in the phrase.</sem>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="2.3.11.7">
    <rubrik>Free style editorial notes</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>witDetail</name>
    wit="#..."
   </elem>
  </synx>
    <sem>Marks in text critical notes (<refsekt id="2.5.2"/>) the editors remarks which can find no other expression. See example above, <refsekt id="2.3.11.3"/> and <refsekt id="2.3.11.6"/>.</sem>
   </sekt>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.3.12">
   <rubrik>Barfods comments</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>witDetail</name>
    wit="#EP"
      <attr class="responsibility">resp</attr>="#EP"
   </elem>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks notes or comments given by Barfod to the text from <tit>EP</tit>.
<tit>SKS</tit> renders the content in brackets and same
smaller size as <tit>EP</tit> authors notes.
   The difference from the marking above in <refsekt id="2.3.11.7"/> (apart from the <x>resp</x> attribute present) is that this <tag>witDetail</tag> appears outside text critical notes as a part of the copy-text whose origin is then <tit>EP</tit> (also see <refsekt id="2.3.11.2"/>).</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><witDetail wit="#EP" resp="#EP">Senere tilføielse:</witDetail></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><barfod kom="Senere tilføielse:"/></ex>
  </sekt>

  </sekt>

 <sekt id="2.4">
 <rubrik>Referring terms</rubrik>

 <sem>Whenever a <term>date</term>, <term>person</term>, <term>place</term>, <term>literature</term> or <term>bible references</term> occurs in the text, it is marked with the purpose of creating <term>indexes</term>.
  To this end the occurrance must be <term>normalised</term>.
  In <tit>SKS-E</tit> the normalised form should be displayed as a pop-up when the mouse points to the occurance.</sem>
 <sem>Only occurrances in a strictly sense is marked; i.e. allusions or hints, like »to day« eller »her« are not. Please refer the <tit>SKS-E</tit> guide to <reflit id="Registre"/>.</sem>

  <sekt id="2.4.1">
   <rubrik>Dates</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>date</name>
      <html:a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-att.datable.w3c.html#tei_att.when">when</html:a>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"
   </elem>
   </synx>
   <sem>Marks a text is a date. The attribute <x>when</x> gives the date on
standard form: four digit year, two digit month, and day, also see
dating of entries <refsekt id="3.6"/>.
    Zeroes may be used to signify unknown month or day.</sem>
    <sem on="TEI">This is why this 8 digit date model has been preferred over the ISO model with dashes YYYY-mm-dd, which does not allow zeroes.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><date when="18360913">d. 13 <hi rendition="#lat">Sept:</hi> 36</date>.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><dag dat="18360913">d. 13 <ant>Sept:</ant> 36</dag>.</ex>
    <sem>Two digit years are interpreted strictly, e.g. 48.... means <typ art="capi">a.d.</typ> 48:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Man kunde ogsaa gjøre det saaledes, at blot Dato blev fælles. <date when="480725">D 25 Juli 48</date> sagde 
                        <persName key="Paulus">Paulus</persName>
                      det og det – hvorfor han blev hudflettet. <date when="18480725">D. 25 Juli 1848</date> sagde <persName key="N. N.">N. N</persName>, at <persName key="Paulus">Paulus</persName> havde sagt det og var blevet hudflettet derfor og blev N.N. til Belønning derfor 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>R af D.</abbr>
                           <expan>Ridder af Dannebrog</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Man kunde ogsaa gjøre det saaledes, at blot Dato blev fælles. <dag dat="00480725">D 25 Juli 48</dag> sagde <pers norm="Paulus">Paulus</pers> det og det – hvorfor han blev hudflettet. <dag dat="18480725">D. 25 Juli 1848</dag> sagde <pers norm="N. N.">N. N</pers>, at <pers norm="Paulus">Paulus</pers> havde sagt det og var blevet hudflettet derfor og blev N.N. til Belønning derfor <fork opl="Ridder af Dannebrog">R af D.</fork></ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.4.2">
  <rubrik>Persons</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>persName</name>
      <attr class="canonical">key</attr>="<meta>normalised name</meta>"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="linking">sameAs</attr>="<meta>alternative name</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global">n</attr>="*"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks a name of a person. The attribute <x>key</x> gives a nomalised form of the name. <x>sameAs</x> an alternative form, pen name, nick name or the like, which in an index will typically refer back to the normalised name.
    The normalised form follows the way common for names in <tit>SKS</tit>, e.g. <tag>persName key="Sokrates"</tag>Socrates<tag>/persName</tag>.
    Family name is first, followed by a comma, except for kings, fictional persons and others that will be known under their first name.
    <x>n="*"</x> designates in the commentaries that this is a so-called <term>initial commentary</term> in which the person is presented in general terms with year of birth etc.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Som <persName key="Lafontaine, August Heinrich Julius">Lafontaine</persName> sidder han derfor og græder over sine ulykkelige Helte, der maae gaae under, og hvorfor? fordi <persName key="Andersen, Hans Christian">Andersen</persName> er den som han er.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Som <pers norm="Lafontaine, August Heinrich Julius">Lafontaine</pers> sidder han derfor og gr<e name="ae">æ</e>der over sine ulykkelige Helte, der maae gaae under, og hvorfor? fordi <pers norm="Andersen, Hans Christian">Andersen</pers> er den som han er.</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.4.3">
  <rubrik>Places</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>placeName</name>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="canonical">key</attr>="<meta>normalised name</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="linking">sameAs</attr>="<meta>alternative name</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
   </synx>
   <sem>Marks a place name. The attributes <x>key</x> and <x>sameAs</x> applies as for persons <refsekt id="2.4.2"/>.
    If <x>key</x> is not specified, the content of the element is used.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Om der nogensteds skulde sprudle en <placeName sameAs="Glemslens Flod">Lethe</placeName>, veed jeg ikke; men [...] Glemsomhed er ikke identisk med den Kunst at kunne glemme.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Om der nogensteds skulde sprudle en <sted alt="Glemslens Flod">Lethe</sted>, veed jeg ikke; men [...] Glemsomhed er ikke identisk med den Kunst at kunne glemme.</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.4.4">
  <rubrik>Literature</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>title</name>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="canonical">key</attr>="<meta>...</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
   </synx>
   <sem>Marks the title of literature. No usage nor coding has been made in any more detail.</sem>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.4.5">
  <rubrik>Abbreviations</rubrik>
  <synx>
     <elem><name>choice</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>abbr</name></elem>
      <meta>source text</meta>
      <tag>/abbr</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>expan</name>
       <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.analytic">ana</attr>="#<meta>ref</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
      </elem>
      <meta>expanded text</meta>
      <tag>/expan</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><elem>expan
       <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>ref</meta>"
       <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="means"
      </elem>
      <meta>explanation</meta>
      <tag>/expan</tag><sepa>]</sepa>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/choice</tag>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks the authors abbreviations. The following <tag>expan</tag> element gives an expansion of the abbreviation.
    In case this expansion adds little or no further understanding of the abbreviation, yet another <tag>expan</tag> element may be added that contains a translation or otherwise describe the meaning.
    The expansion is phrased after the custom and orthography of the author, wheras the further explanation follows modern orthography as expected in editorial texts. 
    When the abbreviation is a part of a date, persons name or other referring term, that one takes precedens, i.e. the abbreviation is not marked as such.
    Thus <cit>Sept:</cit> is not expanded in <tag>date when="18360913"</tag>d. 13 Sept: 36<tag>/date</tag> (<refsekt id="2.4.1"/>), and neither is <cit>Cap.</cit> or <cit>V.</cit> in <tag>rs type="bible" key="Judit 10,11"</tag>Judiths Bog, Cap. 10, V. 11<tag>/rs</tag> (<refsekt id="2.4.6"/>).</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
    Men Den, som vedkjender sig denne Anskuelse (der da sjeldent foredrages <choice>
        <abbr>o: s: v:</abbr>
        <expan>og saa videre</expan>
     </choice> i Journalen NB <choice>
        <abbr>p.</abbr>
        <expan ana="#means1">pagina</expan>
        <expan rend="means" xml:id="means1">side</expan>
     </choice> 97 <choice><abbr>lin</abbr><expan ana="#means2">linea</expan>
        <expan rend="means" xml:id="means2">linje</expan></choice> 4 <choice>
        <abbr>fr.</abbr>
        <expan>fra</expan>
     </choice> neden.
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Men Den, som vedkjender sig denne Anskuelse (der da sjeldent foredrages <fork opl="og saa videre">o: s: v:</fork> i Journalen NB <fork opl="pagina" norm="side">p.</fork> 97 lin 4 <fork opl="fra">fr.</fork> neden.</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.4.6">
  <rubrik>Biblical references</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>rs</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="bible"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="canonical">key</attr>="<meta>Book chapter,verse</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks the text as a reference to the Bible. The attribute <x>key</x>
gives the reference on standard form, see <tit>Bibelen</tit>, Copenhagen 1992,
or <reflit id="Registre"/> Bible index.
    If the <x>key</x> attribute is omitted, the element content is used as key; this will typically be the case for the commentaries.
    Do note that there is no space between chapter and verse.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Et ganske fuldendt Exempel paa Romantik finder jeg i det Gamle Testamente, i <rs type="bible" key="Judit 10,11">Judiths Bog, Cap. 10, V. 11</rs>:</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Et ganske fuldendt Exempel paa Romantik finder jeg i det Gamle Testamente, i <bib id="Judit 10,11">Judiths Bog, Cap. 10, V. 11</bib>:</ex>
  </sekt>

 </sekt>
 
 <sekt id="2.5">
 <rubrik>Internal references</rubrik>

  <sem>By internal references is understood <term>authors references</term>, <term>text critical notes</term>, <term>indirect text sources</term> and <term>illustrations</term>.
   In addition there are <term>cross references</term> between commentaries which are handled in the section for commentaries <refsekt id="3.8.3"/>.</sem>
  <sekt id="2.5.1">
  <rubrik>Authors references to own notes</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>ptr</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="author"
      <attr class="pointing">target</attr>="#<meta>short title</meta>.<meta>n</meta>"
   /</elem>
  </synx>
  <sem>Marks references in printed texts to the authors own footnotes.
   In the copy-text, references will typically be given by systematic reference markers, e.g. one, two, or three asterisks. Each page uses unique markers, and the corresponding note is put at the footer of the page, and may possibly run over onto the next page. SKS-B renders this system using elevated digits <hoj>1, 2, 3</hoj> etc. The digits are determined when the page is finally set and does not occur from this coding. 
   The <x>target</x> attribute unambigously identifies the note, which must correspond to a note somewhere in the current document, see <refsekt id="3.3"/>.
   <tit>SKS-E</tit> which have no such thing as a footer nor a page, renders the note immediately after the reference. This results in a most unfortunate break of the running texst, wich we have to accept. As marker an astesisk is used.
 Example from printed works:</sem>

   <ex gen="-sks">
    gangs-Periode – meget rigtigt! idetmindste er Granit-Formationen allerede længe forbi, Fløse-Formationen overstaaet, og vi har formodentlig en god Stund fordybet os i Tørve-Formationen.<ptr type="author" target="#lp.14"/> Eller var det vor Tids Generalforsamlinger,<ptr type="author" target="#lp.15"/> disse det politiske Livs Omnibusser, disse brasilianske Myretuer, hvilke, efter en Naturforskers Beretning, ved en Samling af flere Millioner, frembyde en frappant Lighed med Fortidens Mindesmærker over en Mand – en Kæmpehøi? Eller hvorledes skulde <pb xml:id="ss28" edRef="#SKS" n="28"/>
   </ex>
 <html:img src="ex2.5.1.a.jpg" alt="SKS 1,27, klip fra bogen" width="100%" style="border: 1px solid navy"/>
	<sem>Same example, rendered according to <tit>SKS-E</tit>:</sem>
  <ex gen="-kn1"><lin>gangs-Periode – meget rigtigt! idetmindste er Granit-Formationen allerede længe forbi, Fløse-Formationen overstaaet, og vi har formodentlig en god Stund fordybet os i Tørve-Formationen.<ref type="sk" id="lp.14"/> Eller var det vor Tids Generalforsamlinger,<ref type="sk" id="lp.15"/> disse det politiske Livs Omnibusser, disse brasilianske Myretuer, hvilke, efter en Naturforskers Beretning, ved en Samling af flere Millioner, frembyde en frappant Lighed med Fortidens Mindesmærker over en Mand – en Kæmpehøi? Eller hvorledes skulde <kor kil="SKS" id="28"/></lin>
  <not type="sk" id="lp.14">
      <lin>Det er ogsaa ret mærkeligt, at den nyere Udvikling i saa mange Henseender har <kom id="lp-164">distingueret sig</kom> som <kom id="lp-165">Formetørvs-Perioden</kom>.</lin>
    </not>
    <not type="sk" id="lp.15">
    <lin><ant><kom id="lp-166">Sed nimis</kom> arta premunt olidae convivia caprae.</ant></lin>
    </not>
</ex>
  <sem>The note coding is explaned in <refsekt id="3.3"/>.</sem>
   <sem>In the journals and papers too <tit>SKS</tit>
renders reference markers as digits when regarding notes which are
placed at the footer of the manuscript or following the entry in the
main column. Same goes for notes originating from <tit>EP</tit>. References to the margin column is rendered as elevated litra <hoj>a, b, c</hoj> etc, and typed <x>type="author"</x>.    
    Each entry uses unique markers for its notes, which furthermore constitutes a canonical reference within the <tit>SKS</tit>. Hence these may be unambigiously determined and encoded at the stage of text establishment, by means of the following <term>reference marker</term> element:</sem>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>ref</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="author"
      <attr class="pointing">target</attr>="#<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>entry number</meta>.<meta>reference marker</meta>"
   </elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>seg</name>
    <attr class="typed">type</attr>="refMarker"
   </elem> <meta>digit|litra</meta> <tag>/seg</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/ref</tag>
  </synx>

  <sem>Not all notes are in fact referred by a marker in the copy-text. Such notes are attributed by <x>anchored="false"</x>, see the section on notes <refsekt id="3.3"/>. For the case of marginal notes the position will be visible, however, in so far as the location of the reference does determine the vertical position of the corresponding marginal entry. A <tag>ptr</tag> tag should be encoded at the beginning of the line of main column text where the marginal entry is placed in the manuscript.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Den kunde begyndt med de Ord: <ref type="commentary" target="kom.xml#jj-244" xml:id="jj-244">vide I</ref> da som ere onde at give Eders Børn gode Gaver, hvor meget mere skulde da Gud ikke vide det.<ref type="author" target="#jj-108.1"><seg type="refMarker">1</seg></ref> Den skulde<ptr type="author" target="#jj-108.a"/> da begynde med Tvivlen om nu virkelig et <choice><abbr>Msk</abbr><expan>Menneske</expan></choice> vidste at give gode Gaver.</ex>
  <ex gen="-kn1">Den kunde begyndt med de Ord: <kom id="jj-244">vide I</kom> da som ere onde at give Eders B<e name="o-">ø</e>rn gode Gaver, hvor meget mere skulde da Gud ikke vide det.<ref type="sn" id="jj-108.1"><indv>1</indv></ref> Den skulde <ref type="mu" id="jj-108.a"/>da begynde med Tvivlen om nu virkelig et <fork opl="Menneske">Msk</fork> vidste at give gode Gaver.</ex>
    <sem>The <x>target</x> value <x>"JJ-108.1"</x> corresponds to the canonical JJ:108.1, hyphen replacing colon, which should not be used as identification, <reflit id="XML"/>, 2.3.</sem>
  <sem>Note that the editor may decide to supplement a reference marker left
out by the author.</sem>
  </sekt> 
  
  <sekt id="2.5.2">
  <rubrik>Text-critical notes</rubrik>
   <synx>
    <elem><name>app</name></elem>
    <elem><name>lem</name></elem>
    { <elem><name>rdg</name></elem> }
    | { <elem><name>rdgGrp</name></elem>
    } <tag>/app</tag>
   </synx>

   <sem>Marks a <term>text critical note</term>, which may contain exactly one <term>lemma</term> followed by a number of <term>readings</term> or <term>reading groups</term>.</sem>

   <sem>A Lemma may consist of coherent text, <term>additions</term> or <cit>corrections</cit>. Additions and corrections are text portions added to the reading text of <tit>SKS</tit>. The <x>wit</x> attribute may inform about the source or provenance of this text.</sem>

    <sem><cit>Readings</cit> are text portions that are not
rendered in the reading text of <tit>SKS</tit>. <tit>SKS-B</tit> renders it in a footnote (below the authors footnote, cf. example in <refsekt id="2.5.1"/>), and <tit>SKS-E</tit> in line on demand. The <x>wit</x> attribute designates the source or provenance of the text. In the case of more than one reading, a <x>rendition</x> attribute designates a delimiter character, specifying the relationship between the readings, see Text Critical Guidelines, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.5.
   A <term>reading</term> <tag>rdg</tag> may further consist of a <term>deletion</term> <tag>del</tag>, <term>correction</term> <tag>corr</tag>, <term>supplied text</term> <tag>supplied</tag>, or it may consitute a <term>supplementary note</term> (<reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.4), pointing out sources with differring or equal readings <tag>sic</tag>.</sem>
   
   <sem>An addition, deletion, supplement, or other may be given a formal editorial text by a reference by the <x>rendition</x> attribute to a <tag>rendition</tag> element in the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, as further specified below.</sem>
   
   <sem>The main two uses of text-critical notes are for <term>text emendation</term> (primarily in printet texts, <refsekt id="2.5.2.1"/>) or <term>internal variance</term> (only in mss. <refsekt id="2.5.2.2"/>).</sem>

 <sem on="TEI">Short about the use of <x>wit</x>: TEI usually destinguish between a <term>wittness</term> and a <term>responsible</term> when it comes to text amendments. KN1 does not make a similay distinction, as every such thing is termed <x>KN1:kil</x> (dan. <frspr>kilde</frspr> = source) which is invariantly transformed into <x>TEI:wit</x>, both in the case where a copy-text is corrected according to an edition, eventually <tit>SKS</tit> itself (in which case <x>TEI:resp</x> would be a better choice) and in the case where the same edition actually plays the role of copy-text.</sem>

  <sekt id="2.5.2.1">
   <rubrik>Text emendation</rubrik>
   <synx>
    <elem><name>app</name></elem>
     <html:br/>
     &#x2003;<elem><name>lem</name> <attr class="witnessed">wit</attr>="#<meta>siglum</meta>"</elem>
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;&#x2003;{
    <meta>coherent text</meta>
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>corr</name></elem>
    <meta>coherent text</meta>
    <elem><name>witDetail</name></elem>
    <meta>free editorial text</meta>
    <tag>/witDetail</tag>
    <tag>/corr</tag>}
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<tag>/lem</tag>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;{<elem><name>rdg</name>
     <attr class="witnessed">wit</attr>="#<meta>siglum</meta>"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#komma"</elem>
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;&#x2003;{
     <elem>corr
     <attr class="editLike">evidence</attr>="suggestedConjecture"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#mff"
    </elem>
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;&#x2003;|
     <elem><name>supplied</name>
     <attr class="editLike">evidence</attr>="suggestedConjecture"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#mgl"</elem>
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;&#x2003;|
     <elem><name>sic</name>
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#so"</elem>}
    <html:br/>
     &#x2003;<tag>/rdg</tag> }
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;|
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;{<elem><name>rdgGrp</name>
      <sepa>[</sepa>rendition="#semiko"<sepa>]</sepa></elem>
     {<tag>rdg</tag>}
     <tag>/rdgGrp</tag>
     }
     <html:br/>
    <tag>/app</tag>
   </synx>
   <sem>In the case of <term>text emendation</term> the usual
copy-text reading (<tag>rdg</tag>) is replaced by an alternative text (<tag>corr</tag>). <tit>SKS-B</tit> renders the
original text in a footnote. A text reading with no corresponding text
addition designates a supplementary note, suggesting a conjectural reading.</sem>
   <sem>The general layout for <tit>SKS</tit> of a text emendation note is</sem>

   <sem>
    lemma<refnote id="1"/>]
    <html:i>source-of-lemma</html:i><refnote id="2"/>
    <html:i>free-editorial-text-for-lemma</html:i><refnote id="3"/><html:i>,
     type-tekst</html:i><refnote id="6"/>
    note-tekst<refnote id="4"/>
    <html:i>source-of-note</html:i><refnote id="5"/>
   </sem>
   <sem>where <refnote id="6"/> through <refnote id="5"/> may be repeated for each reading, delimted as specified.<refnote id="7"/></sem>
  <ex gen="-kn1">»<kom id="lp-64">Solchen</kom> Sekanten, Kosekanten, Tangenten, <tn><sub kil="A">Kotagenten</sub><add kil="SKS">Kotangenten <udg spec="fri" txt="(efter Jean Paul)"/></add></tn> kommt alles excentrisch vor, besonders das Centrum.«</ex>

   <note id="1">Lemma is the portion of the text surrounded by <tag>lem</tag>.</note>

   <note id="2">If the source of lemma is not identical with the source of the copy-text in general, the lemma should be attributed <x>wit</x> to designate the source. The source is rendered as a
siglum in italics after the <term>lemma character</term> (]).</note>

   <note id="3">Free style editorial text that is put within the <tag>lem</tag> element is set in italics after the lemma character.
   <refnote id="2"/> and/or <refnote id="3"/> is separated from the following by a comma in italics.</note>

   <note id="6">The note text may contain a leading legend text, similar to internal variants (<refsekt id="2.5.2.2"/>) as given by the attribute <x>rendition</x>, corresponding to statements in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of the document, e.g.
   <ex gen="-sks"><rendition xml:id="so" selector="sic" scope="before">content:"således også "</rendition></ex>
   <html:br/>
     The legends relevant for text emendation are:</note>
   <ex vis="vert" gen="-sks">
    <rdg wit="#X"> <sic rendition="#so"/> </rdg> <forkl><cit>således også X</cit>, »same reading as <cit>X</cit>«, no evidence for correction, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.4.2</forkl>
    <rdg> <corr evidence="suggestedConjecture" rendition="#mff"> ... </corr> </rdg> <forkl><cit>måske fejl for</cit> ..., »possibly error; read ...«, suggested correction, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.4.4</forkl>
    <rdg> <supplied evidence="suggestedConjecture" rendition="#mgl"> ... </supplied> </rdg> <forkl><cit>ord mangler, fx ...</cit>, »missing word, e.g. ...«, suggested supplement, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 8.6.3</forkl>
   </ex>

   <note id="4">The text of the note in ordinary typeface consisting of the readings of the <tag>app</tag> element. Free style editors notes occuring inside the <tag>rdg</tag> elements are set in italics where they occur.</note>

   <note id="5">For each reading the source is identifed by a siglum which is set in italics after the note.
    <x>wit</x> is a pointer, referring to a full statement of the referred source in the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, see <refsekt id="3.10.7"/>.</note>
   
    <note id="7">Individual readings of the same kind are delimited by commas (<reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/>, 3.5.1), whereas reading groups <tag>rdgGrp</tag> are delimited by a semicolon (<reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/>, 3.5.2) as given by the <x>rendition</x> attribute.</note>

   <sem>Example, editors conjecture; editors conjecture combined with supplemental note:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">I »Biblische Legenden der
	<app>
                  <lem wit="#SKS">
                     <corr>Muselmänner <witDetail wit="#SKS">(efter Weil)</witDetail>
                     </corr>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>Muselmanner</rdg>
               </app>
	aus arabischen Qvellen</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">I »Biblische Legenden der
	<tn><add kil="SKS">Muselmänner <udg spec="fri" txt="(efter Weil)"></udg></add><sub>Muselmanner</sub></tn>
	aus arabischen Qvellen</ex>
   <ex gen="-sks">Træffer den et Menneske, der paa det Spørgsmaal, hvortil han <app><lem wit="#SKS"
><corr>har den</corr></lem><rdgGrp><rdg wit="#A">har det</rdg></rdgGrp><rdgGrp rendition="#semiko"><rdg wit="#K #R">har det</rdg></rdgGrp></app>,
     ikke kan svare Andet, end at han ikke ret selv veed det,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Træffer den et Menneske, der paa det Spørgsmaal, hvortil han <tn>
    	<sub kil="A">har det</sub>
	    <sub kil="K" skil="semiko">har det</sub>
	    <sub kil="R" skil="komma"/>
     <add kil="SKS">har den</add></tn>,
	ikke kan svare Andet, end at han ikke ret selv veed det,</ex>
   <sem>Example, supplementary notes; suggested conjecture; the two combined:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">men dog vel neppe bringe Nogen til at <app>
                  <lem>bede
	</lem>
                  <rdg wit="#K">bede, eller til at bede</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#R" rendition="#komma">bede eller til at bede</rdg>
               </app>
	paa nogen anden Maade end med den Tilbageholdenhed, der er fornøden, naar vi bede om jordiske Goder;</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">men dog vel neppe bringe Nogen til at <tn>bede
	<sub kil="K">bede, eller til at bede</sub>
	<sub kil="R" skil="komma">bede eller til at bede</sub></tn>
	paa nogen anden Maade end med den Tilbageholdenhed, der er forn<e name="o-">ø</e>den, naar vi bede om jordiske Goder;</ex>
  <ex gen="-sks">thi i Socrates Anskuelse var der sandeligen god Mening, om vi end <app>
                  <lem>forlode det </lem>
                  <rdg wit="#R">
                     <sic rendition="#so"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app> for at opdage det tidligere Projekterede,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">thi i Socrates Anskuelse var der sandeligen god Mening, om vi end <tn>forlode det <sub kil="R" type="so"/></tn> for at opdage det tidligere Projekterede,</ex>
   <ex gen="-sks">Skjøndt denne Bog godt veed <app>
                  <lem>med mig selv
	</lem>
                  <rdgGrp>
                     <rdg wit="#R">mig selv</rdg>
                  </rdgGrp>
                  <rdgGrp rendition="#semiko">
                     <rdg>
                        <corr evidence="suggestedConjecture" rendition="#mff">med sig selv</corr>
                     </rdg>
                  </rdgGrp>
               </app>,
	hvad dens Forfatter veed endnu bedre,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Skjøndt denne Bog godt veed <tn>med mig selv
	<sub kil="R">mig selv</sub>
	<sub type="mff" skil="semiko">med sig selv</sub></tn>,
	hvad dens Forfatter veed endnu bedre,</ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="2.5.2.2">
   <rubrik>Internal variance</rubrik>
   <synx>
    <elem><name>app</name></elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<elem><name>lem</name></elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;{ 
    <meta>coherent text</meta>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>add</name> <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#til"<sepa>]</sepa></elem>}
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<tag>/lem</tag>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;{<elem><name>rdg</name>
     <sepa>[</sepa>rendition="#komma"<sepa>]</sepa></elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;{
    coherent text
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>del</name>
     <attr class="editLike">instant</attr>="<meta>Boolean</meta>"
     rendition="#<meta>legend</meta>"</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>corr</name>
     <attr class="editLike">evidence</attr>="suggestedConjecture"
     rendition="#mff"
    </elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>supplied</name>
     <attr class="editLike">evidence</attr>="suggestedConjecture"
     rendition="#mgl"</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;|
    <elem><name>sic</name>
     rendition="#so"</elem>}
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003; <tag>/rdg</tag>}
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;|
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;{<elem><name>rdgGrp</name>
      <sepa>[</sepa>rendition="#semiko"<sepa>|</sepa>"#ny"<sepa>]</sepa></elem>
     {<tag>rdg</tag>}
     <tag>/rdgGrp</tag>
     }
     <html:br/>
    <tag>/app</tag>
   </synx>
    <sem on="TEI"><term>Internal variance</term>, i.e. corrections in the authors
own hand, are in <tit>SKS</tit> genetically determined. I.e. the intension with the text-critical notes is to reveal the genesis of the the text rather
than the appearance of the manuscripts as described in Text Critical Guidelines.
    This perspective is mirrored in TEI with the <x>instant</x> attribute that may be true, false or unknown. The latter fact illustrates that the genesis can not be etablished, hence the position of the alteration is given, cf. <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 4.4.  
The genesis is rendered by a nomenclature as defined in <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> sect. 5: a fixed set of formal legend texts
which in TEI is expressed through the <x>rendition</x> attribute of the relevant element (cf. <refsekt id="2.5.2.1"/> on text emendtion):</sem>
   <ex vis="vert" gen="-sks">
    <rdg><del instant="true" rendition="#fs">...</del></rdg> <forkl><cit>først skrevet ... </cit>, »initially written ... «, instant alteration, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 5.1 </forkl>
    <rdg><del instant="false" rendition="#aef">...</del></rdg> <forkl><cit>ændret fra ... </cit>, »altered from ... «, later alteration, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 5.2</forkl>
    <lem><add instant="false" rendition="#til">...</add></lem>  <forkl><cit> ... tilføjet</cit>, » ... added«, later addition, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 5.2.3</forkl>
    <lem varSeq="2"/>
    <rdg varSeq="1">
       <del instant="unknown" rendition="#sletfor">...</del>
    </rdg>  <forkl><cit>foran er slettet ... </cit>, »before is deleted ... «, genetically uncertain deletion, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/>  5.3.1</forkl>
    <lem varSeq="1"/>
    <rdg varSeq="2">
       <del instant="unknown" rendition="#sletbag">...</del>
    </rdg> <forkl><cit>herefter er slettet ... </cit>, »after this, the following is deleted ...«</forkl>
    <rdg><del instant="unknown" rendition="#uvis">...</del></rdg>  <forkl><cit>&lt; ... </cit>, genetically uncertain correction, <reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/> 5.3.2</forkl>
  </ex>

   <sem>The general layout of the note text for internal variance is</sem>
   <sem>lemma] addition <html:i>legend-text</html:i> reading</sem>
   <sem>e.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-kn1">men dette er ogsaa nødvendigt for at Gud kan skabe <tn>Noget <sub type="fs">ad</sub> <add>af</add></tn> os; thi Gud skaber altid af Intet,</ex>
   <sem>The lemma may or may not include an addition. If the addition is identical to the lemma as a whole, it is omitted from the note. The following examples illustrates the use or not use of additions in lemma:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Sætteren beder for dette Forord. <app>
                  <lem>Jeg</lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="true" rendition="#fs"/>Han be</rdg>
               </app> loe rigtignok lidt af ham,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">S<e name="ae">æ</e>tteren beder for dette Forord. <tn><sub type="fs">Han be</sub> Jeg</tn> loe rigtignok lidt af ham,</ex>
   <sem>We may argue that here is no additional text, so the deleted text is merely anchored in a lemma of invariant text, viz. text following the deletion.
    There is no text addition, hence nothing before the legend.
    In contrast, however, we may choose to interpret the lemma as a substitution for the reading.
    In that case, we code</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Sætteren beder for dette Forord. <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>Jeg</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="true" rendition="#fs"/>Han be</rdg>
               </app> loe rigtignok lidt af ham,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Sætteren beder for dette Forord. <tn><sub type="fs">Han be</sub> <add>Jeg</add></tn> loe rigtignok lidt af ham,</ex>
   <sem>Both ways may be justified and will result in the same note; the coding is up to the encoding philologist.</sem>
   <sem>In rare cases, it has been necessary to anchor an alteration to a larger text part than strictly involved. In this case the addition has to be repeated in the note to signal that the alteration not as usual starts with the lemma.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><app>
                  <lem>Noget <add>af</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="true" rendition="#fs"/>ad</rdg>
               </app></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><tn>Noget <sub type="fs">ad</sub> <add>af</add></tn></ex>
   <sem>This is done exclusively for the benefit of the book version. To be preferred was</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Noget <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>af</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="true" rendition="#fs"/>ad</rdg>
               </app></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Noget <tn><sub type="fs">ad</sub> <add>af</add></tn></ex>
   <sem>but since the word is frequent and actually occurs 6 words further in the line, we add invariant text to identify the the spot correctly in <tit>SKS-B,</tit> where the line numbers are used for identification, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.1.</sem>
   <sem>Example: Later alteration</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Eller skulde den Χstne ikke opmundres til at <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>kæmpe</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="false" rendition="#aef"/>stride</rdg>
               </app> under en Hærfører</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Eller skulde den <e name="g.Ch">Χ</e>stne ikke opmundres til at <tn><sub type="aef">stride</sub> <add>k<e name="ae">æ</e>mpe</add></tn> under en H<e name="ae">æ</e>rf<e name="o-">ø</e>rer</ex>
   <sem>Example: Later addition</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">en Pige, der i de afgjørende Dage før Brylluppet <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add instant="false" rendition="#til">blev bedraget</add>
                  </lem>
               </app>,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">en Pige, der i de afgj<e name="o-">ø</e>rende Dage f<e name="o-">ø</e>r Brylluppet <tn><add type="til">blev bedraget</add></tn>,</ex>
   <sem>Same with invariant text involed</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">Der gives Msk, der ved med en skrækkelig Geskjæftighed at blande <app>
                  <lem>sig <add instant="false" rendition="#til">i</add> Alt</lem>
               </app>,</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Der gives Msk, der ved med en skr<e name="ae">æ</e>kkelig Geskj<e name="ae">æ</e>ftighed at blande <tn>sig <add type="til">i</add> Alt</tn>,</ex>
   <sem>Example: deleted words</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">et saadant stort Værk tænker man vel maa have <app>
                  <lem varSeq="2"> meget</lem>
                  <rdg varSeq="1">
                     <del instant="unknown" rendition="#sletfor"/>en</rdg>
               </app> dyb Grund</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">et saadant stort Værk tænker man vel maa have <tn><sub type="sletfor">en</sub> meget</tn> dyb Grund</ex>
   <sem>The legend <x>"sletfor"</x> has been preferred over <x>"sletbag"</x> whenever there have been a free choice of lemma.</sem>
    <sem on="TEI">As TEI demands that the lemma is placed first in the apparatus, the attribute <x>varSeq</x> has been introduced to specify that the sequence is actually wronged.</sem>
   <sem>Example: uncertain alteration.
    The legend <x>"uvis"</x> is used whenever the genesis of an substituting variant could not be determined with certaincy.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">fordi Tænkeren <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>er</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="unknown" rendition="#uvis"/>har</rdg>
               </app> i det uendelige Inderligheds Forhold til sin Gjenstand</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">fordi Tænkeren <tn><sub type="uvis">har</sub> <add>er</add></tn> i det uendelige Inderligheds Forhold til sin Gjenstand</ex>
   <sem><x>"uvis"</x> is futhermore used with alterations of single letters or punctuation. The encoding granularity is one word, i.e. in the case of single words or parts thereof, the word is rewritten:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>det</add>
                  </lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="unknown" rendition="#uvis"/>der</rdg>
               </app></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><tn><sub type="uvis">der</sub> <add>det</add></tn></ex>
   <sem>There may be several layers of alterations.
    An <tag>app</tag> element may contain more than one <tag>rdg</tag>.
    In the context of internal varians this means that alterations in the text are themselves altered.
    Example:
    The author has written <cit>naar han spurgte</cit>, but corrected <cit>han</cit> to <cit>Een</cit>, we can not tell when. Later he has decided for <cit>man</cit>, which is the final text:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">naar <app>
                  <lem>
                     <add>man</add>
	spurgte</lem>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="false" rendition="#aef"/>Een</rdg>
                  <rdg>
                     <del instant="unknown" rendition="#uvis"/>han</rdg>
               </app>, hvordan har De det, svarede han: mg? o: s: v:.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">naar <tn>
   <sub type="aef">Een</sub><sub type="uvis">han</sub><add>man</add>
	spurgte</tn>, hvordan har De det, svarede han: mg? o: s: v:.</ex>
   <sem>This case shows a chain of alterations, <cit>han</cit> referring to <cit>Een</cit> referring to <cit>man</cit> in the lemma.</sem>
   <sem>Note that cases of layers of alterations (more than one <tag>rdg</tag>
element) have been encoded in opposite sequence of the naturally
chronological one (<cit>han</cit> is actually written before <cit>Een</cit>) in order to suit a note that is read chronologicaly backwards.
    Note that text emendation notes are rendered in forward chronological order, <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 3.4.2.1.</sem>
    <sem on="TEI">Here the <x>varSeq</x> attribute might have come in handy, cf. earlier i this section.</sem>
    <sem>In cases where a correction later than the first one refers to lemma, a delimiter is necessary. A semicolon after the quoted text will not suffice as it might mistakenly be understood as belonging to that text. This delimiter is encoded skil="ny" and rendered as a centered dot (<reflit id="Retningslinier/jp"/>, 8.5.3):</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#ant">ubi Lysias tribunus <app>
                     <lem varSeq="2">
                        <add>descenderit</add>
                     </lem>
                     <rdgGrp>
                        <rdg>
                           <del instant="unknown" rendition="#uvis"/>descendit</rdg>
                     </rdgGrp>
                     <rdgGrp rendition="#ny">
                        <rdg varSeq="1">
                           <del instant="unknown" rendition="#sletfor"/>ac</rdg>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app> ego etiam decernam vestram causam.</hi></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><ant>ubi Lysias tribunus <tn>
	<sub type="uvis">descendit</sub>
	<sub type="sletfor" skil="ny">ac</sub>
	<add>descenderit</add></tn> ego etiam decernam vestram causam.</ant></ex>
  </sekt>

  </sekt> 
  
  <sekt id="2.5.3">
   <rubrik>Indirect source</rubrik>
   <sem>The copy-text for journals and papers are the authors manuscripts. 
    Now and then it happens, though, that other sources have been used. There are two distinct cases here:
    One is that a larger or smaller part of the ms. may be missing.
    The other is that the author has himself made additions on separate sheets of paper.</sem>
   <sem>As these passages may start and end anywhere (typically at
    manuscript page breaks) independantly of the structure of the
document, it may not necessarily be possible to place the tags paired
the proper XML way. Hence they are defined as two independant
elements, so called <term>milestones</term>.</sem>
   <synx>
    <elem>app</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;
    <elem>rdg</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;
    <elem><name>witStart</name>
     <attr class="rdgPart">wit</attr>="#<meta>X</meta>"
     <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page in X</meta>"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#<meta>startMarker</meta>"
    /</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;
    <elem><name>witDetail</name>
     <attr>wit</attr>="#<meta>X</meta>"
     <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page in ms.</meta>"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#msifBbeg #msifBslut"
    </elem>
    <meta>free editorial description of source</meta>
    <tag>/witDetail</tag>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;
    <tag>/rdg</tag>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;
    <elem><name>rdg</name> <attr class="witnessed">wit</attr>="#<meta>Y</meta>"</elem> <meta>other reading</meta> <tag>/rdg</tag>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/app</tag>
    <html:br/>
    ...
    <html:br/>
    <elem>app</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;
    <elem>rdg</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;
    <elem><name>witEnd</name>
     <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#<meta>endMarker</meta>"
    /</elem>
    <html:br/>&#x2003;
    <tag>/rdg</tag>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/app</tag>
   </synx>

   <sem>At the start of the passage a note is placed.</sem>

   <sem>The general layout for a note is</sem>
   <sem>
    ▸...◂<refnote id="1"/>]
    <html:i>source</html:i><refnote id="2"/><html:i>,</html:i>
    <html:i>page</html:i> <refnote id="3"/>
    <html:i>(page in ms.)</html:i><refnote id="4"/>
    other reading<refnote id="5"/>
   </sem>
   <sem>where <refnote id="4"/> and <refnote id="5"/> are usually mutually  exclusive.</sem>  

   <html:img src="ex2.5.3.a.png" alt="SKS 18,167, klip fra bogen" width="100%" style="border: 1px solid navy"/>
   <html:img src="ex2.5.3.b.png" alt="SKS 18,176, klip fra bogen" width="100%" style="border: 1px solid navy"/>
   <sem>(The example rendering taken from <tit>SKS-B</tit>; the following examples shows the <tit>SKS-E</tit> rendering)</sem>
<!--   <ex gen="-kn1"><altbeg spec="hakbag" kil="EPI-II" msifB="30-31" n="406-407"/>...<altslut spec="hakbag"/></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><altbeg spec="hakhak" kil="Bfort" n="368"><sub kil="EPI-II">Det</sub></altbeg>...<altslut spec="hakhak"/></ex>   
-->   
   <note id="1">The note is introduced by diacritics as given by the  <x>rendition</x> attribute surrounding a three dot ellipsis.</note>
   <note id="2">The alternative source as given by <x>wit</x>. The source is rendered as a siglum in italics.</note>
   <note id="3">The source reference denotes the page, number or the like as given by <x>n</x> and rendered in italics together with any free style editor text.</note>
   <note id="4">The manuscript reference denotes page number(s) in the copy-text according to B-fort. as given by <x>n</x>. It is rendered in italics in parentesis with a leading and a trailing text as specified by <x>rendition</x>, i.e. <cit>ms. s. N if. B-fort.</cit> (»page number N according to Barfods list«).</note>
   <note id="5">The apparatus may contain yet a <x>rdg</x> element in accordance with <refsekt id="2.5.2"/>, or a free style editor text, <refsekt id="2.3.11.7"/> and is then delimited from the
previous by an italicised comma.
   This will be the case where there is two levels of indirect sources (<tit>B-fort.</tit> over <tit>EP</tit>, marked with double notches).</note>
   
   <sem>The diacriticas used for markers appears from a <tag>rendition</tag> element in the <tag>encodingDesc</tag> part of the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <rendition xml:id="hakbeg" selector="witStart" scope="before"> content: "▶" </rendition>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-sks">
  <rendition xml:id="hakhakbeg" selector="witStart" scope="before"> content: "▶▶" </rendition>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <rendition xml:id="hakbagbeg" selector="witStart" scope="before"> content: "▶"; text-align: justify </rendition>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <rendition xml:id="armbeg" selector="witStart" scope="before"> content: "⌈" </rendition>
    </ex>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <rendition xml:id="hakslut" selector="witEnd" scope="after"> content: "◀" </rendition>
    </ex>
    <sem>
    <term>Notches</term> indicates indirect text sources, typically copies in print (<x>"#hakbag"</x>, e.g. <tit>EP</tit>) or on loose pieces of paper (<x>"#hak"</x>).
    If the text is merely witnessed, but not available as such, double notches are used.
    <term>Ceilings</term> or <term>arms</term> (<x>"#arm"</x>) are used to indicate loose papers or scaps originating from the author.</sem>
   <sem>Example: A page has disappeared from the journal <tit>FF</tit>, its content being copied to page 24 by previous editor Barfod.
    According to same Barfods list of the mss. (<tit>B-fort.</tit>), this text has appeared at page 25, which is missing.
    Note the page break (<tag>pb</tag>) immedialte before the alternative source starts.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">hvorimod det let kunde ha<pb/>
               <app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witStart wit="#Bafskr" rendition="#hakbeg"/>
                     <witDetail wit="#Bafskr" rendition="#msifBbeg #msifBslut" n="25" place="elsewhere">ms. s. 24</witDetail>
                  </rdg>
               </app>ve blevet hans Undergang, da Folk bleve saa forbittrede derover, at de nær havde slaaet ham ihiel.<app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witEnd rendition="#hakslut"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">hvorimod det let kunde ha<kor/><altbeg spec="hak" kil="Bafskr" paa="ms. s. 24" msifB="25"/>ve blevet hans Undergang, da Folk bleve saa forbittrede derover, at de nær havde slaaet ham ihiel.<altslut spec="hak"/></ex>

   <sem>Example: From the journal <tit>JJ</tit> page 30-31 has disappeared,
    the content of which is recorded on the Barfods List (<tit>B-fort.</tit>).
    The text is taken from page 406-407 in <tit>EP</tit>, vol. I-II.
    Note that the alternative source ends where page 32 starts (<tag>pb n="32"</tag>).
    Part of the text has appearently been deleted, as the deletion streches into page 32:</sem>

   <ex gen="-sks"><p>[...] – Dog det hjalp ikke. Da tænker jeg, at <persName key="Abraham">Abraham</persName> har et Øieblik vendt sig bort fra ham, og da han atter vendte sig <pb/><app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witStart wit="#EPI-II" n="406-407" rendition="#hakbagbeg"/>
                     <witDetail wit="#EPI-II" rendition="#msifBbeg #msifBslut" n="30-31"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app>til ham, da var han ukjendelig for ham, hans Øie var vildt, hans Mine isnende, de ærværdige Lokker havde reist sig som Furier over hans Hoved. Han greb <persName key="Isak">Isaak</persName> i Brystet, han drog Kniven, han sagde: »Du troede, at det var for Guds Skyld, [...]</p>
    <p rendition="#ind">Dog hvo var der i min<app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witEnd rendition="#hakbagslut"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               <pb xml:id="s32" n="32"/>
               <del>Samtid der forstod denne?</del></p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin>[...] – Dog det hjalp ikke. Da tænker jeg, at <pers norm="Abraham">Abraham</pers> har et <e name="O-">Ø</e>ieblik vendt sig bort fra ham, og da han atter vendte sig <kor/><altbeg spec="hakbag" kil="EPI-II" msifB="30-31" n="406-407"/>til ham, da var han ukjendelig for ham, hans <e name="O-">Ø</e>ie var vildt, hans Mine isnende, de ærværdige Lokker havde reist sig som Furier over hans Hoved. Han greb <pers norm="Isak">Isaak</pers> i Brystet, han drog Kniven, han sagde: »Du troede, at det var for Guds Skyld, [...]</lin>
    <lin ryk="ind">Dog hvo var der i min<altslut spec="hakbag"/><kor id="32"/><udg spec="slet">Samtid der forstod denne?</udg></lin>
</ex>
   
   <sem>Example: In Notebook 1 the author has, probably in lack of space, introduced four notes on an enclosed piece of scrap.</sem>
   
   <ex gen="-sks"><p><app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witStart rendition="#armbeg"/>
                  </rdg>
                  <witDetail wit="#Ms">løs indlagt lap</witDetail>
               </app>
               <hi rendition="#und">Fra den religieuse Side.</hi>
            </p>
    
            <p>[...]  og prise Herren.<app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witEnd rendition="#armslut"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app></p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
    <lin><altbeg spec="arm"><udg spec="fri" txt="løs indlagt lap"/></altbeg><spa>Fra den religieuse Side.</spa></lin>
    <lin>[...]  og prise Herren.<altslut spec="arm"/></lin>
</ex>
   <sem>Example: In The Journal <tit>FF</tit>, page 53 has been reconstructed, here after a copy by previous editor Heiberg (<tit>H-afskrift</tit>). Heiberg has, however, painstakingly expanded the abbreviation <cit>Mskeligt</cit> (<frspr>Menneskeligt</frspr>, »human«), which appears from the older, hence better text witness, Barfods List (<tit>B-fort.</tit>).</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">               <app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witStart wit="#Hafskr" rendition="#hakbeg"/>
                     <witDetail wit="#Hafskr" rendition="#msifBbeg #msifBslut" n="53" place="elsewhere">lap</witDetail>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
	  »Alt
	  <app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witStart wit="#Bfort" n="443" rendition="#hakhakbeg"/>
                  </rdg>
	    
                  <rdg wit="#Hafskr">Menneskeligt</rdg>
	  
               </app>
	    Mskeligt
	  <app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witEnd rendition="#hakhakslut"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
	  lyver, Haabet som Fortvivlelsen«, læste jeg som Citat      af en gammel Opbyggelsesbog.
	<app>
                  <rdg>
                     <witEnd rendition="#hakslut"/>
                  </rdg>
               </app></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><altbeg spec="hak" kil="Hafskr" paa="lap" msifB="53"/>
	  »Alt
	  <altbeg spec="hakhak" kil="Bfort" n="443">
	    <sub kil="Hafskr">Menneskeligt</sub>
	  </altbeg>
	    Mskeligt
	  <altslut spec="hakhak"/>
	  lyver, Haabet som Fortvivlelsen«, læste jeg som Citat      af en gammel Opbyggelsesbog.
	<altslut spec="hak"/></ex>
  </sekt>
    
   <sekt id="2.5.4">
    <rubrik>Pointer to illustrations</rubrik>
    <synx import="refi"/>
    <sem>Marks a point in the text for which an illustration showing a facsimile exists (<tag>figure</tag>, <refsekt id="3.4"/>) elsewhere in the document or the text account.
      The pointer is rendered in <tit>SKS-E</tit> with a clickable text <html:i>fax</html:i>, e.g.
     </sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
<app><lem><ptr type="figure" target="#ill_5"/>Det <milestone type="ellipsis" unit="appLem" spanTo="#anderledes."/><witDetail wit="#Ms.">blad i kvartformat, fastklæbet på journalens første blad if. B-fort.</witDetail></lem></app>større Forord til »en Cyclus ethisk-religieuse Afhandlinger« kan dog ikke bruges, da det svækker Virkningen af Afhandlingen
      [...]
      ell. og maatte i en Anmærkning i selve Forordet bemærkes, at just Aar 48 Katastrophe havde stillet Martyriet anderledes
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><tn><refi id="5"/>Det  <udg spec="ellipse" txt="anderledes."/><udg spec="fri" txt="blad i kvartformat, fastklæbet på journalens første blad if. B-fort."/></tn>større Forord til »en Cyclus ethisk-religieuse Afhandlinger« kan dog ikke bruges, da det svækker Virkningen af Afhandlingen 
     [...]
     ell. og maatte i en Anmærkning i selve Forordet bemærkes, at just Aar 48 Katastrophe havde stillet Martyriet anderledes.</ex>
    <sem>As mentioned, the pointer may refer to an illustration in the text account (<x>txr.xml</x>).</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
               <pb xml:id="s65" n="65" facs="ill_k3.jpg"/>
               <ptr type="figure" target="txr.xml#ill_k3"/>Den Vei gaaer Χst. ligesom i Livet (hans jordiske Levnet) saaledes ogsaa i Historien mellem 2 Røvere, den ene forhærder sig, den anden omvender sig.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kor id="65"/><refi id="k3"/>Den Vei gaaer <e name="g.Ch">Χ</e>st. ligesom i Livet (hans jordiske Levnet) saaledes ogsaa i Historien mellem 2 R<e name="o-">ø</e>vere, den ene forh<e name="ae">æ</e>rder sig, den anden omvender sig.</ex>
    <sem>The pointer is employed in cases where an illustration is relevant for more than one location in a document (as illustrated by the first example above or NB13:21 in <refsekt id="3.6.1"/>) or for more than one document (text and text account). 
      Another typical example is shown in <refsekt id="3.2.3"/>.</sem>
   </sekt>
 </sekt>
 
  <sekt id="2.6">
   <rubrik>External references</rubrik>
   <sem>Marks any reference out of the authors text, such as <term>correlations</term>, <term>commentary references</term>, <term>shaft references</term> and <term>page references</term>.
    Other such linking out of the current document is handled in section <refsekt id="3.8.4"/>.</sem>
  
   <sekt id="2.6.1">
    <rubrik>Correlations</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>pb</name>
      <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="s<meta>page number</meta>"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page number</meta>"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="edition">edRef</attr>="#<meta>edition</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="supplied"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.facs">facs</attr>="<meta>image file</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
     </elem>
     <html:br/>
     <elem><name>milestone</name>
      <attr class="milestoneUnit">unit</attr>="entry"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>entry number</meta>"
      <attr class="edition">edRef</attr>="#<meta>edition</meta>"
     </elem>
    </synx>

    <sem>The <tag>pb/</tag> tag marks a page break in the copy-text or other editions of the text;
     in the latter case <x>edRef</x> gives the edition in question.
     The <tag>milestone</tag> tag marks a journal entry for <x>edRef="#Pap."</x> <x>n="</x><meta>volume</meta><meta>section</meta><meta>number</meta><x>"</x>; entries not present in that edition is given the attribute <x>unit="unnumbered"</x>, se example in <refsekt id="3.2.3"/>. The element also applies to letters in <x>edRef="#BogA"</x>, see example in <refsekt id="3.7.2.2"/>.</sem>
     <sem>E.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="IVA74"/>
               <pb xml:id="s29" n="29"/>Hiin Qvinde, der i den franske Revolution blev tilbedt »som Fornuftens Gudinde«</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kor kil="Pap" id="IVA74"/><kor id="29"/>Hiin Qvinde, der i den franske Revolution blev tilbedt »som Fornuftens Gudinde«</ex>
    <sem>If the page break separates words, white space should be put on either side of the element</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">men denne Spøg er tillige den dybeste Alvor, netop <pb xml:id="s33" n="33"/> fordi ethvert Msk. gjør det.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">men denne Sp<e name="o-">ø</e>g er tillige den dybeste Alvor, netop <kor id="33"/> fordi ethvert Msk. gj<e name="o-">ø</e>r det.</ex>
    <sem>otherwise not.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">Victor Eremita, som nu ikke mere kan være Udgiver (sympathetisk Ironi); Mode<pb xml:id="s179" n="179" rend="supplied"/>handleren (dæmonisk Fortvivlelse)</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Victor Eremita, som nu ikke mere kan være Udgiver (sympathetisk Ironi); Mode<kor kil="supp" id="179"/>handleren (dæmonisk Fortvivlelse)</ex>    
    <sem>Page breaks of the copy-text is rendered by <tit>SKS</tit> as a vertical bar, in <tit>SKS-B</tit> accompanied by the number in the margin.
      Note that the vertical bar is tied to the last word
or character on a page whereas the marginal page number is tied to
the first word or character on the new page, i.e. if parted by a line
break, the bar and number will not appear in the same line.
      Page numbers may be supplied, and should then be tagged by the attribute <x>rend="supplied"</x>, and rendered in square brackets.
      <tit>SKS-E</tit> render page numbers on demand. They are furthermore used to compile concordances.</sem>
     <sem on="TEI">Pagebreaks in KN1 is only permitted in coherent text, i.e. inside paragraphs or blocks, not in between, as allowed in TEI.
      The placement is retained in TEI, hence we will see that the pagebreak does not occur until after the coherent text of a section starts, and after possible decorations and the like, which may lead to a false understanding of on which page it appears.
      This has also lead to the frequent placement of page breaks in headers or list labels whenever these appears as the first text on a page.
     <!--<red.note>Overvej at flytte sidetallene ud mellem <tag>div</tag></red.note>-->
     </sem>
   </sekt>
  
   <sekt id="2.6.2">
    <rubrik>Commentary references</rubrik>
    <synx>
    <elem><name>ref</name>
     <html:br/>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary"
     <html:br/>
     <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="e"<sepa>]</sepa>
     <html:br/>
     <attr class="pointing">target</attr>="kom.xml#<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>number</meta>"
     <html:br/>
     <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>number</meta>"
    </elem>
   </synx>
     <sem>Marks the reference to a commentary. For every document of author text, <tit>SKS</tit> publishes a companion document of commentaries. To identify the annotated part in the text, the page and line number of the text are printed before the commentary together with a lemma, i.e. a short extract of the authors text.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><ref type="commentary" target="kom.xml#aa-1" xml:id="aa-1">Gilleleie</ref>.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kom id="aa-1">Gilleleie</kom>.</ex>
    <sem>When set at page 7, line 1 of SKS-B, it will give rise to a
commentary in vol. K18, as follows:</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><note type="commentary" xml:id="aa-1" n="7,1"> <label><hi rendition="#bol">Gilleleie</hi></label> <p>Gilleleje, fiskerleje [...]</p> </note></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><k id="aa-1" side="7" linie="1" nr="1"> <lemma><fed>Gilleleie</fed></lemma> <klin>Gilleleje, fiskerleje [...]</klin> </k></ex>
    <sem>The encoding of the commentary itself follows from <refsekt id="3.8"/>. The two documents are linked by the <x>target</x> / <x>xml:id</x> attribute. The page/line number pair was determined from the occurrence of the start tag (the start of the
lemmas first word) at the time when <tit>SKS-B</tit> was set. The end tag is preferred to appear at the end of lemma, this can not always be realised, however.
    Readers with special interest in the establishment of the lemma / commentary linking in <tit>SKS</tit> are referred to <reflit id="KN1"/>.
    Note that this encoding anticipates that the commentary document is called <x>kom.xml</x> and is placed alongside the referring document.</sem>
    <sem>The subtype <x>"e"</x> signals that this commentary appears in <tit>SKS-E</tit> only.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><ref type="commentary" subtype="e" target="#bb-450" xml:id="bb-450">63. Faustus</ref> ein Gedicht in lyrischer Form</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kom x="e" id="bb-450">63. Faustus</kom> ein Gedicht in lyrischer Form</ex>
   </sekt>
  
   <sekt id="2.6.3">
    <rubrik>Shaft references</rubrik>
    <synx>
    <elem><name>ref</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="shaft"
     <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>shaft id</meta>"
    </elem>
   </synx>
    <sem>Marks references for orthogonal data structures linking parallel
layers of text, so-called shafts.
    The idea is basically to supply parallel texts in diferent documents with the same shaft reference, e.g. the print version of <tit>Preface</tit> and two drafts for the same work:</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><seg type="shaft" xml:id="f-008-2">høre Posthornets Lyd og Echos vinkende Indbydelse,</seg></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><skakt id="f-008-2">h<e name="o-">ø</e>re Posthornets Lyd og Echos vinkende Indbydelse,</skakt></ex>
    <ex gen="-sks"><seg type="shaft" xml:id="f-008-2">at hilse Echos vinkende Indbydelse med et Fingerkys.</seg></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><skakt id="f-008-2a">at hilse Echos vinkende Indbydelse med et Fingerkys.</skakt></ex>
    <ex gen="-sks"><seg type="shaft" xml:id="f-008-2">høre Posthornets Lyd og Echo som vinker ad Een,</seg></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><skakt id="f-008-2b">h<e name="o-">ø</e>re Posthornets Lyd og Echo som vinker ad Een,</skakt></ex>
     <sem>Parallel layes has not been implemented in <tit>SKS-E</tit> and shafts are not marked except for a few experimental cases.
    Readers with special interest in parallel text linking are referred to <reflit id="KN1"/>. A short introduction is given in <reflit id="skakt"/> which also contains a further reference list. 
     </sem>
   </sekt>
  
   <sekt id="2.6.4">
    <rubrik>Page references</rubrik>
    <synx>
    <elem><name>ref</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="page"
     <attr class="pointing">target</attr>="<meta>document</meta>#s<meta>page number</meta>"
     <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>SKS page number</meta>"
    </elem>
   </synx>
    <sem>Marks the authors own references to pages in own writings, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">cfr. p. <ref type="page" target="#s163">163</ref> i denne Bog.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">cfr. p. <refs id="163">163</refs> i denne Bog.</ex>    
    <sem>The reference may be to another work, e.g. <tit>Stages on the Lifes Way</tit></sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">(cfr. »Stadier paa Livets Vei« <hi rendition="#ant">P.</hi>
	
               <ref type="page" target="../slv/txt.xml#s340">340</ref> o. ff. § 3).</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">(cfr. »Stadier paa Livets Vei« <ant>P.</ant>
	<refs tit="slv" id="340">340</refs> o. ff. <e name="pgf">§</e> 3).</ex>
    <sem>Note that this linking anticipates that the said work is placed in a file <tit>txt.xml</tit> in a neighbouring folder called <tit>slv</tit>.</sem>
     <sem>Such numbers are for convenience substituted with the page numbers of <tit>SKS</tit> in the contents table of <tit>SKS-B</tit>, cf. <reflit id="Retningslinier/ts"/> 2.9.2. This value is stored in the <x>n</x> attribute for this reason, see example in <refsekt id="2.3.10"/>. <tit>SKS-E</tit> links to the page in question.</sem>
   </sekt>
  
  </sekt>

 </sekt>
 
 <sekt id="3">
  <rubrik>Document structure</rubrik>
  <sem>Until now the coherent text content has been described. The rest of
this paper will deal with the elements that structure the text. The
description continues <s.k.>bottom up</s.k.>, i.e. just as the previous section
started describing the individual characters and went on with
compound elements, this section describes first the lowest level of
structuring concepts: a paragraph and ends up describing the entire
TEI document.</sem>

  <sekt id="3.1">
   <rubrik>Lines</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>p</name>
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"
   </elem>
    <meta>coherent text</meta>
    <elem>/p</elem>
  </synx>
    <html:br/>
  <synx>
   <elem>p
      <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="decoration"
   </elem>
   <elem>figure
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="<meta>decoration</meta>"/</elem>
   <elem>/p</elem>
  </synx>

	 <sem>Marks lines of coherent text delimited by semantically significant line breaks, also called
paragraphs.</sem>
   <sem>The text may be indented in various ways as given by the attribute <x>rendition</x>, corresponding to statements in the <tag>teiHeader</tag> of the document, e.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks"><rendition xml:id="ind" selector="p,l,cell">text-indent: 1em</rendition></ex>
   <sem>The most important values of <x>rendition</x> are:</sem>
	 <ex vis="vert" gen="-kn1">
    <lin ryk="init"><typ art="init">A</typ>bc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#init</x>: left jusitfied with initial letter</forkl>
    <lin ryk="ind">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#ind</x>: short indentation (1 em) of first line</forkl>
    <lin ryk="ind2">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#ind2</x>: long indentation (2 em) of first line</forkl>
    <lin ryk="ud">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#ud</x>: short indentation of following but first line (hanging indentation)</forkl>
    <!--lin ryk="indud">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x></x>: short indentation followed by hanging indentation</forkl-->
	  <lin ryk="kort">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#kort</x>: short indentation (1 em) of all lines</forkl>
	  <lin ryk="lang">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#lang</x>: long indentation of all lines</forkl>
	  <lin ryk="xlang">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#xlang</x>: extra long indentation of all lines</forkl>
	  <!--lin ryk="kortind">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x></x>: short indentation all lines and furthermore short indentation of first line</forkl>
	  <lin ryk="langind">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#langind</x>: long indentation all lines and furthermore short indentation of first line</forkl>
	  <lin ryk="xlangind">Abc defg hijkl mnop qrs tu vw xy z æøå ...</lin> <forkl><x>#xlangind</x>: extra long indentation all lines and furthermore short indentation of first line</forkl-->
	  <lin ryk="cen">Abc</lin> <forkl><x>#cen</x>: centering</forkl>
    <lin ryk="bag">Abc</lin> <forkl><x>#bag</x>: right justification</forkl>
    <lin ryk="bagind">Abc</lin> <forkl><x>#bagind</x>: short indentation from right edge</forkl>
    <lin ryk="baglang">Abc</lin> <forkl><x>#baglang</x>: long indentation from right edge</forkl>
	 </ex>
	 <sem>A line may be empty (<tag>p</tag> element with no text content) and then carry a <term>decoration</term>.
	   Such a decoration, with may especially be blank, is marked with a <tag>figure</tag> element of a given <x>type</x>:</sem>
	 <ex vis="vert" gen="-kn1">
    <lin dek="klum"/> <forkl><x>columnRuler</x>: ruler of the width of the column</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="skil"/> <forkl><x>divisionRuler</x>: division ruler, 4 ems</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="dobskil"/> <forkl><x>divisionRulerDouble</x>: double division ruler</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="skilbag"/> <forkl><x>divisionRulerRight</x>: division ruler, right justified</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="ast"/> <forkl><x>asterisk</x>: asterisk</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="ast2"/> <forkl><x>2asterisks</x>: 2 asterisks</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="ast3"/> <forkl><x>3asterisks</x>: 3 asterisks</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="ast3op"/> <forkl><x>3asterisksUp</x>: 3 asterisks, central elevated</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="ast3ned"/> <forkl><x>3asterisksDown</x>: 3 asterisks, central lowered</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="dobkors"/> <forkl><x>hash</x>: double cross</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="edobkors"/> <forkl><x>hashSingleDouble</x>: cross with single vertikal, double horizontal bar</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="dobstreg"/> <forkl><x>dashDouble</x>: double dash</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="blg"/> <forkl><x>wave</x>: wave</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="blgskil"/> <forkl><x>divisionRulerWaved</x>: waved division line</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="blgskilpunkt"/> <forkl><x>divisionRulerWavedPoint</x>: waved line with full stop</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="S"/> <forkl><x>hashEntwined</x>: Omslynget dobbeltkors</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="kors"/> <forkl><x>cross</x>: cross</forkl>	 
    <lin dek="blank"/> <forkl><x>blank</x>: blank line</forkl>	 
	 </ex>
	 <sem>Examples: Under a centered heading a paragraph starts with the first line indented:</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rendition="#cen">Anlæg.</p>
	
            <p rendition="#ind">Et Msk. har i sin tidlige Ungdom engang ladet sig i en exalteret Tilstand henrive til at besøge et offentlig Fruentimer.</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="cen">Anl<e name="ae">æ</e>g.</lin>
	<lin ryk="ind">Et Msk. har i sin tidlige Ungdom engang ladet sig i en exalteret Tilstand henrive til at bes<e name="o-">ø</e>ge et offentlig Fruentimer.</lin></ex>
	 <sem>All lines of a paragraph is indented except the first one (hanging indentation):</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rendition="#ud">»Das Buch, Schimpf und Ernst genannt, welches durchläuft der Welt Handel mit viel schönen und kurzweilichen Exempeln und Gleichnissen, Parabeln und Historien« etc. Augsburg 1536. Fol.</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="ud">»Das Buch, Schimpf und Ernst genannt, welches durchläuft der Welt Handel mit viel schönen und kurzweilichen Exempeln und Gleichnissen, Parabeln und Historien« etc. Augsburg 1536. Fol.</lin></ex>
	 <sem>All lines are long indented:</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rendition="#lang">Idet jeg afskriver det Foregaaende er det ikke fordi jeg troer, at der er sagt noget stort dermed; men fordi det fornøier mig at see, at en Deel af de Bemærkninger der findes stemme væsentlig overeens med hvad jeg ved senere Læsning af <persName key="Fichte, Johann Gottlieb">d. y: Fichte</persName> er stødt paa.</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="lang">Idet jeg afskriver det Foregaaende er det ikke fordi jeg troer, at der er sagt noget stort dermed; men fordi det forn<e name="o-">ø</e>ier mig at see, at en Deel af de Bem<e name="ae">æ</e>rkninger der findes stemme v<e name="ae">æ</e>sentlig overeens med hvad jeg ved senere L<e name="ae">æ</e>sning af <pers norm="Fichte, Johann Gottlieb">d. y: Fichte</pers> er st<e name="o-">ø</e>dt paa.</lin></ex>
	 <sem>Long indentation often designates <term>lyrics</term> (also note <tag>lg</tag>, however, <refsekt id="3.2"/>).</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rendition="#lang">Da kom paa Hesten trap trap trap</p>
	
            <p rendition="#lang">Jens Skovfod ridende saa rap.</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="lang">Da kom paa Hesten trap trap trap</lin>
	<lin ryk="lang">Jens Skovfod ridende saa rap.</lin></ex>
	 <sem>Datings are often long indented from the right, see example of <refsekt id="3.6"/>.</sem>
	 <sem>Generally a <tag>p</tag> with no text content signals a break in the text, typically an empty line:</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rend="decoration">
               <figure type="blank"/>
            </p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin dek="blank"/></ex>
	 <sem>or a decoration like a division ruler:</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks"><p rendition="#cen">Forholdet mellem Enten – Eller og</p>
	
            <p rendition="#cen">Stadierne.</p>
	
            <p rend="decoration">
               <figure type="divisionRuler"/>
            </p>
	
            <p>I Enten – Eller var det æsthetiske Moment et Nærværende kæmpende med det Ethiske, og det Ethiske Valget ud deraf.</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin ryk="cen">Forholdet mellem Enten – Eller og</lin>
	<lin ryk="cen">Stadierne.</lin>
	<lin dek="skil"/>
	<lin>I Enten – Eller var det <e name="ae">æ</e>sthetiske Moment et N<e name="ae">æ</e>rv<e name="ae">æ</e>rende k<e name="ae">æ</e>mpende med det Ethiske, og det Ethiske Valget ud deraf.</lin></ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.2">
   <rubrik>Blocks</rubrik>
   <sem>By a <term>block</term> is understood different from a paragraph, such as a <term>table</term>, <term>lyrics</term>, or <term>label</term>.</sem>
   
   <sekt id="3.2.1">
    <rubrik>Table</rubrik>
  <synx>
    <elem><name>table</name></elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;{<elem><name>row</name></elem>
    {<elem><name>cell</name>
      <attr class="tableDecoration">cols</attr>="<meta>n</meta>"
      <attr class="tableDecoration">rows</attr>="<meta>n</meta>"
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#<meta>indent | border</meta>"</elem>}
    <tag>/row</tag>}
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/table</tag>
  </synx>

    <sem>Inside a table each line consists of a number of <tag>cell</tag> elements. The
attribute <x>cols</x> indicates that the element should span over a
number of columns in the line. Likewise <x>rows</x> may indicate that the element should span over a number of lines in the column. 
      The content of each <tag>cell</tag> element may be centered, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
     <table>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell cols="2">En Bestaaen <hi rendition="#spa">ved sig</hi>
         </cell>
      </row>	
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell cols="2">En Bestaaen <hi rendition="#spa">for sig</hi> (Individualitet)</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell>Receptivitet</cell>
         <cell>Spontaneitet.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell>1.</cell>
         <cell cols="2" rendition="#cen">
            <hi rendition="#spa">Krystal.</hi>
         </cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell cols="2" rendition="#cen">(Production)</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell>2.</cell>
         <cell cols="2" rendition="#cen">
            <hi rendition="#spa">Plante.</hi>
         </cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell cols="2" rendition="#cen">(Reproduction)</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell>Absorption</cell>
         <cell>Secretion.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell/>
         <cell>a) til Ernæring.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell/>
         <cell>b) Secretion</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
         <cell/>
         <cell/>
         <cell>c) Excretion.</cell>
      </row>
    </table>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><blok ryk="tab">
	<lin><tab/><tab klumspan="2">En Bestaaen <spa>ved sig</spa></tab></lin>

	<lin><tab/><tab klumspan="2">En Bestaaen <spa>for sig</spa> (Individualitet)</tab></lin>

	<lin><tab/><tab>Receptivitet</tab><tab>Spontaneitet.</tab></lin>
 
	<lin><tab>1.</tab><tab klumspan="2" ryk="cen"><spa>Krystal.</spa></tab></lin>
 
	<lin><tab/><tab klumspan="2" ryk="cen">(Production)</tab></lin>
 
	<lin><tab>2.</tab><tab klumspan="2" ryk="cen"><spa>Plante.</spa></tab></lin>

	<lin><tab/><tab klumspan="2" ryk="cen">(Reproduction)</tab></lin>

	<lin><tab/><tab>Absorption</tab><tab>Secretion.</tab></lin>

	<lin><tab/><tab/><tab>a) til Ern<e name="ae">æ</e>ring.</tab></lin>
	<lin><tab/><tab/><tab>b) Secretion</tab></lin>
	<lin><tab/><tab/><tab>c) Excretion.</tab></lin>

    </blok></ex>
    <sem>A table cell may be bordered by a line or an accolade which is specifiede by the <x>rendition</x> attribute, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <table>
        <row>
          <cell>Ontologie</cell>
          <cell rows="2" rendition="#venstreark-ind">Disses Vished er den absolute – her er Tænken
      og Væren eet, men til Gjengjeld er disse Videnskaber Hypotheser.</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>Mathematik.</cell>
        </row>
      </table>
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><blok ryk="tab">
     <lin><tab>Ontologie</tab><tab linspan="2" venstre="ark-ind">Disses Vished er den absolute – her er Tænken
      og Væren eet, men til Gjengjeld er disse Videnskaber Hypotheser.</tab></lin>
     <lin><tab>Mathematik.</tab></lin>
    </blok></ex>
     <sem>To this reference belongs a <tag>rendition</tag> element in the Tei header:</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">
       <rendition selector="cell" scheme="css" xml:id="venstreark-ind">border-left:thin solid</rendition><!--accolade pointing in-->
     </ex>
     <sem>As the css sceme can not specify accolades, it has to be added as an xml comment. </sem>
   </sekt>
   
   <sekt id="3.2.2">
    <rubrik>Opposite</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>table</name>
      <attr class="table">rows</attr>="1"
      <attr class="global.rendition">cols</attr>="2"
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#udspark"
   </elem>
    <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>row</name></elem>
    <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>cell</name>
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="#<meta>left indent</meta>"
   </elem>
   <tag>cell
      rendition="#<meta>right indent</meta>"
   </tag>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<elem>/row</elem>
    <html:br/>
    <elem>/table</elem>
    <html:br/>
  </synx>
     <html:br/><html:br/>
     <synx>
       <elem><name>rendition</name>
         <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="udspark"
         <attr>selector</attr>="table"
         <attr class="styleDef">scheme</attr>="css"
       </elem>
       <x>width:100%</x>
       <elem>/rendition</elem>
     </synx>
    <sem>Marks the special typesetting where two texts pieces are placed at each end of a line.
      The <tag>table</tag> element must contain one <tag>row</tag> element containing excactly two <tag>cell</tag> elements, which may in turn bear attributes determining a possible indention from the margin.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><table cols="2" rows="1" rendition="#udspark">
      
                  <row>
       
                     <cell rendition="#ind">Den 11te Januar.</cell>
       
                     <cell rendition="#bagind">S. Kierkegaard:</cell>
      
                  </row>
     
               </table></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <blok ryk="udspark">
      <lin>
       <tab ryk="ind">Den 11te Januar.</tab>
       <tab ryk="bagind">S. Kierkegaard:</tab>
      </lin>
     </blok>
    </ex>
     <sem on="TEI">Note that the difference between this and the general <tag>table</tag> element of <refsekt id="3.2.1"/> is that the cells span over the entire page. Normally typesetting would place two cells in a row as close as possible after each other indented to the left margin.</sem>
   </sekt>
   
   <sekt id="3.2.3">
    <rubrik>Label</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>div</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="label"
   </elem>
    { <elem><name>p</name></elem> }
   <elem>/div</elem>
  </synx>
    <sem>Marks a label on the front of a book.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks"><div type="label">
      <p rendition="#cen">
         <milestone unit="unnumbered" edRef="#Pap."/>
         <pb xml:id="ss7" edRef="#SKS" n="7"/>
         <ptr type="figure" target="txr.xml#ill_k1"/>
         <hi rendition="#size6">
            <app>
               <lem>NB<witDetail wit="#Ms">etiket på bindets forside</witDetail>
               </lem>
            </app>
         </hi>
      </p>
               </div></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><blok ryk="etiket">
<lin ryk="cen"><kor kil="Pap" id="0"/><kor kil="SKS" id="7"/><refi id="k1"/><gra str="+6"><tn>NB<udg spec="fri" txt="etiket på bindets forside"/></tn></gra></lin>
</blok>
</ex></sekt>
   
   <sekt id="3.2.4">
    <rubrik>Lyrics</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>lg</name></elem>
    { <elem><name>l</name></elem> }
   <elem>/lg</elem>
  </synx>
    <sem>Marks verse or lyrics, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <lg>
        <l>Hvert Hjert' er Garn,</l>
        <l>Hver Skalk som Barn,</l>
        <l>Hvert Løfte som en Skygge.</l>
     </lg>
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><blok ryk="lyrik">
	  <lin>Hvert Hjert' er Garn,</lin>
	  <lin>Hver Skalk som Barn,</lin>
	  <lin>Hvert L<e name="o-">ø</e>fte som en Skygge.</lin>
	</blok></ex>
	<sem>This encoding is intended for a uniform rendering of printed works.
	  At other occasions where the authors own spatial arrangement has been considered more important, the indentation has been be encoded explicitly, see <refsekt id="3.1"/>.</sem>
   </sekt>
  </sekt>
     
  <sekt id="3.3">
   <rubrik>Notes</rubrik>
  <synx>
    <elem><name>note</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="author"
      <html:br/>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="subnote"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="">place</attr>="bottom <sepa>|</sepa> margin"
      <html:br/>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="">anchored</attr>="true <sepa>|</sepa> false"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="">xml:id</attr>="<meta>id</meta>"</elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><elem><name>seg</name>
      type="refMarker"</elem>
    <meta>digit <sepa>|</sepa> litra</meta>
    <tag>/seg</tag><sepa>]</sepa>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><elem><name>p</name></elem>
    <meta>note text</meta>
    <tag>/p</tag><sepa>}</sepa>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/note</tag>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks the authors footnotes and marginal entries.
     Any note is associated with a reference or pointer within the ordinary text of the same type, see <refsekt id="2.5.1"/>.</sem>
   <sem>Footnotes of printed texts are typeset at the bottom of the page in <tit>SKS-B</tit> and a number, unique for each page is generated as a reference marker.
     In <tit>SKS-E</tit> the notes are displayed immediately after the referrence, marked with an asterisk.
     The notes are coded as end notes after the chapters of the dokument, see <refsekt id="3.9.1"/>.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
    <note type="author" place="bottom" xml:id="lp.15">
    <p><hi rendition="#ant">Sed nimis arta premunt olidae convivia caprae.</hi></p>
    </note>
   </ex>
	 <sem>The rendering can be seen in <refsekt id="2.5.1"/>.</sem>
	 <sem>Notes in the <term>main column</term> of journals and papers are encoded at the bottom of the column, see <refsekt id="3.6.1"/>.
	   <tit>SKS-E</tit> displays the notes at the same place.
	   In <tit>SKS-B</tit> the notes are typeset at the bottom of the page or at the end of the main entry, whichever occurs first.
	   Notes that originates from <tit>EP</tit> is handled like column notes but rendered slightly different.</sem>
	 <sem>Marginal notes are encoded in the <term>marginal column</term>, <refsekt id="3.6.1"/>.
	   The notes are displayed in a marginal column with the <term>reference marker</term>.</sem>
	 <sem>Reference markers of jounals and papers is determined from the <tag>seg type="refMarker"</tag> element.
	   Such markes may be missing from the ms text, the ms note or both places.
	   Out of consideration for the general reference system of <tit>SKS</tit> all <tag>note type="author"</tag> elements are normally equipped with a reference marker, possible supplied by the editor, even in the case where the corresponding marker in the  <tag>ref</tag> element is not supplied; these cases are encoded with the attribute <x>anchored="false"</x> and the marker is italicesed in the note in addition to the usual highlighting of editors supplement <refsekt id="2.3.11.2"/>.</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks">
	   <note type="author" place="margin" anchored="false" xml:id="jj-108.a">
      <seg type="refMarker"><supplied>a</supplied></seg>
      <p>Mskene forstaae sig meget lidt paa hvad det Gode er. De vide Beskeed om Veier og Vind [...]</p>
     </note>
	 </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><ms>
	<not type="mu" id="JJ-108.a"><indv><udg spec="supp">a</udg></indv>
	<lin>Mskene forstaae sig meget lidt paa hvad det Gode er. De vide Beskeed om Veier og Vind [...]</lin></not></ms></ex>
    <sem>Notes may refer notes, in which case the latter will be subtyped <x>"subnotes"</x>. They are rendered with a smaller font size.</sem>
  </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.4">
    <rubrik>Illustrations</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>figure</name>
      <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>id</meta>"
      <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="recto<sepa>|</sepa>verso<sepa>|</sepa>opening<sepa>|</sepa>separate"
      </elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>graphic</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>head</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/figure</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>Marks an illustration an contains as such a graphic file. (<tag>graphic</tag>, <refsekt id="3.4.1"/>) and a caption (<tag>head</tag>).
      The <x>xml:id</x> specifies the illustration number of the respective volume.
      Illustrations in the commentary volumes are prefixed <x>k</x>.
      The <x>rend</x> attribute specifies the placement of the illustration in <tit>SKS-B</tit>:</sem>
     <sem><x>"recto"</x> places the illustration on the first following right page.
      <html:br/>
      <x>"verso"</x>  places the illustration at the latest previous page shift if this is to a left page (in which case the reference will appear on the opposite right page), otherwise on the first following left page.
      <html:br/>
      <x>"opening"</x> designates one picture occupying an opening in the book. The illustration is placed on the first following left and following right page; the pictures are placed close as possible to the inner edge.
      <html:br/>
      <x>"separate"</x> designates two separate pictures which is nevertheless to be placed placed on the first following left and following right page; the pictures are placed with the usual inner margin.
    </sem>
     <sem>In the authors text where the illustrations show facsimiles of the page, the figure element is encoded at the page start, immediately after the <tag>pb/</tag> and rendered in <tit>SKS-E</tit> with a clickable text <html:i>fax</html:i>; if the illustration is relevant to other locations, a pointer may be used, see <refsekt id="2.5.4"/>.
     Note that the <tag>pb</tag> tag has a reference <x>facs</x> to the same picture file, cf. <refsekt id="2.6.1"/>.
     </sem>
       <ex gen="-sks"><pb xml:id="s173" n="173" facs="../jj/ill_5.jpg"/>
          <figure xml:id="ill_5" rend="verso">
            <graphic url="../jj/ill_5.jpg"/>
            <head>Journalen JJ, s. 173 (JJ:319-320)</head>
          </figure>
          Stundom bliver man utaalmodig, fordi det ikke lykkes bedre med at ville det Gode, men denne Utaalmodighed er dog ikke Sorg over sin Synd, men Voldsgjerning mod Gud.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><lin><kor id="173"/><refi><ill id="5" tving="recto"><illfil id="SKS-18-5.jpg"/><lin>Journalen JJ, s. 173 (JJ:319-320)</lin></ill></refi>Stundom bliver man utaalmodig, fordi det ikke lykkes bedre med at ville det Gode, men denne Utaalmodighed er dog ikke Sorg over sin Synd, men Voldsgjerning mod Gud.</lin></ex>
     <sem>In a commentary, the element typically occurs at the first place of reference, e.g.</sem>
<ex gen="-sks">
      <hi rendition="#ita">Corsaren</hi> bragte i 1846 en række satiriske artikler om, allusioner til og tegninger [...] af SK, nemlig [...] 16. jan. (nr. 278) (se <ref target="../NB/kom.xml#ill_k5" type="figure">illustration 5</ref>, [...]
      <figure xml:id="ill_k5" rend="recto">
          <graphic url="../nb/ill_k5.jpg"/>
          <head>5. Peter Klæstrups karikatur i <hi rendition="#ita">Corsaren</hi>, nr. 278, den 16. jan. 1846</head>
      </figure>
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kur>Corsaren</kur> bragte i 1846 en r<e name="ae">æ</e>kke satiriske artikler om, allusioner til og tegninger [...] af SK, nemlig [...] 16. jan. (nr. 278) (se <refx type="ill" tit="NB" id="k5">illustration 5</refx>,</ex>

    <sekt id="3.4.1">
     <rubrik>Graphics file</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>graphic</name>
      <attr class="resourced">url</attr>="<meta>id</meta>"
      </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>Pointer to a graphics file belonging to an illustration.
       <!--If not present, the file name must be implied by the short title of the document and the figure id.
     <red.note>Tjek at der altid er en <tag>graphic</tag></red.note>--></sem>
    </sekt>
    
   </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.5">
   <rubrik>Chapter and rubric</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="chapter"
     <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="col2"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="<sepa>(</sepa> newPage<sepa>|</sepa>recto<sepa>|</sepa>verso <sepa>)</sepa>
     <sepa>(</sepa> long<sepa>|</sepa>short <sepa>)</sepa>"
   </elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;[<elem><name>head</name>
      type="topText"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>top text</meta>"
    /</elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;[<tag>head
      type="topText"
      subtype="versoPage"
      n="<meta>left page top text</meta>"
    /</tag>]]
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;[<elem>head
      <attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>level</meta>"
    </elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>l</name>
      rendition="<meta>alignment</meta>"
    </elem>
    <meta>rubric</meta>
    <tag>/l</tag>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<tag>/head</tag>]
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/> &#x2003;{<elem><name>p</name></elem>|<elem><name>table</name></elem>|<elem><name>lg</name></elem>}
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/>
&#x2003;{<tag>div type="chapter"</tag>}
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/div</tag>
  </synx>

	 <sem>Marks the content text of a <term>printed text</term> such as it appears divided by semantically significant page breaks and <term>rubrics</term>.
	   A chapter consist of a number of headings, followed by <term>lines</term> or <term>blocks</term> as described above, and possibly other (sub)chapters.
	   A chapter thus comprises larger or smaller text divisions.</sem>
	 <sem>Thus, a chapter appears for every forced page break (<x>rend="newPage"</x>) especially when starting at a left (<x>"verso"</x>) or right page (<x>"recto"</x>). <x>"blankVerso"</x> marks a right page whose corresponding left page must be blank.</sem>
	 <sem>The first page of the chapter may be vertically indented as further specified by the <x>rend</x> attribute as <x>"long"</x> or <x>"short"</x>.</sem>
	 <sem>Newspaper articles is further attributed <x>subtype="col2"</x>, signalling that <tit>SKS-B</tit> should render this in two columns, starting in a new left hand column.
	   <tit>SKS-E</tit> renders this in one column with a fixed, smaller width.</sem>
	 <sem>A chapter may define the top text as it is typeset above right hand pages of <tit>SKS-B</tit>. Similarly, the capitalised top text on the left hand pages may be defined; if it is not, it will be produced from the <tag>title</tag> element in the TEI header.
	 Such text are defined by the <x>n</x> attribute of a <tag>head type="topText"</tag> element, <x>subtype="versoPage"</x> as relevant.</sem>
    <sem on="TEI">As the top texts are solely a matter of typesetting and not a part of the copy-text, an attribute is to be preferred for this purpose, in contrast to the following rubric.</sem>

	 <sem>A chapter may be headed by a rubric, consisting of one or more lines (<tag>l</tag>) serving as head lines for the chapter.
	   The vertical delimiters of the rubric, determining the level of the chapter, may be given by a <x>rendition</x> attribute for <tag>head</tag>. The following renditions apply:</sem>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>rendition</name>
        <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="niv1"
        <attr>selector</attr>="head"
        <attr class="styleDef">scheme</attr>="css"
      </elem>
      <x>margin-top: 2em; margin-bottom: 1em</x>
      <tag>/rendition</tag> <!-- default rendition -->
      <html:br/>
      <tag>rendition
        xml:id="niv0"
        selector="head"
        scheme="css"
      </tag>
      <x>margin-top: 1em; margin-bottom: 0em</x>
      <tag>/rendition</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>rendition
        xml:id="niv00"
        selector="head"
        scheme="css"
      </tag>
      <x>margin-top: 0; margin-bottom: 0</x>
      <tag>/rendition</tag>
    </synx>
    
    <sem>E.g.</sem>  
	 <ex gen="-sks">
    <div type="chapter" rend="recto short"><head type="topText" n="Lectori benevolo!"/>
      <head rendition="#niv1">
        <l rendition="#cen"><hi rendition="#size1"><hi rendition="#ant"><hi rendition="#bol">Lectori  benevolo!</hi></hi></hi></l>
      </head>
      <p rendition="#init"><hi rendition="#size0 #lineHight1"><hi rendition="#initTyp">S</hi>aasom  og eftersom der skal være Redelighed udi Alt, besynderligt  da udi Sandhedens Rige og Bogverdenen, samt at ingen velfornemme Professor [...]
      </hi></p></div>
	 </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kap tving="recto" ryk="kort" klum="Lectori benevolo!" sp="1">
      <rub niv="1">
        <lin ryk="cen"><gra str="+1"><ant><fed>Lectori  benevolo!</fed></ant></gra></lin>
      </rub>
      <lin ryk="init"><gra str="0" skyd="+1"><typ art="init">S</typ>aasom  og eftersom der skal være Redelighed udi Alt, besynderligt  da udi Sandhedens Rige og Bogverdenen, samt at ingen velfornemme Professor [...]</gra></lin></kap></ex>
	
	<sem>If a chapter have a content of its own in addition to subchapters, the former must appear collected and first as paragraphs (<refsekt id="3.1"/>) or other block elements (<refsekt id="3.2"/>).
	  Content appearing <em>after</em> a subchapter <tag>div</tag> element is wrapped in a separate subchapter.
	  In the following example (the end of <tit>Forord</tit> (Prefaces)) the text under the division ruler is supposed to belong as a fourth subchapter under chapter VIII, and <tit>Efterskrift</tit> the entire work, after VIII.</sem>
	<ex gen="-sks"> 
	  <div type="chapter" rend="newPage short"><head type="topText" n="VIII"/>
	    <head>
        <l rendition="#cen">VIII</l>
      </head>
      <p rendition="#xlang">Hvad jeg forudsiger, det vil enten skee, eller det vil ikke skee;</p>
      <p rendition="#xlang">thi Apollo har forundt mig Prophetiens Gave.</p>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head>
          <l rendition="#cen">§ 1</l>
        </head>
        <p>At begynde et philosophisk Tidsskrift i Danmark, kan ikke blot synes at være, men er i Sandhed en betænkelig Sag; [...]</p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head>
          <l rendition="#cen">§ 2</l>
        </head>
        <p>Hvor glædeligt det end er, at see Philosophien udbrede sig trindt i Landet, [...]</p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <head>
          <l rendition="#cen">§ 3</l>
        </head>
        <p>Da Læseren kjender min Hensigt, saa kjender han ogsaa min Forventning; [...]</p>
        <p rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></p>
        <p rend="decoration"><figure type="divisionRuler"/></p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter">
        <p rendition="#ind">I det Foregaaende har jeg stræbt [...]</p>
      </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" rend="newPage short"><head type="topText" n="Efterskrift"/>
        <head>
          <l rendition="#cen">Efterskrift</l>
        </head>
        <p rendition="#ind">Det behøves vel neppe at siges, at denne Morskabslæsning umueligen, det er: uden at alle Erfaringer og Begreber omstødes, vil kunne begynde Strid og Trætte; thi Forord bryder jo ingen Trætte</p>
    </div>

	</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
<kap tving="nyside" ryk="kort" klum="VIII">
 <rub>
  <lin ryk="cen">VIII</lin>
 </rub>
  <lin ryk="xlang">Hvad jeg forudsiger det vil enten skee, eller det vil ikke skee;</lin>
  <lin ryk="xlang">thi Apollo har forundt mig Prophetiens Gave.</lin>

 <kap>
  <rub>
   <lin ryk="cen">§ 1</lin>
  </rub>
  <lin>At begynde et philosophisk Tidsskrift i Danmark, kan ikke blot synes at være, men er i Sandhed en betænkelig Sag; [...]</lin>
 </kap>

 <kap>
  <rub>
   <lin ryk="cen">§ 2</lin>
  </rub>
  <lin>Hvor glædeligt det end er, at see Philosophien udbrede sig trindt i Landet, [...]</lin>
 </kap>

 <kap>
  <rub>
   <lin ryk="cen">§ 3</lin>
  </rub>
  <lin>Da Læseren kjender min Hensigt, saa kjender han ogsaa min Forventning; [...]</lin>
   <lin dek="blank"/>
  <lin dek="skil"/>
 </kap>

 <kap>
   <lin ryk="ind">I det Foregaaende har jeg str<e name="ae">æ</e>bt [...]</lin>
 </kap>
</kap>

<kap tving="nyside" ryk="kort">
 <rub>
  <lin ryk="cen">Efterskrift</lin>
 </rub>
 <lin ryk="ind">Det beh<e name="o-">ø</e>ves vel neppe at siges, at denne Morskabsl<e name="ae">æ</e>sning umueligen, det er: uden at alle Erfaringer og Begreber omst<e name="o-">ø</e>des, vil kunne begynde Strid og Tr<e name="ae">æ</e>tte; thi Forord bryder jo ingen Tr<e name="ae">æ</e>tte</lin>
</kap></ex>
    <sem on="TEI">As it is in KN1, TEI does not allow paragraph-like elements to appear in <tag>div</tag> elements after a <tag>div</tag>.
      A <tag>postscript</tag> or similar <cit>model.divBottom</cit> element would have been appropriate, though, see <reflit id="TEI"/> app. C, div for details.</sem>

   <sem>Newpaper articles are typeset right justified in two columns.
     This is hardly implementable on a screen, why <tit>SKS-E</tit> in stead renders the text in a single, somewhat narrower column.
     In stead of the verso page top text explained above, this title is displayed in a navigation bar. The rest of the bar consist of the chapters rubric or, in absence of such, the recto page top text or, in the absence of both, the first words of the text. E.g.</sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
      <div type="chapter" subtype="col2" rend="newPage"><head type="topText" n="Fædrelandet · 25. juli 1848" subtype="versoPage"/><head type="topText" n="Krisen og en Krise. II"/>
      <head>
        <l rendition="#cen"><pb xml:id="s1493" n="1493"/><hi rendition="#size1"><hi rendition="#bol">Krisen og en Krise i en Skuespillerindes <choice><orig>Liv.</orig><reg>Liv</reg></choice></hi></hi></l>
      </head>
      <p rendition="#cen">II.</p>
      <p rendition="#init"><hi rendition="#initTyp">I</hi>eg tænker mig altsaa en Skuespillerinde i hendes første Begynden, i hendes tidlige Ungdoms første Lykke, i det Øieblik, da hun første Gang viste sig og første Gang gjorde glimrende Lykke. [...]</p></div>
      </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <kap sp="2" vklum="Fædrelandet · 25. juli 1848" klum="Krisen og en Krise. II" tving="nyside">
		
     <rub>
       <lin ryk="cen"><kor id="1493"/><gra str="+1"><fed>Krisen og en Krise i en Skuespillerindes <udg spec="stil" txt="Liv.">Liv</udg></fed></gra></lin>
     </rub> 
     <lin ryk="cen">II.</lin>
     <lin ryk="init"><typ art="init">I</typ>eg t<e name="ae">æ</e>nker mig altsaa en Skuespillerinde i hendes f<e name="o-">ø</e>rste Begynden, i hendes tidlige Ungdoms f<e name="o-">ø</e>rste Lykke, i det <e name="o-">ø</e>ieblik, da hun f<e name="o-">ø</e>rste Gang viste sig og f<e name="o-">ø</e>rste Gang gjorde glimrende Lykke. [...]</lin>
     </kap>
</ex>
    <sem>Finally an example from the <tit>Postscript</tit>:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
    <div type="chapter" rend="recto short"><head type="topText" n="Det subjektive Problem. Subjektets Forhold til Christendommens Sandhed, eller det at blive Christen"/>
      <head rendition="#niv1">
        <l rendition="#cen"><pb xml:id="s41" n="41" rend="supplied"/><pb edRef="#SV3" n="53"/><pb xml:id="ss63" edRef="#SKS" n="63"/>
          <hi rendition="#size4">Anden Deel</hi></l>
        <l rendition="#cen"><hi rendition="#size3">Det subjektive Problem. Subjektets Forhold til Christendommens Sandhed, eller det at blive Christen</hi></l>
      </head>
      <div type="chapter" rend="recto short"><head type="topText" n="Noget om Lessing"/>
        <head rendition="#niv1">
          <l rendition="#cen"><pb xml:id="s43" n="43" rend="supplied"/><pb edRef="#SV3" n="55"/><pb xml:id="ss65" edRef="#SKS" n="65"/>
            <hi rendition="#size4"><hi rendition="#spa">Første Afsnit</hi></hi></l>
          <l rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></l>
          <l rendition="#cen"><hi rendition="#size2">Noget om Lessing</hi></l>
        </head>
        <div type="chapter"><head type="topText" n="Yttring af Taknemlighed mod Lessing"/>
          <head rendition="#niv1">
            <l rendition="#cen"><hi rendition="#size2"><hi rendition="#bol"><choice><abbr>Cap.</abbr><expan>Capitel</expan></choice> 1</hi></hi></l>
            <l rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></l>
            <l rendition="#cen"><hi rendition="#size1">Yttring af Taknemlighed mod Lessing</hi></l>
          </head>
          <p rendition="#init"><hi rendition="#initTyp">D</hi>ersom en stakkels privatiserende Tænker, en spekulativ Grillefænger, der liig en fattig Logerende beboede et Tagkammer øverst oppe i en uhyre Bygning, [...]</p></div></div></div>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
  <kap tving="recto" ryk="kort">
    <rub>
    <lin ryk="cen"><kor kil="supp" id="41"/><kor kil="SV3" id="53"/><kor kil="SKS" id="63"/> <gra str="+4">Anden Deel</gra></lin>
    <lin ryk="cen"><gra str="+3">Det subjektive Problem. Subjektets Forhold til Christendommens Sandhed, eller det at blive Christen</gra></lin></rub>

  <kap tving="recto" ryk="kort">
    <rub>
    <lin ryk="cen"><kor kil="supp" id="43"/><kor kil="SV3" id="55"/><kor kil="SKS" id="65"/> <gra str="+4"><spa>F<e name="o-">ø</e>rste Afsnit</spa></gra></lin>
    <lin dek="blank"/>
    <lin ryk="cen"><gra str="+2">Noget om Lessing</gra></lin></rub>

  <kap klum="Yttring af Taknemlighed mod Lessing">

    <rub>
    <lin ryk="cen"><gra str="+2"><fed><fork opl="Capitel">Cap.</fork> 1</fed></gra></lin>
    <lin dek="blank"/>
    <lin ryk="cen"><gra str="+1">Yttring af Taknemlighed mod Lessing</gra></lin></rub>
    <lin ryk="init"><typ art="init">D</typ>ersom en stakkels privatiserende T<e name="ae">æ</e>nker, en spekulativ Grillef<e name="ae">æ</e>nger, der liig en fattig Logerende beboede et Tagkammer <e name="o-">ø</e>verst oppe i en uhyre Bygning, [...]</lin></kap></kap></kap>
   </ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.6">
   <rubrik>Entries</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="entry"
     <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="<sepa>(</sepa> newPage<sepa>|</sepa>recto<sepa>|</sepa>verso <sepa>|</sepa>newBlist <sepa>)</sepa>
     <sepa>(</sepa> long<sepa>|</sepa>short <sepa>)</sepa>"
   </elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<elem><name>dateline</name>
    </elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>date</name>
      <attr class="datable.w3c">when</attr>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="datable.w3c">notAfter</attr>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.responsibility">resp</attr>="#<meta>source</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
    /</elem>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;<tag>/dateline</tag>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;[<elem><name>head</name>
      type="topText"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>top text</meta>"
    /</elem>]
    <html:br/>
   &#x2003;[<elem><name>p</name>
      rend="decoration"
   </elem>
    <html:br/>
  &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>figure</name>
      type="<meta>decoration</meta>"/</elem>
    <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem>/p</elem>]
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/>
    &#x2003;[<tag>div
      type="marginalColumn"</tag>]
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/>
&#x2003;{<tag>div type="mainColumn"</tag>
    <html:br/>
&#x2003; [<tag>div type="marginalColumn"</tag>] }
    <html:br/>
    <html:br/>
    <tag>/div</tag>
  </synx>
   <sem>Marks separate entries of <term>journals and papers</term>.
     Entries are numbered by the <tit>SKS</tit> editors.
     Entries are always marked with a <term>date</term> and often separated from the previous one by a <term>decoration</term>.
     The placement on the pages and use of top texts is given as for chapters, see <refsekt id="3.5"/>.
     An entry typically consists of exactly one main column followed by a marginal column. Dependant on the rendering of the main column, these elements may occur several times, se below. 
</sem>
	 <sem>When a decoration is present, <tit>SKS-B</tit> should separate the entries with two blank lines. Between those the decoration is placed, unless this is of <x>type="blank"</x>. If leading decoration is absent, it is usually because the previous entry ends with a decoration which it is for various reasons important to assign to that entry (e.g. the consideration for a <tag>witEnd</tag> marking, see <refsekt id="2.5.3"/>). In this case the entry is separated from the previous one with a single blank line.</sem>
    <sem>The entry number is typeset in <tit>SKS-B</tit> in bold in the inner margin aligned with  the first line of the entry.
	   <tit>SKS-E</tit> displays the short title and number together with the leading words of the entry in a navigation bar.</sem>
	 <ex gen="-sks">
	   <div type="entry" n="115" xml:id="n115"><dateline><date when="18430517"/></dateline><p rend="decoration"><figure type="hash"/></p>
      <div type="mainColumn">
        <p rendition="#baglang"><date when="18430517">d. 17 Mai</date>.</p>
        <p rendition="#ind"><del>Havde jeg haft Tro, da var jeg bleven hos Regine. Gud skee Lov og Tak det har jeg nu indseet.</del></p></div></div>
	 </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><opt tit="JJ" nr="115" dek="dobkors" dat="18430517">
	<hs>
	<lin ryk="baglang"><dag dat="18430517">d. 17 Mai</dag>.</lin>
	<lin ryk="ind"><udg spec="slet">Havde jeg haft Tro, da var jeg bleven hos Regine. Gud skee Lov og Tak det har jeg nu indseet.</udg></lin></hs></opt></ex>
	
	 <sem>Dates are given on standardised form, see <refsekt id="2.4.1"/>. If an interval is needed, a latest date is given as well, e.g. between 5 May 1813 ans 11 November 1855: <x>when="18050505" notAfter="18551111"</x>.
	   The <tag>dateline</tag> marks the editors best estimate for a dating of the main entry. Marginal entries may be younger.
	   The <x>resp</x> attribute may be used to give a source of the dating, it is very rarely used, though.
	   In <tit>SKS-B</tit> the year of this dating is typeset in the top text together with the short titel and the number.
	   In <tit>SKS-E</tit> the same data appear from the title bar and the afore mentioned navigation bar.</sem>

   <sekt id="3.6.1">
    <rubrik>Columns</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>div</name>
        <attr class="typed">type</attr>="mainColumn"
        <attr class="global.rendition">rend</attr>="wide<sepa>|</sepa>full<sepa>|</sepa>transverse"
      </elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<elem><name>p</name></elem>|<elem><name>table</name></elem>|<elem><name>lg</name></elem>}
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<elem><name>note</name>
        type="author"
        <attr class="placement">place</attr>="bottom"
      </elem>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/div</tag>
    </synx>
     <sem/>
    <synx>
      <tag>div
        type="marginalColumn"
      </tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<tag>note
        type="author"
        place="margin"
      </tag>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/div</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>An entry consists of two types of columns:
      The <term>main column</term> holds the main entry text, possible footnotes and their footnotes included, see <refsekt id="3.3"/>.</sem>
      <sem>Marginal notes are placed in the <term>marginal column</term>, and should be rendered vertically closest possible to the reference in the main column, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <div type="entry" n="106" xml:id="n106"><dateline><date when="18430000"/></dateline><p rend="decoration"><figure type="divisionRuler"/></p>
      <div type="mainColumn">
        <p rendition="#ind"><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="IVA96"/>Det er utroligt, hvilken Naivitet man kan finde endog hos en saa udviklet Forfatter som <hi rendition="#und">Heiberg,</hi> [...] Om jeg kunde faae 100<hi rendition="#sup">rd</hi>, om jeg kunde blive erklæret for et Genie, jeg vilde ikke have skrevet en saadan Sludder for Alvor.<ref type="author" target="#jj-106.a">
          <seg type="refMarker">a</seg>
          </ref> Majoren vrøvler (efter Heibergs Ordre) ganske alvorlig aldeles som kunde det være Holbergs Ulisses, der ogsaa er Karl for Tiden.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="marginalColumn">
        <note type="author" place="margin" xml:id="jj-106.a">
          <seg type="refMarker">a</seg>
          <p rendition="#ind">at skrive saaledes, det er, hvad jeg kalder, at lade Pennen løbe med Snak paa Papiret.</p>
        </note>
      </div>
    </div>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <opt tit="JJ" nr="106" dek="skil" dat="18430000"> 
	<hs>
	<lin ryk="ind"><kor kil="Pap" id="IVA96"/>Det er utroligt, hvilken Naivitet man kan finde endog hos en saa udviklet Forfatter som <spa>Heiberg,</spa>
	[...]
	Om jeg kunde faae 100<hoj>rd</hoj>, om jeg kunde blive erkl<e name="ae">æ</e>ret for et Genie, jeg vilde ikke have skrevet en saadan Sludder for Alvor.<ref type="mn" id="jj-106.a"><indv>a</indv></ref> Majoren vr<e name="o-">ø</e>vler (efter Heibergs Ordre) ganske alvorlig aldeles som kunde det v<e name="ae">æ</e>re Holbergs Ulisses, der ogsaa er Karl for Tiden.</lin>
	</hs>
	<ms>
	<not type="mn" id="jj-106.a"><indv>a</indv>
	<lin ryk="ind">at skrive saaledes, det er, hvad jeg kalder, at lade Pennen l<e name="o-">ø</e>be med Snak paa Papiret.</lin>
	</not>
	</ms>
	</opt>
	  </ex>
     <sem>The vertical placement of an unanchored marginal note (<refsekt id="3.3"/>) is determined by the pointer in the main column as explained in <refsekt id="2.5.1"/>.
     In the following example the main text refers an unanchored marginal note and – in the same line – an ordinary footnote:</sem>
	  <ex gen="-sks">
	    <div type="entry" n="108" xml:id="n108"><dateline><date when="18430000"/></dateline><p rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></p>
      <div type="mainColumn">
        <p rendition="#ind"><pb xml:id="s45" n="45"/><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="IVA98"/>Den anden Prædiken kunde ogsaa være anlagt anderledens. Den kunde begyndt med de Ord: vide I da som ere onde at give Eders Børn gode Gaver, hvor meget mere skulde da Gud ikke vide det.<ref type="author" target="#jj-108.1">
          <seg type="refMarker">1</seg>
          </ref> Den skulde<ptr type="author" target="#jj-108.a"/> da begynde med Tvivlen om nu virkelig et Msk vidste at give gode Gaver. [...]</p>
        <note type="author" place="bottom" xml:id="jj-108.1">
          <seg type="refMarker">1</seg>
          <p rendition="#ind"><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="IVA99"/>Χstus vil deraf bevise Guds Godhed, og Beviset er slaaende; men han vil ikke bevise den første Sætning.</p>
        </note>
      </div>
      <div type="marginalColumn">
        <note type="author" place="margin" anchored="false" xml:id="jj-108.a">
          <seg type="refMarker"><supplied>a</supplied></seg>
          <p><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="IVA100"/>Mskene forstaae sig meget lidt paa hvad det Gode er. De vide Beskeed om Veier og Vind (cfr et Sted i Evangel.: naar Himlen rødmer da sige I: det bliver Blæst</p>
        </note>
      </div>
    </div>
	 </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <opt tit="JJ" nr="108" dat="18430000" dek="blank">
   <hs>
    <lin ryk="ind"><kor id="45"/><kor kil="Pap" id="IVA98"/>Den anden Pr<e name="ae">æ</e>diken kunde ogsaa v<e name="ae">æ</e>re anlagt anderledens. Den kunde begyndt med de Ord: vide I da som ere onde at give Eders B<e name="o-">ø</e>rn gode Gaver, hvor meget mere skulde da Gud ikke vide det.<ref type="sn" id="jj-108.1"><indv>1</indv></ref> Den skulde<ref type="mu" id="jj-108.a"/> da begynde med Tvivlen om nu virkelig et Msk vidste at give gode Gaver. [...]</lin>
    <not type="sn" id="jj-108.1"><indv>1</indv>
    <lin ryk="ind"><kor kil="Pap" id="IVA99"/><e name="g.Ch">Χ</e>stus vil deraf bevise Guds Godhed, og Beviset er slaaende; men han vil ikke bevise den f<e name="o-">ø</e>rste S<e name="ae">æ</e>tning.</lin>
    </not>
   </hs>
   <ms>
    <not type="mu" id="jj-108.a"><indv><udg spec="supp">a</udg></indv>
    <lin><kor kil="Pap" id="IVA100"/>Mskene forstaae sig meget lidt paa hvad det Gode er. De vide Beskeed om Veier og Vind (cfr et Sted i Evangel.: naar Himlen r<e name="o-">ø</e>dmer da sige I: det bliver Bl<e name="ae">æ</e>st</lin>
    </not>
   </ms>
  </opt>	  
	  </ex>
	  <sem>The main column is rendered with a width of 8 cm and the margin
5 cm (<tit>SKS-B</tit>). If the margin is, however, sparce or absent for long stretches of
a journal, the main column is widened to 10 cm, given by the
<x>rend="wide"</x> attribute to the  <tag>div type="mainColumn"</tag> element, as is the case with The
Journal CC whose first part consists of a Latin translation with a few
single words in the margin.</sem>
    <sem>A main entry that makes use of the full page width is marked with the attribute <x>rend="full"</x>. It is meaningless if such a main column is followed by a marginal column.
      At rare occations, such as The Journal KK:2, the author switches between the inner column and the full width. Such entries therefore contains several main entries with alternating use of a <x>rend</x> attributes.
      The margin notes referred in such main columns is placed in the immediately following marginal column.</sem>
	  <sem>In the later period of »The Journal« Kierkegaard uses the special effect of writing along the book spine, i.e. transverse of the normal writing direction. The main column is in these cases attributed <x>rend="transverse"</x> and in <tit>SKS</tit> rendered by using the full page width (like the <x>"full"</x> case above).
	    The arrangement does not, however, prevent the author from also using marginal notes that now appears above or below the <s.k.>main column</s.k.> as a result of the transversal.
	    This introduces the situation whera a marginal column may occur both before and after a main column. They are then typeset with the smaller size usual for marginal colums but with a somewhat wider width as shown in the follwing example.
	    Please note the referred illustration, the caption reads: »9. The Journal NB13, p. 28-29, the entry NB13:21, written along the page with additions above and under the text«.</sem>
     <html:img src="ill_9.jpg" alt="NB13:21, facsimile" width="100%" style="border: 1px solid navy"/>
     <sem>The illustration shows an opening of the journal and is hence referred twice, at the start of either page.</sem>
	  <ex gen="-sks">
	    <div type="entry" n="21" xml:id="n21" rend="newPage"><dateline><date when="18490000"/></dateline><p/>

<div type="marginalColumn">
<note type="author" place="margin" xml:id="nb13-21.a"><seg type="refMarker">a</seg>
<p><hi rendition="#lat"><hi rendition="#und">Anm</hi> Det allersandeste Udtryk er dog, at der er et <hi rendition="#und">tillige;</hi> thi en Deel har jeg dog forstaaet fra Begyndelsen, og stadig forstaaet forud, <hi rendition="#und">førend</hi> jeg gjorde det.</hi></p>
</note>
</div>

<div type="mainColumn" rend="transverse">

<p rendition="#cen"><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="X2A89"/><pb xml:id="s28" n="28" rend="supplied" facs="../nb13/ill_9.jpg"/><pb xml:id="ss285" edRef="#SKS" n="285"/><figure xml:id="ill_9" rend="opening"><graphic url="../nb13/ill_9.jpg"/><head>9. Journalen NB13, s. [28]-29, optegnelsen NB13:21, skrevet på langs ad siden med tilføjelser over og under teksten</head></figure><hi rendition="#lat">Om den færdigt liggende Productivitet og mig selv.</hi></p>
<p rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></p>
<p rendition="#ind"><hi rendition="#lat">Vanskeligheden ved at udgive det om Forfatterskabet er og bliver, at jeg dog egentligen har været brugt, uden ret selv at vide det eller ganske at vide det; og nu først forstaaer jeg og overskuer jeg det Hele – men saa kan jeg jo dog ikke sige: jeg. Jeg kan i det Høieste (det vil sige naar Fordringen til Sandhed er som den er for min Ængstelighed) sige: saaledes forstaaer jeg nu den tilbagelagte Productivitet.<ref type="author" target="#nb13-21.a"><seg type="refMarker">a</seg></ref> Det Forkeerte er saa igjen, at naar jeg ikke selv gjør det, saa <pb xml:id="s29" n="29" facs="ill_9.jpg"/><ptr type="figure" target="#ill_9"/> er der Ingen, som kan fremstille det, thi Ingen veed det saaledes som jeg.<ref type="author" target="#nb13-21.b"><seg type="refMarker">b</seg></ref></hi></p>

<p rendition="#ind">[...]</p>

<p rendition="#ind"><hi rendition="#lat">»Fra Høiheden vil Han drage Alle til sig.« skal gjøres pseudonym.<ref type="author" target="#nb13-21.c"><seg type="refMarker">c</seg></ref></hi> <pb/></p>
</div>
<div type="marginalColumn">
<note type="author" place="margin" xml:id="nb13-21.b"><seg type="refMarker">b</seg>
<p><hi rendition="#lat">Ingen kan som jeg belyse Structuren af det Hele.</hi></p>
</note>
<note type="author" place="margin" xml:id="nb13-21.c"><seg type="refMarker">c</seg>
<p><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#Pap." n="X2A90"/><hi rendition="#lat">Paa en dette Manuscript vedlagt Lap graat Papir findes bemærket, at dette Skrift saa paa en Maade indeholder et dialektisk Kjætterie. [...]</hi> </p>
</note>

</div>
</div></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <opt tit="NB13" nr="21" tving="nyside" dat="18490000">

<ms>
<not type="mn" id="nb13-21.a"><indv>a</indv>
<lin><ant><spa>Anm</spa> Det allersandeste Udtryk er dog, at der er et <spa>tillige;</spa> thi en Deel har jeg dog forstaaet fra Begyndelsen, og stadig forstaaet forud, <spa>førend</spa> jeg gjorde det.</ant></lin>
</not>
</ms>
<hs klum="tvaers">
<lin ryk="cen"><kor kil="Pap" id="X2A89"/><kor kil="supp" id="28"/><refi><ill id="9" tving="ops"><illfil id="http://sks.dk/nb13/ill_9.jpg"/><lin>9. Journalen NB13, s. [28]-29, optegnelsen NB13:21, skrevet på langs ad siden med tilføjelser over og under teksten</lin></ill></refi><ant>Om <kom id="nb13-121">den færdigt liggende Productivitet</kom> og mig selv.</ant></lin>
<lin dek="blank"/>
<lin ryk="ind"><ant>Vanskeligheden ved at udgive det om Forfatterskabet er og bliver, at jeg dog egentligen har været brugt, uden ret selv at vide det eller ganske at vide det; og nu først forstaaer jeg og overskuer jeg det Hele – men saa kan jeg jo dog ikke sige: jeg. Jeg kan i det Høieste (det vil sige naar Fordringen til Sandhed er som den er for min Ængstelighed) sige: saaledes forstaaer jeg nu den tilbagelagte Productivitet.<ref type="mn" id="nb13-21.a"><indv>a</indv></ref> Det Forkeerte er saa igjen, at naar jeg ikke selv gjør det, saa <kor id="29"/><refi id="9"/> er der Ingen, som kan fremstille det, thi Ingen veed det saaledes som jeg.<ref type="mn" id="nb13-21.b"><indv>b</indv></ref></ant></lin>
<lin ryk="ind">[...]</lin>
<lin ryk="ind"><ant>»Fra Høiheden vil Han drage Alle til sig.« skal gjøres pseudonym.<ref type="mn" id="nb13-21.c"><indv>c</indv></ref></ant> <kor/></lin>
</hs>
<ms>
<not type="mn" id="nb13-21.b"><indv>b</indv>
<lin><ant>Ingen kan som jeg belyse Structuren af det Hele.</ant></lin>
</not>
<not type="mn" id="nb13-21.c"><indv>c</indv>
<lin><kor kil="Pap" id="X2A90"/><ant>Paa en dette Manuscript vedlagt Lap graat Papir findes bemærket, at dette Skrift saa paa en Maade indeholder et dialektisk Kjætterie. [...]</ant> </lin>
</not>
</ms>
</opt>
	  </ex>
   </sekt>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.7">
   <rubrik>Letters and dedications</rubrik>

   <sekt id="3.7.1">
    <rubrik>Correspondance</rubrik> 
    <sem><term>Letters</term> in <tit>SKS</tit> are grouped into <term>correspondances</term>. A document file may contain one or more such correspondances, described in the <term>TEI header</term> under the name of a <term>correspondance context</term>:</sem>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>correspContext</name>
          <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>id</meta>"
      </elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>p</name></elem>
      <elem><name>name</name></elem>
      <meta>correspondant name</meta>
      <tag>/name</tag>
      <tag>/p</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/correspContext</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>The correspondance is described by the name of the person with whom the author corresponds.
      The name is used as a head line for the text.
      The name <x>"SK"</x> designates the author.
    </sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <correspContext xml:id="correspContext1"><p><name>Peter Christian Kierkegaard</name></p></correspContext>
    </ex>
    <sem on="TEI">Unfortunately these names like the names used for the particular correspondance action as described below, and unlike names appearing in the authors text, does not carry a <x>key</x> attribute referring a standardised form, cf. <refsekt id="2.4.2"/>.
      The distinct element <tag>name</tag> has been preferred over <tag>persName</tag> to minimise confusion.</sem>
    <sem>The correspondance text is marked:</sem>
     <synx>
       <elem><name>div</name>
         <attr class="typed">type</attr>="correspondance"
         <attr class="global.linking">corresp</attr>="#<meta>correspondance context</meta>"
         <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.linking">rend</attr>="newPage"<sepa>]</sepa>
       </elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>head</name>
         <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>top text</meta>"
       /</elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><tag>div
         type="letter"
       </tag><sepa>}</sepa>
       <html:br/>
       <tag>/div</tag>
     </synx>
     <sem>The page break rendering and top text decribed for chapters applies, see <refsekt id="3.5"/>.
       An example is given in <refsekt id="3.7.2"/> below.</sem>
   </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.7.2">
      <rubrik>Letter</rubrik>
      <sem>A <term>letter</term> is described in the <term>TEI header</term> under the name of a <term>correspondance description</term>:</sem>
      <synx>
        <elem><name>correspDesc</name>
          <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>id</meta>"
        </elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<elem><name>correspAction</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="sent"</elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>name</name>
          <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.source">source</attr>="#supplied"<sepa>]</sepa>
        </elem>
        <meta>sender</meta>
        <tag>/name</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><elem><name>note</name></elem><sepa>]</sepa>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>date</name>
          <attr class="datable.w3c">when</attr>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"
          <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="datable.w3c">notAfter</attr>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          <sepa>[</sepa>source="#<sepa>(</sepa>stamp<sepa>|</sepa>supplied<sepa>|</sepa>supplied year<sepa>|</sepa>undated<sepa>)</sepa>"<sepa>]</sepa>
        </elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<tag>/correspAction</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<tag>correspAction type="received"</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>name
          <sepa>[</sepa>source="#supplied"<sepa>]</sepa>
        </tag>
        <meta>receiver</meta>
        <tag>/name</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<tag>/correspAction</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<elem><name>correspContext</name></elem>
        <html:br/>
        <tag>/correspDesc</tag>
      </synx>
      <sem>The description consists of three parts:
        Two <term>correspondance actions</term> identifying the name of the sender and the receiver resp. and a <term>correspondance context</term> describing the correspondance as such, cf. above <refsekt id="3.7.1"/>.
        The sending action also contains a <tag>date</tag> with attributes as for journal entries, see <refsekt id="2.4.1"/>. A <x>source</x> attribute may indicate the source of the sender, receiver or date in the case such data are not evident from the letter text.
        The sending action may include a <tag>note</tag> indicating some free editorial explanation.
        As a correspondance may comprise several letters, the correspondance context can refer to the first one by the attribute <x>sameAs</x> in order not to dupplicate data.
        E.g.
      </sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
          <correspDesc xml:id="correspDesc1"><correspAction type="sent"><name>SK</name><date when="18290308"/></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><name>Kierkegaard, P.C.</name></correspAction><correspContext xml:id="correspContext1"><p><name>Peter Christian Kierkegaard</name></p></correspContext></correspDesc>        
      </ex>
<!--      <ex gen="-sks">
        <div type="letter" n="3" xml:id="n3" corresp="#correspDesc3"><head type="letterHeader" n="Fra M.P. Kierkegaard og SK · 13. og 15. juli 1829 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"/></div>
      <correspDesc xml:id="correspDesc3"><correspAction type="sent"><name>Kierkegaard, M.P.</name><date when="18290715"/></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><name>Kierkegaard, P.C.</name></correspAction><correspContext sameAs="#correspContext1"><p/></correspContext></correspDesc>
      </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><brev nr="3" fra="Kierkegaard, M.P." dat="18290715" til="Kierkegaard, P.C." txt="Fra M.P. Kierkegaard og SK · 13. og 15. juli 1829 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"></brev></ex>
-->
      <ex gen="-sks">
        <correspDesc xml:id="correspDesc4"><correspAction type="sent"><name>SK</name><date when="18420227" source="stamp"/></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><name>Kierkegaard, P.C.</name></correspAction><correspContext sameAs="#correspContext1"><p/></correspContext></correspDesc>
      </ex>
      <sem>The letter text is marked:</sem>
     <synx>
       <elem><name>div</name>
         <attr class="typed">type</attr>="letter"
         <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>number</meta>"
         <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="n<meta>number</meta>"
         <attr class="global.linking">corresp</attr>="#<meta>correspondance description</meta>"
       </elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>head</name>
         <attr class="typed">type</attr>="letterHeader"
         <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>header text</meta>"
       /</elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<sepa>(</sepa>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>opener</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>dateline</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>salute</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>/opener</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>div type="mainText"</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>closer</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>signed</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>/closer</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>postscript</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>trailer</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>note</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<sepa>)</sepa>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<sepa>|</sepa>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa>
       <tag>div</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>dateline</tag>|<tag>salute</tag>|<tag>signed</tag>|<tag>postscript</tag>|<tag>trailer</tag>|<tag>note</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>/div</tag>
       <sepa>}</sepa>
       <html:br/>
       <tag>/div</tag>
     </synx>
     <sem>Each letter is given a sequence number, <x>n</x>, unique throughout the letter corpus.
       The letter links to the relevant correspondance description, <x>corresp</x>, in the same way as the containing correspondance, <refsekt id="3.7.1"/>.
       The <term>letter header</term> given here explicitly, may in principle be derived from that description.
       E.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">
      <div type="correspondance" corresp="#correspContext1"><head type="topText" n="P.C. Kierkegaard"/>
        <div type="letter" n="1" xml:id="n1" corresp="#correspDesc1"><head type="letterHeader" n="Fra SK · 8. marts 1829 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"/><div>[...]</div></div>
        <div type="letter" n="4" xml:id="n4" corresp="#correspDesc4"><head type="letterHeader" n="Fra SK · stemplet 27. feb. 1842 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"/>
          <div>[...]</div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <korrespondance med="Peter Christian Kierkegaard" klum="P.C. Kierkegaard">
       <brev nr="1" fra="SK" dat="18290308" til="Kierkegaard, P.C." txt="Fra SK · 8. marts 1829 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"><txt>[...]</txt></brev>
       <brev nr="4" fra="SK" dat="18420227" datkil="stemplet" til="Kierkegaard, P.C." txt="Fra SK · stemplet 27. feb. 1842 · til P.C. Kierkegaard"><txt>[...]</txt></brev>
     </korrespondance>
    </ex>
      <sem>A letter consists of text boxes as described in the sequel.
        Paragraphs not contained in some sort of box should not appear, if in doubt, the main text box is chosen.
        Boxes may be centered or right indented as given by the <x>rendition</x> attribute, see <refsekt id="3.1"/> and the lines contained is indented relatively, see an example of this in section <refsekt id="3.7.2.5"/>.
        The boxes cannot be indented from the left; the same effect is however obtained by indenting the individual lines.
        The boxes primarily designates vertically distinct entities and secondarily semantic classification. Whenever a clash occurs, a suitable box is chosen, e.g. <tag>signed</tag> even though the text contains a dating as well as a signature, see example in <refsekt id="3.7.2.6"/>.</sem>
      <sem on="TEI">The transformation to TEI has been hampered by the fact that textboxes of a KN1 letter can be (and is in fact) placed in any sequence which TEI does not allow. Thus a postscipt within the opening sequence is for some reasons forbidden.
      The solution chosen in such a case is to wrap the banned element in a <tag>div</tag>.
      If this solution is used because of one box, all boxes have to be wrapped with <tag>div</tag>s to satisfy the TEI syntax, see the detailed coding for each idividual box, <refsekt id="3.7.2.1"/>-<refsekt id="3.7.2.8"/>.
      This hack has been applied for 20 letters out of 336.</sem>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.1">
        <rubrik>Dateline</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>dateline</name>
            <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>or</sem>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>div</name>
            <attr class="typed">type</attr>="dateline"
            <sepa>[</sepa>rendition="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>Marks the dating of the letter, e.g.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
          <dateline rendition="#bagxlang"> 
            <placeName key="København">Kbh:</placeName> <date when="18290308">d: 8<hi rendition="#sup">de</hi> Martz. 1829</date>.
          </dateline>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <datering> 
            <lin ryk="bagxlang"><sted norm="København">Kbh:</sted> <dag dat="18290308">d: 8<hoj>de</hoj> Martz. 1829</dag>.</lin>
          </datering>
        </ex>
        <sem on="TEI"><tag>dateline</tag> elements must not contain tables.
        Hence, this alternative coding may be used used:</sem>
        <!-- Brev 171 -->
        <ex gen="-sks">
<div type="dateline">
<table cols="2" rows="1" rendition="#udspark">
<row>
<cell><placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</cell>
<cell><date when="18411208">d. 8 Dec. 41</date></cell>
</row>
</table>
</div>        </ex>
        <ex gen="-kn1">
<datering>
<blok ryk="udspark">
<lin>
<tab><sted>Berlin</sted>.</tab>
<tab><dag dat="18411208">d. 8 Dec. 41</dag></tab>
</lin>
</blok>
</datering>
        </ex>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.2">
        <rubrik>Salute</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>salute</name>
            <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>Initial salutation, e.g.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
          <salute> 
            <l rendition="#xlang"><pb xml:id="s1r" n="1r" rend="supplied"/><milestone unit="entry" edRef="#BogA" n="1"/>Kjære Broder!</l>
            <l rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></l>
          </salute>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <tiltale> 
            <lin ryk="xlang"><kor kil="supp" id="1r"/><kor kil="BA" id="1"/>Kjære Broder!</lin>
            <lin dek="blank"/>
          </tiltale>
      </ex>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.3">
        <rubrik>Main text</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>div</name>
            <attr class="typed">type</attr>="mainText" <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>The main text of the letter</sem>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.4">
        <rubrik>Signed</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>signed</name>
            <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>Closing salutation and signature, see examples in the sections below.</sem>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.5">
        <rubrik>Postscript</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>postscript</name>
            <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>postscript after or in addition to the closing.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
         <closer><signed rendition="#baglang"> 
            <l rendition="#cen">Deres</l>
            <l rendition="#cen">S. Kierkegaard.</l>
          </signed>
          </closer><postscript>
            <l>P.S. Giv mit Bud paa en Stump Papir en ell. anden Hieroglyph tilbage som Tegn paa, at De har modtaget dette.</l>
          </postscript>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <hilsen ryk="baglang"> 
            <lin ryk="cen">Deres</lin>
            <lin ryk="cen">S. Kierkegaard.</lin>
          </hilsen>
          <efterskrift>
            <lin>P.S. Giv mit Bud paa en Stump Papir en ell. anden Hieroglyph tilbage som Tegn paa, at De har modtaget dette.</lin>
          </efterskrift>
        </ex>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.6">
        <rubrik>Address in letter</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>trailer</name>
            <attr class="typed">type</attr>="addrInLetter" <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global.rendition">rendition</attr>="<meta>indentation</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>Full names and titles of the receiver supplementing the salute, typically placed after the signature.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
<closer>
  <signed>
        <table cols="2" rows="1" rendition="#udspark">
          <row>
            <cell>Kiøbenh: den 16 Marts 1839.</cell>
            <cell rendition="#bagind">med Agtelse tegner jeg mig</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <l rendition="#baglang">Deres hengivne Onkel. –</l>
        <l rendition="#baglang">M. A. Kierkegaard</l>
        <l rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></l>
      </signed>
      </closer><trailer type="addrInLetter">
        <l rendition="#lang">Til</l>
        <l>dHr Doctor P. Chr. Kierkegaard!</l>
        <l>og Søren A. Kierkegaard!</l>
      </trailer>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <hilsen>
            <blok ryk="udspark">
              <lin>
                <tab>Kiøbenh: den 16 Marts 1839.</tab>
                <tab ryk="bagind">med Agtelse tegner jeg mig</tab>
              </lin>
            </blok>
           <lin ryk="baglang">Deres hengivne Onkel. –</lin>
           <lin ryk="baglang">M. A. Kierkegaard</lin>
           <lin dek="blank"/>
         </hilsen>
         <endtit>
           <lin ryk="lang">Til</lin>
           <lin>dHr Doctor P. Chr. Kierkegaard!</lin>
           <lin>og Søren A. Kierkegaard!</lin>
         </endtit>
        </ex>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.7">
        <rubrik>Address on envelope</rubrik>
        <synx>
          <elem><name>trailer</name>
            <attr class="typed">type</attr>="addrOnEnvelope" 
          </elem>
        </synx>
        <sem>Address on the outside of the letter, usually on the back side.
          The address is rendered in a frame, indented from both sides. No explicit indentation can be specified this box.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
<trailer type="addrOnEnvelope"> 
            <l rendition="#xlang"><pb xml:id="s2v" n="2v" rend="supplied"/>Herrn</l>
            <l rend="decoration"><figure type="blank"/></l>
            <l rendition="#ind"><choice><abbr>Cand: Theol:</abbr><expan>Candidatus Theologiæ</expan></choice> <persName key="Kierkegaard, Peter Christian">P.C. Kierkegaard</persName>.</l>
            <l rendition="#xlang"><placeName key="Unter den Linden">unter Linden</placeName> 20 drey Treppen</l>
            <l rendition="#baglang">in</l>
            <table cols="2" rows="1" rendition="#udspark"> 
              <row> <cell><choice><abbr>frco</abbr><expan>franco</expan></choice> <placeName key="Hamborg">Hamburg</placeName></cell> <cell><placeName>Berlin</placeName></cell> </row>
            </table>
          </trailer>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <udskrift> 
            <lin ryk="xlang"><kor kil="supp" id="2v"/>Herrn</lin>
            <lin dek="blank"/>
            <lin ryk="ind"><fork opl="Candidatus Theologiæ">Cand: Theol:</fork> <pers norm="Kierkegaard, Peter Christian">P.C. Kierkegaard</pers>.</lin>
            <lin ryk="xlang"><sted norm="Unter den Linden">unter Linden</sted> 20 drey Treppen</lin>
            <lin ryk="baglang">in</lin>
            <blok ryk="udspark"> 
              <lin> <tab><fork opl="franco">frco</fork> <sted norm="Hamborg">Hamburg</sted></tab> <tab><sted>Berlin</sted></tab> </lin>
            </blok>
          </udskrift>
        </ex>
        <sem on="TEI">It may seem that <tag>address</tag> would be a better candidate for this use. However, like <tag>dateline</tag> above, an address element must not contain tables, which is heavily used for the layout of envelopes. Furthermore it must not be placed after a <tag>postscript</tag>.</sem>
      </sekt>
      <sekt id="3.7.2.8">
        <rubrik>Note</rubrik>
        <sem>Authors notes in letters are handled similar to notes in the main column of journals and follows the rules for those, i.e. a reference marker is specified for the note, and reference and marker in the text.
         Digits are used for markers, see <refsekt id="2.5.1"/>.</sem>
        <ex gen="-sks">
<div type="mainText">
        <p rendition="#ind">De havde altsaa modtaget hiint Brev. [...] Der var en Passus<ref type="author" target="#b-279.1"><seg type="refMarker">1</seg></ref> deri, som De maaskee har forstaaet [...]</p>
      </div><closer>
      <note type="author" place="bottom" xml:id="b-279.1"><seg type="refMarker">1</seg>
        <p><hi rendition="#spa"><choice><abbr>Anm:</abbr><expan>Anmærkning</expan></choice></hi> Den Passus begynder saaledes: al Meddelelse i Reduplicationens
          Form«, en Passus som i andet Fald vilde have været en latterlig
          Reminiscents.</p>
      </note>
    </closer>
        </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
          <txt>
            <lin ryk="ind">De havde altsaa modtaget hiint Brev. [...] Der var en Passus<ref type="sn" id="b-279.1"><indv>1</indv></ref> deri, som De maaskee har forstaaet [...]</lin>
          </txt>
          <not type="sn" id="b-279.1"><indv>1</indv>
            <lin><spa><fork opl="Anmærkning">Anm:</fork></spa> Den Passus begynder saaledes: al Meddelelse i Reduplicationens
     Form«, en Passus som i andet Fald vilde have været en latterlig
     Reminiscents.</lin>
          </not>
        </ex>
      </sekt>
    </sekt>
  
  <sekt id="3.7.3">
    <rubrik>Work</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>div</name>
        <attr class="typed">type</attr>="work"
      </elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>head</name>
         <attr class="typed">type</attr>="workHeader"
         <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>header text</meta>"
       </elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<tag>head
         type="workTitle"
         n="<meta>title</meta>"
       /</tag>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>dateline</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
         &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>date</name>
           <attr class="typed">when</attr>="YYYYmmdd"
         /</elem>
      <tag>/date</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>/dateline</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><tag>div type=""dedication</tag><sepa>}</sepa>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/div</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>Decications in  <tit>SKS</tit> are ordered after the work of which the auther has dedicated.
      For each work a blue heading reads
      <kur>Dedikation</kur> (plural: <kur>Dedikationer</kur>) <kur>i</kur>, title, centeret dot, <kur>Udkom den</kur> and date
      (Dedication(s) in ... Published the ...), se example below.</sem>
  </sekt>
    <sekt id="3.7.4">
      <rubrik>Dedication</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>div</name>
        <attr class="typed">type</attr>="dedication"
      </elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;<elem><name>head</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>name</name>
         <attr class="canonical">key</attr>="<meta>canonical person name</meta>"
       /</elem>
       <html:br/>
       &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>bibl</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
         &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>msIdentifier</name></elem>
       <html:br/>
         &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>institution</name>
           key="<meta>provenance</meta>"
         /</elem>
       <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/msIdentifier</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/bibl</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>/head</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><tag>div type="mainText"</tag><sepa>}</sepa>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/div</tag>
    </synx>
      <sem>A dedication hold a <term>main text</term> as for letters, cf. <refsekt id="3.7.2.3"/>.
        In the case of a letter dedication, there may in addition occur an <term>address on envelope</term>, <refsekt id="3.7.2.7"/>.
      <!--The <tag>name</tag>  <refsekt id="3.7.1"/>--></sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
<div type="work"><head type="workHeader" n="Dedikationer i Om Begrebet Ironi · udkom den 29. sept. 1841"/><head type="workTitle" n="Om Begrebet Ironi"/><dateline><date when="18410929"/></dateline>

  <div type="dedication" n="12">
    <head>
      <name key="Münter, Balthasar"/>
      <bibl>
        <msIdentifier>
          <institution key="Privateje"/>
        </msIdentifier>
      </bibl>
    </head>
    <div type="mainText">
          <p>Til</p>
          <p rendition="#lang"><choice><abbr>S. T.</abbr><expan>Salvo Titulo</expan></choice> Høiærværdige Hr Hofprædikant <choice><abbr>Dr.</abbr><expan>Doctor</expan></choice> <persName key="Münter, Balthasar">Münter</persName></p>
          <p rendition="#x5lang"><choice><abbr>R af D.</abbr><expan>Ridder af Dannebrog</expan></choice> og <choice><abbr>DM.</abbr><expan>Dannebrogs-Mand</expan></choice></p>
        </div>
      </div>
</div>
      </ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">
     <skr titel="Om Begrebet Ironi" udk="18410929" txt="Dedikationer i Om Begrebet Ironi · udkom den 29. sept. 1841">
     <ded nr="12" til="Münter, Balthasar" prov="Privateje">
        <txt>
          <lin>Til</lin>
          <lin ryk="lang"><fork opl="Salvo Titulo">S. T.</fork> Høiærværdige Hr Hofprædikant <fork opl="Doctor">Dr.</fork> <pers norm="Münter, Balthasar">Münter</pers></lin>
          <lin ryk="x5lang"><fork opl="Ridder af Dannebrog">R af D.</fork> og <fork opl="Dannebrogs-Mand">DM.</fork></lin>
        </txt>
      </ded>
     </skr>
    </ex>
    </sekt>

  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.8">
   <rubrik>Commentaries</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>note</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="e"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>no</meta>"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page</meta>,<meta>line</meta>"
   </elem></synx>
   <sem>The commentaries comprises the explanatory notes as refered to from the text volume, see <refsekt id="2.6.2"/>.
     The individual note is identified by <x>xml:id</x>, the short titel of the work plus a number.
     After the typesetting of the text volume of <tit>SKS-B</tit>, the page and line number of the commentary pointer (<refsekt id="2.6.2"/>) can be established and typeset in the accompanying commentry volume in front of the individual note.
     These values are then transported back into the digital text as values of the attribute <x>n</x>, and displayed for reference in <tit>SKS-E</tit>. For the details of the creation of <tit>SKS</tit>, see <reflit id="KN1"/></sem>
    <sem>Explanatory notes that are not typeset in the book version but exclusively in the electronic version, is subtyped <x>e</x>, se <refsekt id="3.8.3.2"/>.</sem>

  <sekt id="3.8.1">
   <rubrik>Lemma</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>label</name></elem></synx>
   <sem>An explanatory note is introduced by a <term>lemma</term>, an extract of the authors text, possibly abridged by an ellipsis <cit>(...)</cit> or ... .
   The <term>lemma character</term> (]) delimits the lemma from the following lines:</sem>
  </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.8.2">
   <rubrik>Line</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>p</name></elem></synx>
   <sem>After the lemma follows one or more lines.</sem>
   </sekt>
   
   <sekt id="3.8.3">
   <rubrik>Arrow pointer</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>ptr</name>
      <attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary"
      <sepa>[</sepa><attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="e<meta>|</meta>b"<sepa>]</sepa>
      <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>no</meta>"
      <attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page</meta>,<meta>line</meta>"
   </elem>import="refk"></synx>
   <sem>A note may refer to an other note by a <tag>ptr</tag>.
     It is rendered as an arrow followed by page and line number, comma separated, line number in petit, italics: <refk side="145" linie="29" gen="+sks-b"/>, e.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
     <note type="commentary" xml:id="jj-6" n="145,29">
	  <label><hi rendition="#bol">Brutus <hi rendition="#ita">(...)</hi> lod Sønnen henrette</hi></label>
	  <p>Lucius Junius Brutus, hovedmanden bag fordrivelsen af Roms
	    sidste konge, Tarquinius Superbus 
	    (<ptr type="commentary" target="#jj-313" n="183,1"/>),
	    [..]</p>
	</note>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
    <k id="jj-6" side="145" linie="29">
	  <lemma><fed>Brutus <kur>(...)</kur> lod S<e name="o-">ø</e>nnen henrette</fed></lemma>
	  <klin>Lucius Junius Brutus, hovedmanden bag fordrivelsen af Roms
	    sidste konge, Tarquinius Superbus 
	    (<refk id="jj-313" side="183" linie="1"/>),
	    [..]</klin>
	</k>
	 </ex>
	 
<sekt id="3.8.3.1">
   <rubrik>Eksternal pointer</rubrik>
   <sem>As a rule, arrow pointers is reserved for internal references;
     exceptios do exist, howewer, e.g. between notes for the two parts of <tit>Enten – Eller</tit>, between the 10 issues of <tit>Øieblikket</tit> and others.
     The short title of the target (i.e. the text between the two first <x>/</x>s of the <x>target</x> attribute) is rendered between the arrow and the page and line number, except that this is omitted in <tit>SKS-B</tit> whenever source and target is printed in the same volume so that the page and line number becomes unique.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
     <note type="commentary" xml:id="ee2-150" n="49,21"> 
     <label>
      <hi rendition="#bol">Mozart</hi>
     </label>
     <p>dvs. Mozarts operaer, som analyseres i <hi rendition="#ita">EE1, SKS</hi> 2, 53-136. Mozart <ptr type="commentary" target="../EE1/kom.xml#ee1-174" n="55,3"/>. </p>
    </note>
   </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">
     <k id="ee2-150" side="49" linie="21" nr="5"> 
     <lemma>
      <fed>Mozart</fed>
     </lemma>
     <klin>dvs. Mozarts operaer, som analyseres i <kur>EE1, SKS</kur> 2, 53-136. Mozart <refkx tit="EE1" id="ee1-174" side="55" linie="3"/>. </klin>
    </k>
</ex>
</sekt>
   <sekt id="3.8.3.2">
    <rubrik>Pointer to e-notes</rubrik>
    <sem>At certain occations supplementary commentaries have been made as compared to those printed.
      The supplement is handled by <tit>SKS-E</tit> as an extra layer of commentary, so that such e-notes are referred to by subtyping the <tag>ptr</tag> <x>"e"</x>; they are rendered by placing an <tit>SKS-E</tit> after the arrow.
      An e-note may also be referred directly from the authors text in which case the <tag>ref</tag> is subtyped the same way, see <refsekt id="2.6.2"/>.</sem>
    <sem>Same subtyping is used in the referred e-<tag>note</tag>.
      Pointers pointing back from an e-note is subtyped <x>"b"</x>.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <note type="commentary" xml:id="jj-11" n="146m,1"><label><hi rendition="#bol">samme Bind ... Biskop Synesius</hi></label> <p>jf. <hi rendition="#ita">Herder's Werke. Zur schönen Litteratur und Kunst</hi> bd. 16, s. 9-11, som bringes i <ptr type="commentary" target="../JJ/ekom.xml#jj-11-e" subtype="e"/>. [...]</p></note>
    </ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">  <k id="jj-11" side="146m" linie="1" nr="7.a"><lemma><fed>samme Bind ... Biskop Synesius</fed></lemma> <klin>jf. <kur>Herder's Werke. Zur schönen Litteratur und Kunst</kur> bd. 16, s. 9-11, som bringes i <refkx id="jj-11-e" x="e"/>. [...]</klin></k>
</ex>
   </sekt>
   </sekt>

  
   <sekt id="3.8.4">
    <rubrik>General eksternal reference</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <!--<attr class="typed">type</attr>="publishedWritings<sepa>|</sepa>unpublishedWritings<sepa>|</sepa>journalsAndPapers<sepa>|</sepa>lettersAndDedications<sepa>|</sepa>commentary<sepa>|</sepa>textCriticalAccount<sepa>|</sepa>introduction<sepa>|</sepa>figure<sepa>|</sepa>map<sepa>|</sepa>preparatoryManuscript"-->
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="<meta>see below</meta>"
            <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>dir</meta>/<meta>file</meta>#<meta>id</meta>"
            <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>see below</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
            <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global">rend</attr>="<meta>see below</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
    </synx>
    <sem>Marks a <term>general eksternal reference</term> whenever a commentary text refers to some other material in <tit>SKS</tit>.
      The sort of referred material appears from the <x>type</x>.</sem>
      <sem on="TEI">As indicated, <x>target</x> addresses a neighbouring <term>directory</term> dependent on the type of reference. In most cases such directory furthermore specify a <term>short title</term> of some work, the letter case of which may or may not coincide with the canonical one as given by the <tag>titleStmt</tag>, cf. <refsekt id="3.10.3"/>.</sem>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.1">
     <rubrik>Published writings</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="publishedWritings"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/txt.xml#ss<meta>SKS page number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>SKS page number</meta><sepa>|</sepa>sv2:<meta>page</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global">rend</attr>="<meta>title</meta>, <meta>page</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>A <term>published writing</term> is refered to by its short title appearing as a part of the <x>target</x> attribute together with its <tit>SKS</tit> page number.
     The page and possible line number also is given as the <x>n</x> attribute, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">Mozarts operaer, som analyseres i <ref target="../EE1/txt.xml#ss53" type="publishedWritings" n="53"><hi rendition="#ita">EE1, SKS</hi> 2, 53-136</ref></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Mozarts operaer, som analyseres i <refx type="ts" tit="EE1" side="53"><kur>EE1, SKS</kur> 2, 53-136</refx>
     </ex>
     <sem>If a published writing was not yet established by <tit>SKS</tit> at the time the commentary is written, <tit>SV2</tit> has been used as a reference.
       Later, the proper <tit>SKS</tit> reference has then been added and is rendered after the content text in square brackets as indicated by the <x>rend</x> attribute, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks"><p>Tre gange havde SK selv prædiket ved disse altergangsgudstjenester om fredagen, den 18. juni 1847, den 27. aug. 1847 og den 1. sept. 1848. Og han udgav dem alle tre som taler (<ptr type="commentary" target="#nb19-3" n="331,3"/>), dels som nr. II og nr. III i »Taler ved Altergang om Fredagen. Christelige Taler«, fjerde afdeling af <hi rendition="#ita">Christelige Taler</hi> (1848, i <ref target="../CT/txt.xml#ss277" type="publishedWritings" n="277"><hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> 10, 277-283</ref> og <ref target="../CT/txt.xml#ss285" type="publishedWritings" n="285">285-292</ref>), dels som nr. I i »Fra Høiheden vil han drage Alle til sig. Christelige Udviklinger«, nr. III af <hi rendition="#ita">Indøvelse i Christendom</hi> (1850 (<ptr type="commentary" target="#nb19-44" n="336,28"/>), <ref target="../IC/txt.xml#ss155" type="publishedWritings" n="sv2:12" rend="IC, 155"><hi rendition="#ita">SV2</hi> 12, 173-179</ref>).</p></ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Tre gange havde SK selv pr<e name="ae">æ</e>diket ved disse altergangsgudstjenester om fredagen, den 18. juni 1847, den 27. aug. 1847 og den 1. sept. 1848. Og han udgav dem alle tre som taler (<refk id="nb19-3" side="331" linie="3"/>), dels som nr. II og nr. III i »Taler ved Altergang om Fredagen. Christelige Taler«, fjerde afdeling af <kur>Christelige Taler</kur> (1848, i <refx type="ts" tit="CT" side="277"><kur>SKS</kur> 10, 277-283</refx> og <refx type="ts" tit="CT" side="285">285-292</refx>), dels som nr. I i »Fra H<e name="o-">ø</e>iheden vil han drage Alle til sig. Christelige Udviklinger«, nr. III af <kur>Ind<e name="o-">ø</e>velse i Christendom</kur> (1850 (<refk id="nb19-44" side="336" linie="28"/>), <refx type="ts" sv2="12" tit="IC" side="155"><kur>SV2</kur> 12, 173-179</refx>).</ex>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.2">
     <rubrik>Unpublished writings, journals, notebooks and papers</rubrik>
      <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="unpublishedWritings"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/txt.xml#ss<meta>SKS page number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>SKS page number</meta><sepa>|</sepa>pap:<meta>vol. sect. entry</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa><attr class="global">rend</attr>="<meta>title</meta>, <meta>page</meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </elem>
    </synx>
      <sem/>
    <synx>
     <tag>ref
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;type="journalsAndPapers"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;target="../<meta>short title</meta>/txt.xml#n<meta>entry number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;n="<meta>entry number</meta><sepa>|</sepa>pap:<meta>vol. sect. entry</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<sepa>[</sepa>rend="<meta>short title</meta>:<meta></meta>"<sepa>]</sepa>
   </tag>
    </synx>
    <sem><term>Unpublished writing</term> are handles most the same way, e.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">se den utrykte artikel »Et Øieblik, Hr. Andersen!«, i <ref target="../OiA/txt.xml#ss7" type="unpublishedWritings" n="7"><hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> 15, 7</ref></ex>
    <ex gen="-kn1">se den utrykte artikel »Et Øieblik, Hr. Andersen!«, i <refx type="uts" tit="OiA" side="7"><kur>SKS</kur> 15, 7</refx></ex>
     <sem>A <term>journal</term> is refered to by its short title appearing as a part of the <x>target</x> attribute together with its entry number,
     which is also given as the <x>n</x> attribute, i.e. unless the journal is referred to as such. E.g.</sem>

     <ex gen="-sks">Her fortæller han, at han opsøgte Regine Olsen den 8. sept. 1840, og at han modtog hendes ja to dage efter, den 10. sept., om eftermiddagen, se <ref target="../Not15/txt.xml#n4" type="journalsAndPapers" n="4">Not15:4</ref>, i <hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> 19, 433,19 - 434,9.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Her fort<e name="ae">æ</e>ller han, at han ops<e name="o-">ø</e>gte Regine Olsen den 8. sept. 1840, og at han modtog hendes ja to dage efter, den 10. sept., om eftermiddagen, se <refx type="jp" tit="Not15" nr="4">Not15:4</refx>, i <kur>SKS</kur> 19, 433,19 - 434,9.</ex>
     <sem>The <x>rend</x> attribute is used the same way as for published writings (<refsekt id="3.8.4.1"/>) if an unpublished writing or journal was not yet established by <tit>SKS</tit> at the time,
       except that <tit>Pap.</tit> is used as a spare, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">sml. følgende optegnelse, fra midten af nov. 1850, i journalen NB21: »Synderinden er næsten kun tilstede som in effigie, og dog er hun Den, om hvem der handles, den Nærværende« (<ref target="../NB21/txt.xml#n123" type="journalsAndPapers" n="pap:X3A566" rend="NB21:123"><hi rendition="#ita">Pap.</hi> X 3 A 566</ref>).</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">sml. f<e name="o-">ø</e>lgende optegnelse, fra midten af nov. 1850, i journalen NB21: »Synderinden er n<e name="ae">æ</e>sten kun tilstede som in effigie, og dog er hun Den, om hvem der handles, den N<e name="ae">æ</e>rv<e name="ae">æ</e>rende« (<refx type="jp" pap="X3A566" tit="NB21" nr="123"><kur>Pap.</kur> X 3 A 566</refx>).</ex>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.3">
     <rubrik>Letters and dedications</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="lettersAndDedications"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/txt.xml#n<meta>letter number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="ba:<meta>B&amp;A letter number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">rend</attr>="Brev <meta>SKS letter number</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>The rend attribute is used the same way as for published writings (3.8.4.1), except that <tit>B&amp;A</tit> is used as a spare. As the letters were the very last category to be established for <tit>SKS</tit>, this will always be the case, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">Da han forberedte sit <hi rendition="#ita">Album,</hi> bad han også om en prøve af SKs håndskrift, men fik afslag; jf. <ref target="../b208/txt.xml#n213" type="lettersAndDedications" n="ba:123" rend="Brev 213"><hi rendition="#ita">B<e name="amp">&amp;</e>A</hi> bd. 1, s. 144 (nr. 123)</ref>.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">Da han forberedte sit <kur>Album,</kur> bad han også om en prøve af SKs håndskrift, men fik afslag; jf. <refx type="bd" ba="123" tit="b208" nr="213"><kur>B&amp;A</kur> bd. 1, s. 144 (nr. 123)</refx>.</ex>
      <sem>No references to dedications exist.</sem>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.4">
     <rubrik>Commentary</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/kom.txt#<meta>short title</meta>-<meta>id</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page number</meta>,<meta>line number</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>The <term>fragment identifier</term> after <x>#</x> in <x>target</x> is specified as for the referred explanatory note, cf. <refsekt id="3.8"/>, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">(se <ref target="../NB12/kom.xml#nb12-981" type="commentary" n="244m,4">kommentar til <hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> 22, 244<hi rendition="#ita">m,</hi>4</ref>)</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">(se <refx type="kom" tit="NB12" side="244m" linie="4" id="nb12-981">kommentar til <kur>SKS</kur> 22, 244<kur>m,</kur>4</refx>)</ex>
     <sem>The difference between the <tag>ptr type="commentary"</tag> above and this one is that the former is rendered with an arrow and is reserved for cross references between closely related works, see <refsekt id="3.8.3.1"/>.</sem>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.5">
     <rubrik>Text Critical Account</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="textCriticalAccount"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/txr.xml#ss<meta>page number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page number</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>Example from <tit>»Ypperstepræsten« – »Tolderen« – »Synderinden«</tit> (<tit>YTS</tit>):</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks"><hi rendition="#ita">Sygdommen til Døden</hi> udkom den 30. juli 1849, se <ref target="../SD/txr.xml#ss121" type="textCriticalAccount" n="121">tekstredegørelsen, s. 121</ref>, mens <hi rendition="#ita">YTS,</hi> der var blevet afleveret til <placeName>Bianco Lunos Bogtrykkeri</placeName> den 29. okt., udkom den 14. nov. 1849, se <ref target="../YTS/txr.xml#ss253" type="textCriticalAccount" n="253">tekstredegørelsen, s. 253</ref>.</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><kur>Sygdommen til D<e name="o-">ø</e>den</kur> udkom den 30. juli 1849, se <refx type="txr" tit="SD" side="121">tekstredeg<e name="o-">ø</e>relsen, s. 121</refx>, mens <kur>YTS,</kur> der var blevet afleveret til <sted>Bianco Lunos Bogtrykkeri</sted> den 29. okt., udkom den 14. nov. 1849, se <refx type="txr" tit="YTS" side="253">tekstredeg<e name="o-">ø</e>relsen, s. 253</refx>.</ex>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.6">
     <rubrik>Introduction</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="introduction"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title</meta>/int_<meta>id</meta>.xml#ss<meta>page number</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>page number</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>For selected works, one or two introductions to the commentary or text critical account exist.
       The file id is <x>1</x> or <x>2</x> respectively. E.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">De øvrige professorer ved universitetet var ligeledes mødt op, jf. <ref target="../Not11/int_1.xml#ss421" type="introduction" n="421">indledningen til kommentarerne til notesbog 11</ref> i <hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> K19, 421-423</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">De <e name="o-">ø</e>vrige professorer ved universitetet var ligeledes m<e name="o-">ø</e>dt op, jf. <refx type="int" tit="Not11" id="1" side="421">indledningen til kommentarerne til notesbog 11</refx> i <kur>SKS</kur> K19, 421-423</ex>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.7">
     <rubrik>Illustration</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="figure"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../<meta>short title </meta>/<meta>file</meta>#ill_<sepa>[</sepa>k<sepa>]</sepa><meta>id</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>The <term>fragment identifier</term> (the <x>target</x> part after <x>#</x>) is given as the <x>xml:id</x> of the <tag>figure</tag> element of sect. <refsekt id="3.4"/></sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">sigter til <persName key="Klæstrup, Peter">P. Klæstrup</persName>s karrikaturtegninger af SKs tynde ben i et par alt for store støvler i <hi rendition="#ita">Corsaren</hi>, nr. 278, den 16. jan. 1846 (se <ref target="../NB/txt.xml#ill_k6" type="figure">illustration 6</ref>, i <hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> K20, 42).</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">sigter til <pers norm="Klæstrup, Peter">P. Kl<e name="ae">æ</e>strup</pers>s karrikaturtegninger af SKs tynde ben i et par alt for store st<e name="o-">ø</e>vler i <kur>Corsaren</kur>, nr. 278, den 16. jan. 1846 (se <refx type="ill" tit="NB" id="k6">illustration 6</refx>, i <kur>SKS</kur> K20, 42).</ex>
     <sem>This reference is used for all illustration in commentaries, external as well as internal.
       The difference between the illustration pointer of <refsekt id="2.5.4"/> an this one is that the former is used for facsimiles from the authors texts and is rendered with a link <cit>fax</cit>.</sem>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.8">
     <rubrik>Map</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="map"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global.linking">target</attr>="../kort/<meta>map id</meta>_<meta>coordinates</meta>.htm"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="<meta>map id</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>Maps are refered by the commentary text by its number.
       As the maps, however, not always hold the same number in different commentary volumes, they are here identified with names as followes:</sem>
     <ex vis="vert" gen="-sks">
      <ref type="map" n="ber"/> <forkl>Berlin</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="kbh"/> <forkl>København</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="kbhf"/> <forkl>København med forstæder</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="kbhfsv"/> <forkl>København med forstæder, syd-vest</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="kbho"/> <forkl>Københavns omegn</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="mols"/> <forkl>Mols</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="ns"/> <forkl>Nordsjælland</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="nos"/> <forkl>Nordsjælland, øst</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="ring"/> <forkl>Ringkøbing og omegn</forkl>
      <ref type="map" n="vib"/> <forkl>Viborg og omegn</forkl>
     </ex>
     <sem>Coordinates are given, typically as a letter and a digit. If the text indicates an interval the lowest is specified.
       In the <tit>SKS-E</tit> rendering, the content is replaced by an arrow and a globe icon, e.g.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks"><placeName>Ladegaarden</placeName>, en institution i <placeName>København</placeName> på <placeName>Ladegaardsvej</placeName> (nuv. Åboulevard) umiddelbart efter dæmningen mellem <placeName key="Sankt Jørgens Sø">St. Jørgens Sø</placeName> og <placeName>Peblinge Sø</placeName> (<ref target="../kort/kbhfsv_B2.htm" type="map" n="kbhfsv"><hi rendition="#ita">se kort 5, B2-3</hi></ref>)</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1"><sted>Ladegaarden</sted>, en institution i <sted>København</sted> på <sted>Ladegaardsvej</sted> (nuv. Åboulevard) umiddelbart efter dæmningen mellem <sted norm="Sankt Jørgens Sø">St. Jørgens Sø</sted> og <sted>Peblinge Sø</sted> (<refx type="kort" nr="kbhfsv" id="B2"><kur>se kort 5, B2-3</kur></refx>)</ex>
      <sem on="TEI">A note on the special use of html files in the <x>target</x> is due: The maps as such are stored in <cit>DjVu</cit> format, embedded in an html file, calling a plugin. The html <tag>embed</tag> element also holds information of the detailed placement of the coordinates in question.  See <reflit id="wsh"/> for details.</sem>
    </sekt>

    <sekt id="3.8.4.9">
     <rubrik>Preparatory manuscript</rubrik>
    <synx>
     <elem><name>ref</name>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="typed">type</attr>="preparatoryManuscript"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">n</attr>="pap:<meta>entry</meta>"
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<attr class="global">rend</attr>="<meta>short title</meta>"
   </elem>
    </synx>
     <sem>
     The <x>n</x> attribute is used the same way as for journals (<refsekt id="3.8.4.1"/>) refering to the <tit>Pap.</tit> edition. As no preparatory manuscripts have actually been established so far, no <x>target</x> is specified.
       The <x>rend</x> attribute specifies the short title of the corresponding final work.
       The marking has no effect for the present <tit>SKS</tit>.
       E.g.
     </sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">sml. det opr. manuskript til de to særskilte sider, formentlig skrevet i 1849, i slutningen af »Regnskabet«, hvor SK skriver: »[...]« (<ref type="preparatoryManuscript" n="pap:X5B148" rend="FV,"><hi rendition="#ita">Pap.</hi> X 5 B 148</ref>, s. 349</ex>
   <ex gen="-kn1">sml. det opr. manuskript til de to s<e name="ae">æ</e>rskilte sider, formentlig skrevet i 1849, i slutningen af »Regnskabet«, hvor SK skriver: »[...]« (<refx type="e" tit="FV" pap="X5B148"><kur>Pap.</kur> X 5 B 148</refx>, s. 349</ex>
    </sekt>   
    
   </sekt>

  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.9">
   <rubrik>Categories of text</rubrik>
	 <sem>The texts of the authors text are subdivided into four different <term>categories</term> (or genres), viz. <term>published writings</term>, <term>unpublished writings</term>, <term>journals and papers</term> and <term>letters and dedications</term>, each with a different text structure. Furthermore, each of the authors text are accompanied by a <term>critical account of the text</term> (sect. <refsekt id="4"/>), a <term>commentary</term> and possibly an <term>introduction</term> to either of these.</sem>
    <sem on="TEI">KN1 would at the place similar to this have a reference from the authors text file to the accompanying commentary file and vice versa. This seems a nice way, but unfortunately TEI have no obvious field for such information. In stead, this information has been written directly into the <x>target</x> attribute of the relevant reference or pointer, e.g. <tag>ref type="commentary" target="kom.xml#aa-1"</tag>, see <refsekt id="2.6.2"/>
    <red.note>Tjek denne påstand, [TEI] 3.11.2.7 Related Items</red.note>
    </sem>
<sekt id="3.9.1">
   <rubrik>Published writings</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="print"
     <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="publishedWritings"</elem>
    <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="chapter"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>note</name>
     type="author"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
    <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>

  <sem>A <term>published writing</term> is a work printed and published within the lifetime of the author. It consists of a number of <term>chapters</term> followed by a number of <term>notes</term>, i.e. the authors footnotes, stored as end notes (sect. <refsekt id="3.5"/>).</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.2">
   <rubrik>Unpublished writings</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="ms<sepa>|</sepa>print" <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="unpublishedWritings"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="chapter"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>note</name>
     type="author"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>
 <sem>An <term>unpublished writing</term> is a work that was not printed and published within the lifetime of the author. Such texts are a a rule typed <x>"ms"</x>, except in case the work has been printed posthumous and the manuscript diappeared.
   In this caase the print serves a copy-text.
   It consists of a number of <term>chapters</term> followed by a number of <term>notes</term>, i.e. the authors footnotes, stored as end notes.</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.3">
   <rubrik>Journals and papers</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="ms" <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="journalsAndPapers"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="entry"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>
  <sem>A <term>journal</term> (diary, notebook) is a handwritten writing contained in a booklet.
    A <term>paper</term> is a sheet, scrap or slips of Paper.
    It consists of a number of <term>entries</term>, subdivided into a main and possibly a marginal column (sect. <refsekt id="3.6"/>).</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.4">
   <rubrik>Letters and dedications</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="ms" <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="lettersAndDedications"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>div</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="correspondance <sepa>|</sepa> work"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>
 <sem>This category comprise <term>letters</term> either to or from the author. Letters are further organised in <term>correspondances</term> (sect <refsekt id="3.7.1"/>), and filed in relevant groups.
   <term>Dedications</term> are organised with respect to the works in which they have been written (sect. <refsekt id="3.7.3"/>).</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.5">
   <rubrik>Preparatory manuscripts</rubrik>
   <sem>Obsolete.</sem>
  <sem>Readers with special interest in parallel text layers are referred to <reflit id="KN1"/>.</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.6">
  <rubrik>Commentaries</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary" <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="<meta>category</meta>"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>div</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>note</name>
     <attr class="typed">type</attr>="commentary"</elem>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/div</tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>
 <sem>A <term>commentary</term> consists of a number of explanatory notes, authored by the editors of <tit>SKS</tit>. A commentary is typed <x>commentary</x> and subtyped as the author text it accompanies.
   Each such note is referred to from a <term>lemma</term> within the authors text (sect. <refsekt id="3.8"/>).</sem>
</sekt>
<sekt id="3.9.7">
  <rubrik>Text critical accounts</rubrik>
  <sem>Cf. sect. <refsekt id="4"/>.</sem>
</sekt>
 </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.10">
   <rubrik>Colophon, the TEI header</rubrik>
   <synx>
     <elem><name>teiHeader</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>fileDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>titleStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>title</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>author</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>respStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/titleStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>publicationStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/publicationStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>seriesStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/seriesStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>sourceDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/sourceDesc</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>/fileDesc</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>encodingDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>revisionDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>teiHeader</tag>
  </synx>
  <sem>A colophon describes the provenance of the text and other metadata.
    It appears within the <term>TEI header</term> with the following fields:</sem>

   <sekt id="3.10.1">
    <rubrik>Author</rubrik>
   <synx>
     <elem><name>author</name></elem>
   </synx>
    <sem>Author of the texts are <x>Søren Kierkegaard</x>.
      Pseudonymes are not considered in this context.
      For commentaries (<refsekt id="3.8"/>) and critical accounts (<refsekt id="4"/>) this field marks the author(s) of these.</sem>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.2">
    <rubrik>Title</rubrik>
   <synx>
     <elem><name>title</name>
       level="s<sepa>|</sepa>j"</elem>
   </synx>
    <sem>The <tag>title</tag> with no further attributes marks the authors text in question, no matter whether this document holds a commentary, critical account or the text itself.
      <x>level="j"</x> (<x>j</x>=journal) marks a newspaper title, number and date if apppropriate.
      <x>level="s"</x> (<x>s</x>=series) marks the title of <x>Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</x></sem>

    <ex gen="-sks">
     <title level="s">Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</title>
     <title>Ogsaa et Forsvar for Qvindens høie Anlæg</title>
     <title level="j">Kjøbenhavns flyvende Post, nr. 34
17. december 1834</title>
     <title type="short">FQA</title>
    </ex>
   </sekt>
    
    <sem>The <x>level="s"</x> title has been placed in top of the document for the sake of conspicuousness.
    The context of the collected series is further described in the <term>series statement</term>:</sem>
    
    <synx>
      <tag>seriesStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>title xml:id="SKS"</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>biblScope</name> <attr class="citing">unit</attr>="volume"</elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>biblScope unit="file"</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/seriesStmt</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>E.g.</sem>
    <ex gen="-sks">
      <seriesStmt>
       <title xml:id="SKS">Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</title>
       <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
       <biblScope unit="file">http://sks.dk/fqa/txt.xml</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
    </ex>
    <sem on="TEI">Note that the series title is attributed an id, meaning that all references <x>#SKS</x> refers to this item, in the same way as text witnesses refers to a compiled list in the <term>source description</term> (<refsekt id="3.10.7"/>). In this respect, however, <tit>SKS</tit> means the idea of the collected project to which <tit>SKS-E</tit> belongs, wheras the following volume number refers more specifically to the <tit>SKS-B</tit> version, which may og may not be an excact copy of the document described by the header.
      Also see the discussion of the use of the <x>wit</x> attribute in <refsekt id="2.5.2"/>
    The next following file name currently refers to the web address of the KN1 version, which is hence repeated in the <term>revision description</term> (<refsekt id="3.10.11"/>). It should be changed in the this <tag>seriesStmt</tag> in case the document is made accessible on the web with a different address.
    In addition to reference, the file address also documents the intended relative location of the document within the file system, which is an important part of the external references as assumed in <refsekt id="2.6"/> and <refsekt id="3.8.4"/></sem>

   <sekt id="3.10.3">
    <rubrik>Short title</rubrik>
   <synx>
     <elem><name>title</name>
       type="short"
     </elem>
   </synx>
    <sem>Marks the short title of the text.
      The short title is an extremely useful property, e.g constructing identifiers for notes, commentaries etc. or naming files.
    See example of <refsekt id="3.10.2"/>.</sem>
     <sem on="TEI">The short title is specified in <s.k.>camelCase</s.k.> letters, e.g. <x>OiA</x>, short for »Et Øieblik, Hr. Andersen!« or <x>Not1</x> for <tit>Notesbog 1</tit>. Care should be taken if these are used as names in a file system that distinguish names on case. Apart from that, short titles are unique within <tit>SKS</tit> disregarding the letter case. Letters outside A-Z are not used for short titles.</sem>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.4">
    <rubrik>Introduction to commentaries</rubrik>
     <sem>Obsolete.</sem>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.5">
   <rubrik>Editors and publishers</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>editor</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<elem><name>name</name></elem>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/editor</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem/>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>respStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>resp</name></elem>
      <x>udgivet af</x>
      <tag>/resp</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<tag>name</tag>}
      <html:br/>

      <tag>respStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/respStmt</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>resp</tag>
      <x>redigeret af</x>
      <tag>/resp</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<tag>name</tag>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/respStmt</tag>
    </synx>

   <sem><tag>editor</tag> marks names of the members of the editorial board of <tit>SKS</tit> at the time of the first publication of the text.
     The <term>responsibility statemant</term> phrased <x>udgivet af</x> (dan. "published by") is used in cases where the publishers are not identical with the editors collectively. 
     The responsibility statemant phrased <x>redigeret af</x> (dan. "edited by") is used solely in commentaries (and critical accounts, <refsekt id="4"/>) designating persons dedicated to the task of close reading the specific piece in particular.</sem>  </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.6">
   <rubrik>Text establishers</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>respStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>resp</name></elem>
      <x>etableret af</x>
      <tag>/resp</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<tag>name</tag>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/respStmt</tag>
    </synx>
   <sem>Names of the encoding philologists that have the responsibility for the establihment of the authors text.
     This field together with the following.</sem></sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.7">
   <rubrik>Text sources</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>sourceDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>listWit</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>witness</name> xml:id="<meta>sigel</meta>"</elem>}
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>/listWit</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/sourceDesc</tag>
    </synx>
   <sem>The sources of the authors text (first print, manuscript or other).
     As attribute <x>xml:id</x> is used the same attribute <x>wit</x> which is used as a siglum for text critics that root in the that source.
     The list may be subdivided into imbedded lists whose kind is decribed with a header, or more sources may be grouped under the same siglum, e.g.
   </sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">
      <sourceDesc>
       <listWit>
         <listWit>
          <head>Manuskripter</head>
          <witness xml:id="Ms.">KA, D pk. 1 læg 1-4; D pk. 3 læg 4; NKS 3174, 4 <hi rendition="#sup"
            >o</hi> ; NBD 2. rk; Nordiska museets arkiv (NMA) Nm.19740 og Nm.68591</witness>
          <witness xml:id="M-afskrift">Fr. Meidells afskrift</witness>
         </listWit>
         <listWit>
          <head>Udgaver</head>
          <listWit xml:id="EP">
           <witness xml:id="EPI-II">Af Søren Kierkegaards Efterladte Papirer. 1833-1843</witness>
           <witness xml:id="EPVI">Af Søren Kierkegaards Efterladte Papirer. 1849</witness>
          </listWit>
          <witness xml:id="Tilskueren1900">
           <title>Tilskueren,</title> årg. 17, udg. af M. Galschiøt, Kbh. 1900</witness>
         </listWit>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </ex>
     <sem on="TEI">As a TEI header has to include a source description in order to be valid, editorial text (i.e. commentaries or critical accounts) are marked:</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">
      <sourceDesc>
       <bibl copyOf="#SKS"/>
      </sourceDesc>
     </ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.8">
   <rubrik>Encodning</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>encodingDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>tagsDecl</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;{<elem><name>rendition</name> xml:id="<meta>name</meta>" selector="<meta>TEI element</meta>" scheme="css <sepa>|</sepa>free"</elem>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/listWit</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/sourceDesc</tag>
    </synx>
   <sem>The <term>encoding description</term> holds the detailed description of <term>highligting elements</term> and legend texts for the <term>text critical apparatus</term>.
     The <tag>rendition</tag> elemenst are described under the relevant TEI element type, e.g. <refsekt id="2.3"/> and <refsekt id="2.5"/>.
     An attached xml comment may emphasize that this is the rendition of the copy-text, which is not nescesarily followed by <tit>SKS</tit>.
     The sceme is either <x>css</x> (which is the default) or <x>free</x> in case a css description does not apply.
     E.g.</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
		<encodingDesc>
			<tagsDecl>
       <rendition xml:id="sup" selector="hi" scheme="css">vertical-align: super; font-size: 80%;</rendition>
       <rendition xml:id="und" selector="hi" scheme="css">text-decoration: underline</rendition>
  				<!--underlined, in SKS rendered italic-->
  				<rendition xml:id="lat" selector="hi" scheme="free">Latin hand, in SKS rendered sans-serif</rendition>
       <rendition xml:id="fs" selector="rdg" scope="before">content:"først skrevet "</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
   </ex>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.9">
   <rubrik>Copyright</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>publicationStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>authority</name></elem>
      <x>Søren Kierkegaard Forskningscenteret</x> <meta>year of publishing</meta>
      <tag>/authority</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>availability</name></elem>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>p</name></elem>
      copyright
      <tag>/p</tag>
      <tag>/availability</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/publicationStmt</tag>
    </synx>
   </sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.10">
   <rubrik>File name</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>biblScope</name> <attr class="citing">unit</attr>="file"</elem>
    </synx>
   <sem>Name of the file holding the document, see <refsekt id="3.10.2"></refsekt>.</sem></sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.11">
   <rubrik>File date</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>change</name> <attr class="datable.w3c">when</attr>="<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta>"</elem>
    </synx>
   <sem>Date for last revision of the file, see <refsekt id="3.10.13"/>.
   On the format of dates, see <refsekt id="2.4.1"/></sem></sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.12">
   <rubrik>Digital editors</rubrik>   
    <synx>
      <elem><name>respStmt</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>resp</name></elem>
      <x>elektronisk redigeret af</x>
      <tag>/resp</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;{<tag>name</tag>}
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/respStmt</tag>
    </synx>
   <sem>Names of those responsible for the digital encoding.</sem></sekt>

   <sekt id="3.10.13">
   <rubrik>Version</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>revisionDesc</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>change</name> <attr class="datable.w3c">when</attr>=<meta>YYYYmmdd</meta></elem>
      <meta>version description</meta>
      <tag>/change</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/revisionDesc</tag>
    </synx>
    <sem>Any <term>version description</term> should contain a <term>version number</term></sem>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>idno</name> <attr>type</attr>="file"</elem>
    </synx>
   <sem>Version numbers designates the digital version, e.g.  <cit>1.1</cit>, <cit>1.2</cit> etc., the first digit <cit>1</cit> emphasising that this is versions of the same basic edition.
     The oldest <term>change record</term> (placed in the bottom of the <term>revision description</term>) describes the last KN1 version of the work in question published on the web site <tit>sks.dk</tit>.
     The next record describes the TEI tranformation.
     The TEI version is given the version number 1.9, corresponding to the last published KN1 version, 1.8.
     No <x>when</x> attribute is given as it is not available to the xsl transforming proces. In stead the name and revision date of the transformation program is given.</sem>
     <ex gen="-sks">
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>Transformed to TEI by style sheet <bibl type="file">kn12tei.xsl</bibl> version <idno
					type="version">1.9</idno> as of <date>2016-12-16</date> by <name>Karsten Kynde</name>,
					<orgName>Det Kongelige Bibiliotek</orgName>, <placeName>København</placeName></change>
			<change when="20100203">Kierkegaard Normalformat vers. 1, <bibl><idno type="version">1.4</idno>,
						<biblScope unit="file">http://sks.dk/nb36/txt.xml</biblScope></bibl></change>
		</revisionDesc>
     </ex>
   </sekt>
   
   <sem>This is an example of a complete file description:</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="s">Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</title>
				&#x2003;&#x2003;<title>Journalen NB36</title>
				<title type="short">NB36</title>
				<author>
					<name>Søren Kierkegaard</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>udgivet af</resp>
					&#x2003;&#x2003;<name>Niels Jørgen Cappelørn</name>
					<name>Joakim Garff</name>
					<name>Anne Mette Hansen</name>
					<name>Johnny Kondrup</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>etableret af</resp>
					&#x2003;&#x2003;<name>Niels W. Bruun</name>
					<name>Klaus Nielsen</name>
					<name>Stine Holst Petersen</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>elektronisk redigeret af</resp>
					&#x2003;&#x2003;<name>Karsten Kynde</name>
					<name>Kim Ravn</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Søren Kierkegaard Forskningscenteret 2009</authority>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>copyright</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title xml:id="SKS">Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</title>
				<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
				<biblScope unit="file">http://sks.dk/nb36/txt.xml</biblScope>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Ms.">KA, A pk. 40</witness>
					<listWit>
						<witness xml:id="EP"><title>Af Søren Kierkegaards Efterladte Papirer.
							1854-55</title></witness>
					</listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Pap."><title>Søren Kierkegaards Papirer,</title> 2. forøgede udgave, 1968-78,
						bd. XI 2</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>[...]</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>[...]</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
   </ex>
  </sekt>

  <sekt id="3.11">
   <rubrik>The TEI document</rubrik>
    <synx>
      <elem><name>TEI</name> <attr>version</attr>="5" <attr>xmlns</attr>="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"</elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>teiHeader</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<elem><name>text</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>div</name></elem>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
      <html:br/>
      &#x2003;<tag>/text</tag>
      <html:br/>
      <tag>/TEI</tag>
    </synx>

    <sem>The xml <term>name space</term> of a TEI document is  <x>"http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"</x>, see <reflit id="XML"></reflit> for details.</sem>
   <sekt id="3.11.1">
    <rubrik>XML prolog</rubrik>
   <sem>Before the <tag>TEI</tag> tag an xml <term>prolog</term> is inserted identifying the xml file as such, its xml version and character encoding, see <reflit id="XML"/>; 2.8.</sem>
     <sem><tag>?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?</tag>
   </sem>
   </sekt>
      <sem>The outline of an entire document follows from this example (a journal):</sem>
   <ex gen="-sks">
     <?fakeXml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI version="5" fakeXmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
  <teiHeader>[...]</teiHeader>
 <text type="ms" subtype="journalsAndPapers"><body>
  <div type="entry" n="1" xml:id="n1" rend="recto">
    . . .
  </div>
   <div type="entry" n="11" xml:id="n11"><dateline><date when="18540000"/></dateline><p rend="decoration"><figure type="hash"/></p> 
    <div type="mainColumn">[...]</div>
    <div type="marginalColumn">
     <note type="author" place="margin" anchored="false" xml:id="nb36-11.a">[...]</note>
    </div>
   </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
   </ex>
  </sekt>

 </sekt>
  
  <sekt id="4">
    <rubrik>Critical accounts of the text</rubrik>
    <html:p><s.k.>Critical accounts of the texts</s.k.> (Dan. <frspr>tekstredegørelse</frspr>, abbrev. txr) are treated separatetely from KN1. This is mostly due to historical reasons: the format of these were never a part of the KN1 document type description, but merely described in a very short, internal note, <reflit id="txr"/>.</html:p>
    <html:p>TEI is a text format intended for primary texts; these texts are in contrast written by the editors, which does make the formatting less complicated, as we may expect them to follow a more stringent discipline. The same counts, of course, for the commentaries, <refsekt id="3.8"/>. So the colofon expressed in the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, should not be ascribed to the person usually mentioned throughout this paper as <s.k.>the author</s.k.>, but rather the induvidual editor, <refsekt id="3.10.1"/>, and the mandatory TEI element <tag>sourceDesc</tag> have no evident value other than <tit>SKS</tit> in general, <refsekt id="3.10.7"/>.</html:p>
    <html:p>Otherwise, the description of this paper applies for the TEI of critical accounts with respect to the running text, <refsekt id="2.1"/>, typographical signals, <refsekt id="2.3.1"/>-<refsekt id="2.3.9"/>, referring terms, <refsekt id="2.4"/> and illustrations, <refsekt id="3.4"/>.
      General external reference as described in <refsekt id="3.8.4"/> is used extensively, see example after <refsekt id="4.5"/>.
    </html:p>
    <sekt id="4.1">
  <rubrik>The text</rubrik>
  <synx>
   <elem><name>text</name> <attr class="typed">type</attr>="TextCriticalAccount" <attr class="typed">subtype</attr>="<meta>category</meta>"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<elem><name>body</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>div</name></elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>head</name>
     type="topText" <attr class="global">n</attr>="Tekstredegørelse"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>head</tag><x>Tekstredegørelse</x><tag>/head</tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>list</name>
   <attr>type</attr>="TOC"</elem>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;{<tag>div
     type="level1"</tag>}
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/div</tag>
   <html:br/>
   &#x2003;<tag>/body</tag>
   <html:br/>
   <tag>/text</tag>
  </synx>
 <sem>A <term>text critical account</term> consists of a number of chapters, authored by the editors of <tit>SKS</tit>. The text is typed <x>"TextCriticalAccount"</x> and subtyped as the author text it accompanies, cf. <refsekt id="3.9"/>.
   Top text apply as for <refsekt id="3.5"/>.
   A chapter may contains subchapters of type <x>"level2"</x>, that may contain subchapters of type <x>"level3"</x>, see example after <refsekt id="4.5"/>.</sem>
</sekt>
    <sekt id="4.2">
      <rubrik>Table of content and other lists</rubrik>
      <synx>
        
      </synx>
      <sem>Most accounts will start with a table of content, e.g.</sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
        <list type="TOC">
   <item>1. Bibliografiske data <ptr type="chapter" target="#k1" n="553"/> </item>
   <item>2. Manuskripter <ptr type="chapter" target="#k2" n="534"/> </item>
   <item>3. Tilblivelseshistorie <ptr type="chapter" target="#k3" n="540"/> </item>
   <item>4. Udgivelsesmåde <ptr type="chapter" target="#k4" n="562"/> </item>
  </list>
      </ex>
      <!--<ex gen="-kn1">
        <indhold>
   <irub>1. Bibliografiske data <refs id="k1">533</refs> </irub>
   <irub>2. Manuskripter <refs id="k2">534</refs> </irub>
   <irub>3. Tilblivelseshistorie <refs id="k3">540</refs> </irub>
   <irub>4. Udgivelsesmåde <refs id="k4">562</refs> </irub>
  </indhold>
      </ex>-->
      <sem>The <x>n</x> attribute is a page number, rendered by <tit>SKS-B</tit>. The <x>target</x> is a chapter address, rendered by <tit>SKS-E</tit> as a link.</sem>
      <sem>The following example shows a list of accessible copies of the text:</sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
        <list>
      
       <label>A</label>
       <item>Søren Kierkegaard Forskningscenterets arbejdseksemplar,
        tilhørende G.E.C. Gads Forlag (tidligere hos dr.phil. h.c. Gustaf
        Bernström, Göteborg; tidligere hos greve [...] </item>
      
      
       <label>B</label>
       <item>Det kongelige Biblioteks eksemplar, katalogsignatur
        14,–82–8<hi rendition="#sup">o</hi>. Ex. 1, DA BOX, revisionsnr. 01491.
       </item>
     </list>
      </ex>
      <ex gen="-kn1">
        <lis>
      <l>
       <lid>A</lid>
       <ltx>Søren Kierkegaard Forskningscenterets arbejdseksemplar,
        tilhørende G.E.C. Gads Forlag (tidligere hos dr.phil. h.c. Gustaf
        Bernström, Göteborg; tidligere hos greve [...] </ltx>
      </l>
      <l>
       <lid>B</lid>
       <ltx>Det kongelige Biblioteks eksemplar, katalogsignatur
        14,–82–8<hoj>o</hoj>. Ex. 1, DA BOX, revisionsnr. 01491.
       </ltx>
      </l>
     </lis>
      </ex>
    </sekt>
    <sekt id="4.3">
      <rubrik>Manuscript description</rubrik>
      <synx>
        <elem><name>msDesc</name></elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<elem><name>msIdentifier</name></elem>
        <elem><name>collection</name></elem>
        <meta>short title</meta>
        <tag>/idno</tag>
        <tag>/msIdentifier</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><elem><name>msPart</name>
          <attr class="global">xml:id</attr>="physDesc.<meta>id</meta>"
          <attr class="global.linking">next</attr>="#additional.<meta>id</meta>"
        </elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>msIdentifier</tag>
        <elem><name>idno</name></elem>
        <meta>id</meta>
        <tag>/idno</tag>
        <tag>/msIdentifier</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>physDesc</name></elem>
        <html:br/> &#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><elem><name>p</name></elem><sepa>}</sepa>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/physDesc</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<sepa>{</sepa><tag>msPart</tag><sepa>}</sepa>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<tag>/msPart</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<elem>msPart
          xml:id="additional.<meta>id</meta>"
          <attr class="global.linking">prev</attr>="#physDesc.<meta>id</meta>"
        </elem>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>msIdentifier</tag>
        <tag>idno</tag>
        <meta>id</meta>
        <tag>/idno</tag>
        <tag>/msIdentifier</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>additional</name></elem>
        <html:br/>&#x2003;&#x2003;&#x2003;<elem><name>adminInfo</name></elem>
        <elem><name>note</name></elem>
        <tag>p</tag>
        <tag>/note</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;&#x2003;<tag>/additional</tag>
        <html:br/>
        &#x2003;<tag>/msPart</tag><sepa>}</sepa>
        <html:br/>
        <tag>/msDesc</tag>
      </synx>
      <sem>The <tit>SKS</tit> <term>manuscript description</term> is a schema whose interpretation heavily rests on proper indentations.
      Expressed in TEI, it consists of a number of ms. parts, which may in turn consist of a number of parts, and so on in a hierarchic manner.</sem>
      <sem>A <term>ms. part</term> in <tit>SKS</tit> is for some reason divided into two, presented separately, viz. a <term>psysical description</term> of the ms. and <term>additional</term> administrative information about the present custody and availability of the ms. These two parts are coded in separate <tag>msPart</tag> elements, linked together with <x>next</x> and <x>prev</x> attributes.
      The first of these parts may list sub parts immediately after the physical description, which is in this way separated from its additional administration information that appears later.</sem>
      <sem on="TEI">A neater encoding would be to place the <tag>additional</tag> element <em>before</em> the subparts, avoiding to have two <tag>msParts</tag> for the same item. That encoding practice was not preferred neither by the <tit>SKS</tit> editors nor in KN1, as the info given there somehow sums up the similar info given for the subparts.</sem>
      <sem>Each ms. part is identified by an <term>id number</term> with a period followed by an sub number and so on, indicating the level of sub parts.
      The ms. description as a whole must be identified as a collection, here the short title of the work is used.</sem>
      <ex gen="-sks">
     <msDesc>
      <msIdentifier>
       <collection>F</collection>
      </msIdentifier>
      <msPart xml:id="physDesc.1" next="#additional.1">
       <msIdentifier>
        <idno>1</idno>
       </msIdentifier>
       <physDesc>
        <p>Kladde til <hi rendition="#ita">Fs</hi> »Forord« og »II«. </p>
       </physDesc>
       <msPart xml:id="physDesc.1.1" next="#additional.1.1">
        <msIdentifier>
         <idno>1.1</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
         <p>1 sammenhæftning a 8 folioark, i alt 16 blade i 4<hi rendition="#sup">o</hi>. Overskrift
          på bl. [1r]: »<hi rendition="#ant">Forord.</hi>« </p>
         <p>Ingen paginering. </p>
         <p>[...]</p>
        </physDesc>
       </msPart>
       <msPart xml:id="additional.1.1" prev="#physDesc.1.1">
        <msIdentifier>
         <idno>1.1</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <additional>
         <adminInfo>
          <note><p>(<hi rendition="#ita">Pap.</hi> V B 73-75 + 77-78)</p></note>
         </adminInfo>
        </additional>
       </msPart>
       <msPart xml:id="physDesc.1.2" next="#additional.1.2">
        <msIdentifier>
         <idno>1.2</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <physDesc>
         <p>5 løse blade i 4<hi rendition="#sup">o</hi>. Overskrift tilføjet med rødkridt på bl.
          [1r]: »<hi rendition="#ant">II</hi>«. </p>
         <p>[...]</p>
        </physDesc>
       </msPart>
       <msPart xml:id="additional.1.2" prev="#physDesc.1.2">
        <msIdentifier>
         <idno>1.2</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <additional>
         <adminInfo>
          <note><p>(<hi rendition="#ita">Pap.</hi> V B 80-84) </p></note>
         </adminInfo>
        </additional>
       </msPart>
      </msPart>
      <msPart xml:id="additional.1" prev="#physDesc.1">
       <msIdentifier>
        <idno>1</idno>
       </msIdentifier>
       <additional>
        <adminInfo>
         <note><p>(<hi rendition="#ita">L-fort.</hi> 389; KA, B pk. 12 læg 2; <hi rendition="#ita"
            >Pap.</hi> V B 73-75 + 77-78 + 80-84) </p></note>
        </adminInfo>
       </additional>
      </msPart>
      <msPart>
       <msIdentifier>
        <idno>2</idno>
       </msIdentifier>
       <physDesc>
        <p>Kladde til <hi rendition="#ita">Fs</hi> »Forord« samt udkast og kladde til »IV« »V« og
         »VI«. Alle mss. stammer fra renskriften, hvor teksten blev skrevet uden forlæg, bortset fra
         ms. 2.1, der har ms. 1.1 som forlæg. SK har efter renskrivningen forkastet teksterne og
         henlagt dem som kladde. </p>
         <p>[...]</p>
       </physDesc>
      </msPart>
     </msDesc>
      </ex>
      <ex gen="-kn1">
   <mslis>
    <msl>
     <msid>1</msid>
     <mstx>
      <lin>Kladde til <kur>Fs</kur> »Forord« og »II«. </lin>
      <mslis>
       <msl>
        <msid>1.1</msid>
        <mstx>
         <lin>1 sammenhæftning a 8 folioark, i alt 16 blade i 4<hoj>o</hoj>. Overskrift på bl. [1r]: »<ant>Forord.</ant>« </lin>
         <lin>Ingen paginering. </lin>
         <lin>[...]</lin>
         <lin>(<kur>Pap.</kur> V B 73-75 + 77-78)</lin>
        </mstx>
       </msl>
       <msl>
        <msid>1.2</msid>
        <mstx>
         <lin>5 løse blade i 4<hoj>o</hoj>. Overskrift tilføjet med rødkridt på bl. [1r]: »<ant>II</ant>«. </lin>
         <lin>[...]</lin>
         <lin>(<kur>Pap.</kur> V B 80-84) </lin>
        </mstx>
       </msl>
      </mslis>
      <lin>(<kur>L-fort.</kur> 389; KA, B pk. 12 læg 2; <kur>Pap.</kur> V B 73-75 + 77-78 + 80-84) </lin>
     </mstx>
    </msl>
    <msl>
     <msid>2</msid>
     <mstx>
      <lin>Kladde til <kur>Fs</kur>
       »Forord« samt udkast og kladde til »IV«
       »V« og »VI«. Alle mss. stammer fra renskriften, hvor teksten blev skrevet uden forlæg, bortset fra ms. 2.1, der har ms. 1.1 som forlæg. SK har efter renskrivningen forkastet teksterne og henlagt dem som kladde.</lin>
       <lin>[...]</lin>
     </mstx>
    </msl>
   </mslis>
      </ex>
    </sekt>
    <sekt id="4.4">
      <rubrik>Quotations</rubrik>
      <synx>
        <elem><name>quote</name></elem>
      </synx>
      <sem>Quotations are rendered as block quotations, in a smaller size and indented from left, see example after <refsekt id="4.5"/>.</sem>
      
    </sekt>
    <sekt id="4.5">
      <rubrik>Notes</rubrik>
      <synx>
        <elem><name>note</name></elem>
      </synx>
      <sem>Notes are handled directly in the text, i.e. no reference is needed in contrast to authors notes, <refsekt id="3.3"/>.</sem>
    </sekt>
    <sem>Example of external references, chapter, heading, quotation and note:</sem>
<ex gen="-sks"><div type="level1" xml:id="k3">
   <head>3. Tilblivelseshistorie</head>
    <p>Om SKs særlige interesse for forordet som genre vidner en journaloptegnelse fra 17. maj 1839: </p>
   <quote>
    <p><hi rendition="#ita">[...]</hi> kun een Tanke udfylder min Sjæl, en Længsel, en Tørst efter ret at forvilde mig i Forordets lyriske Underskov, ret at baldre mig deri; thi ligesom det maa gaae Digteren, at han snart føler sig lyrisk bevæget, snart episk tiltalt, saaledes føler jeg som Prosaist i det Øieblik en ubeskrivelig Glæde ved at opgive al objektiv Tænkning, og ret at udtømme mig i Ønsker og Forhaabninger, i en hemmelig Hvidsken med Læseren, en Horatzisk <hi rendition="#ant">sussuratio</hi> i Af[ten]stunden; thi Forordet bør altid opfattes i Aftenbelysning, som ogsaa unægtelig er den skjønneste; og det er derfor ikke underligt, at vi læse, at vor Herre spadserede i Aftenkjølingen <hi rendition="#ant">(Genesis),</hi> en Af[ten]stund, naar Tankens Travlhed lyder fjernt høitideligt som Høstkarlens Lee. – <note> <p> Journalen EE, s. 18f.; KA, A pk. 2 læg 4; trykt som <ref target="../EE/txt.xml#n73" type="journalsAndPapers" n="pap:IIA432" rend="EE:73"><hi rendition="#ita">Pap.</hi> II A 432</ref>. Det latinske sussuratio betyder hvisken. </p> </note> </p>
   </quote>
   <p><pb xml:id="ss541" n="541" edRef="#SKS"/>Optegnelsen er ikke et forarbejde til <hi rendition="#ita">F,</hi> men den rummer skriftets æstetiske kim, som SK fem år senere udfolder, nu i polemisk øjemed. Den tekst af <persName key="Horats">Horats</persName>, der alluderes til, genfindes i forordet til <hi rendition="#ita">F,</hi> hvor SK foretager en bestemmelse af forordet som genre (jf. <ref target="../F/txt.xml#ss469" type="publishedWritings" n="469"><hi rendition="#ita">SKS</hi> 4, 469</ref>f.).</p>
      </div></ex>
      <html:img src="ex4.5.png" alt="F, tekstredegøreslse, klip fra sks.dk" width="100%" style="border: 1px solid navy"/>

    <sekt id="4.6">
      <rubrik>Introductions</rubrik>
      <sem>In certain cases there have been a need for a collecting introduction to a series of commentaries or other editorial stuff.
      In these cases the format of the critical account has been reused, e.g.</sem>
      <ex gen="-sks"><text type="TextCriticalAccount" subtype="lettersAndDedications"><body><div><head type="topText" n="Introduktion"/>
    <head>Introduktion til <hi rendition="#ita">Breve</hi></head><div type="level1">
      <head>I. Tidligere udgivelse af brevmaterialet</head>
      <p>[...]</p></div></div></body></text></ex>
    </sekt>
    </sekt>
  
 <app id="lit">
  <rubrik>References</rubrik>
  <lit id="SKS-B"><tit>Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter</tit>, Gads Forlag: København 1997-2012</lit>
  <lit id="SKS-E"><html:a href="http://sks.dk">http://sks.dk</html:a></lit>

  <lit id="KN1"><tit>Kierkegaard Normalformat 1. Dokumentation</tit>, V.1.8, 2013, <html:a href="http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.xml">http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.xml</html:a>, <html:a href="http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.pdf">http://sks.dk/red/kn1dok.pdf</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="KN1Eng">»Kierkegaard Normal Format 1«, in <tit>Kierkegaard Studies. Yearbook 2003</tit>, de Gruyter: Berlin/New York 2003. <html:a href="http://kynde.etxt.dk/KSYB03.pdf">http://kynde.etxt.dk/KSYB03.pdf</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="XML"><tit>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0,</tit>, [1998], latest version <html:a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</html:a>.</lit>
  <lit id="TEI"><tit>P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</tit>, [2016], <html:a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/</html:a>.</lit>
  <lit id="TEIlite"><tit>TEI Lite: Encoding for Interchange: an introduction
to the TEI</tit>,
Final revised edition for TEI P5,
Lou Burnard C. M. Sperberg-McQueen, August 2012, <html:a href="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/Lite/">http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/Lite/</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="MathML"><tit>Mathematical Markup Language (MathML) Version 3.0 2nd Edition</tit>, 2014, <html:a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/">http://www.w3.org/TR/MathML/</html:a>.</lit>
  <lit id="Retningslinier/ts">»Tekstkritiske retningslinier for Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter. Trykte skrifter«, in <tit>SKS-B</tit>, K1, s. 15, Gads Forlag: København 1997. <html:a href="http://sks.dk/red/retningslinier_ts.pdf">http://sks.dk/red/retningslinier_ts.pdf</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="Retningslinier/jp">»Tekstkritiske retningslinier for Søren Kierkegaards Skrifter. Journaler, notesbøger og papirer«, in <tit>SKS-B</tit>, 17, s. 301, Gads Forlag: København 2000. <html:a href="http://sks.dk/red/retningslinier.pdf">http://sks.dk/red/retningslinier.pdf</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="Layout"><tit>SKS LAYOUT</tit>, notat, NJC 18.02.1997, J.nr. 03-09-01.</lit>
  <lit id="Unicode"><tit>The Unicode Standard, Version 3.0.</tit> Addison-Wesley: Reading, MA 2000. <html:a href="http://www.unicode.org/book/u2.html">http://www.unicode.org/book/u2.html</html:a> (or latest version <html:a href="http://www.unicode.org/versions/latest/">http://www.unicode.org/versions/latest/</html:a>)</lit>
  <lit id="Registre"><tit>Indices. Guide</tit>, <html:a href="http://sks.dk/vejl/reg_e.xml">http://sks.dk/vejl/reg_e.xml</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="Bibelhenv"><html:a href="https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/undervisning/laesibibelen/oversigt">https://www.bibelselskabet.dk/undervisning/laesibibelen/oversigt</html:a></lit>
  <lit id="Synoptik">»Synoptiske udgaver i elektronisk form«, in <tit>Varianter och bibliografisk beskrivning</tit>, Nordiskt Nätverk för Editionsfilologer. Skrifter. 5, Svenska litteratursälskapet i Finland: Helsingfors 2003. <html:a href="http://nnedit.org/vol/nne_vol_5.pdf#page=99">http://nnedit.org/vol/nne_vol_5.pdf#page=99</html:a>. Also
  »Interconnecting Textual Layers«, i <tit>Kierkegaard Studies. Yearbook 1998</tit>, de Gruyter: Berlin/New York 1998 or <html:a href="http://kynde.etxt.dk/allc-ach.98.htm">http://kynde.etxt.dk/allc-ach.98.htm</html:a></lit>
   <lit id="skakt">»Om skakter«, in <tit>Kritik</tit>, 216-217, København: Gyldendal 2016, <html:a href="http://kynde.etxt.dk/kritik216.pdf">http://kynde.etxt.dk/kritik216.pdf</html:a></lit>
   <lit id="txr"><tit>Elektronisk format for tekstredegørelser</tit>, 3. reviderede udg., Notat, J.Nr. 03-09, KK 2003.9.19</lit>
   <lit id="wsh"><tit>SKS-E Workshop</tit>, Karsten Kynde, v1.8, 2012-10-01, [first version 2007-04-27], <html:a href="http://sks.dk/red/wsh-vejl.htm">http://sks.dk/red/wsh-vejl.htm</html:a></lit>
  
 </app>
 
 <app id="dtd">
  <rubrik>KN1 dtd</rubrik>
  <html:p>Obsolete</html:p>
  <!--synx><elem><name>supplied</name></elem></synx-->
 </app>
 
 <app id="sumeng">
  <rubrik>Summary in English</rubrik>
  <html:p>Obsolete</html:p>
 </app>

 <app id="elemindex">
  <rubrik>Element index</rubrik>
  <?elem-index?>
 </app>

 <app id="sagindex">
  <rubrik>Term index</rubrik>
  <?sag-index?>
 </app>
 </specs>
